<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE countries [
        <!ENTITY argentina SYSTEM "countries-xml/argentina-transform.xml">
        <!ENTITY cyprus SYSTEM "countries-xml/cyprus-transform.xml">
        <!ENTITY yemen SYSTEM "countries-xml/yemen-transform.xml">
        <!ENTITY nepal SYSTEM "countries-xml/nepal-transform.xml">
        ]>
<countries>
    <argentina>
        <country>
            <name>Argentina</name>
            <introduction>

                In 1816, the United Provinces of the Rio Plata declared their
                independence from Spain. After Bolivia, Paraguay, and Uruguay went
                their separate ways, the area that remained became Argentina. The
                country's population and culture were heavily shaped by immigrants
                from throughout Europe, with Italy and Spain providing the largest
                percentage of newcomers from 1860 to 1930. Up until about the
                mid-20th century, much of Argentina's history was dominated by
                periods of internal political unrest and conflict between civilian
                and military factions.
                After World War II, an era of Peronist populism and direct and
                indirect military interference in subsequent governments was
                followed by a military junta that took power in 1976. Democracy
                returned in 1983 after a failed bid to seize the Falkland Islands
                (Islas Malvinas) by force, and has persisted despite numerous
                challenges, the most formidable of which was a severe economic
                crisis in 2001-02 that led to violent public protests and the
                successive resignations of several presidents. The years 2003-15
                saw Peronist rule by Nestor and Cristina FERNANDEZ de KIRCHNER,
                whose policies isolated Argentina and caused economic stagnation.
                With the election of Mauricio MACRI in November 2015, Argentina
                began a period of reform and international reintegration.

            </introduction>
            <geography>Geography - note:
                This entry includes miscellaneous
                geographic information of significance not included
                elsewhere.
                <location>
                    Southern South America,
                    bordering the South Atlantic Ocean, between Chile and Uruguay
                </location>
                <coordinates>
                    34 00 S, 64 00 W
                </coordinates>
                <map-references>
                    South America
                </map-references>
                <area>
                    <total>2,780,400 sq km</total>
                    <land>2,736,690 sq km</land>
                    <water>43,710
                        sq km
                    </water>
                </area>
                <climate>
                    mostly temperate; arid in
                    southeast; subantarctic in southwest
                </climate>
                <natural-hazards>

                    San Miguel de Tucuman and Mendoza areas in the Andes subject to
                    earthquakes; pamperos are violent windstorms that can strike the
                    pampas and northeast; heavy flooding in some areas
                    volcanism: volcanic activity in the Andes
                    Mountains along the Chilean border; Copahue (2,997 m) last erupted
                    in 2000; other historically active volcanoes include Llullaillaco,
                    Maipo, Planchon-Peteroa, San Jose, Tromen, Tupungatito, and
                    Viedma

                </natural-hazards>
                <population-distribution>
                    one-third of the
                    population lives in Buenos Aires; pockets of agglomeration occur
                    throughout the northern and central parts of the country; Patagonia
                    to the south remains sparsely populated
                </population-distribution>
            </geography>
            <people>

                Argentina's population continues to grow but at a slower rate
                because of its steadily declining birth rate. Argentina's fertility
                decline began earlier than in the rest of Latin America, occurring
                most rapidly between the early 20th century and the 1950s, and then
                becoming more gradual. Life expectancy has been improving, most
                notably among the young and the poor. While the population under
                age 15 is shrinking, the youth cohort - ages 15-24 - is the largest
                in Argentina's history and will continue to bolster the working-age
                population. If this large working-age population is well-educated
                and gainfully employed, Argentina is likely to experience an
                economic boost and possibly higher per capita savings and
                investment. Although literacy and primary school enrollment are
                nearly universal, grade repetition is problematic and secondary
                school completion is low. Both of these issues vary widely by
                region and socioeconomic group.
                Argentina has been primarily a country of immigration for most
                of its history, welcoming European immigrants (often providing
                needed low-skilled labor) after its independence in the 19th
                century and attracting especially large numbers from Spain and
                Italy. More than 7 million European immigrants are estimated to
                have arrived in Argentina between 1880 and 1930, when it adopted a
                more restrictive immigration policy. European immigration also
                began to wane in the 1930s because of the global depression. The
                inflow rebounded temporarily following WWII and resumed its decline
                in the 1950s when Argentina's military dictators tightened
                immigration rules and European economies rebounded. Regional
                migration increased, however, supplying low-skilled workers
                escaping economic and political instability in their home
                countries. As of 2015, immigrants made up almost 5% of Argentina's
                population, the largest share in South America. Migration from
                neighboring countries accounted for approximately 80% of
                Argentina's immigrant population in 2015.
                The first waves of highly skilled Argentine emigrant workers
                headed mainly to the United States and Spain in the 1960s and
                1970s, driven by economic decline and repressive military
                dictatorships. The 2008 European economic crisis drove the return
                migration of some Argentinean and other Latin American nationals,
                as well as the immigration of Europeans to South America, where
                Argentina was a key recipient. In 2015, Argentina received the
                highest number of legal migrants in Latin America and the
                Caribbean. The majority of its migrant inflow came from Paraguay
                and Bolivia.

                <population>
                    45,479,118 (July 2020
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    32
                </population>
                <age-structure>
                    <category>0-14 years: 24.02% (male
                        5,629,188/female 5,294,723)
                    </category>
                    <category>15-24 years: 15.19% (male
                        3,539,021/female 3,367,321)
                    </category>
                    <category>25-54 years: 39.6% (male
                        9,005,758/female 9,002,931)
                    </category>
                    <category>55-64 years: 9.07% (male
                        2,000,536/female 2,122,699)
                    </category>
                    <category>65 years and over: 12.13% (male
                        2,331,679/female 3,185,262) (2020 est.)
                    </category>
                </age-structure>
                <urbanization>
                    urban population: 92.1% of total population (2020)
                    rate of urbanization: 1.07% annual rate of change (2015-20 est.)
                </urbanization>
                <distribution>
                    one-third of the
                    population lives in Buenos Aires; pockets of agglomeration occur
                    throughout the northern and central parts of the country; Patagonia
                    to the south remains sparsely populated
                </distribution>
            </people>
            <government>
                Country name: This entry includes all forms of the country's
                name approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (Italy is used as
                an example): conventional long form (Italian Republic),
                conventional short form (Italy), local long form (Repubblica
                Italiana), local short form (Italia), former (Kingdom of Italy), as
                well as the abbreviation. Also see the Terminology
                note.

                conventional long form: Argentine
                Republic
                conventional short form: Argentina
                local long form: Republica Argentina
                local short form: Argentina
                etymology: originally the area was referred
                to as Tierra Argentina, i.e., "Land beside the Silvery River" or
                "silvery land," which referred to the massive estuary in the east
                of the country, the Rio de la Plata (River of Silver); over time
                the name shortened to simply Argentina or "silvery"

                Government type:
                This entry gives the basic form of
                government. Definitions of the major governmental terms are as
                follows. (Note that for some countries more than one definition
                applies.): Absolute monarchy - a form of government where the
                monarch rules unhindered, i.e., without any laws, constitution, or
                legally organized opposition. Anarchy - a condition of lawlessness
                or political disorder brought about by the absence of governmental
                authority. Authoritarian - a form of government in whic . . .
                more


                presidential
                republic

                Capital: This entry gives the name of the seat of
                government, its geographic coordinates, the time difference
                relative to Coordinated Universal Time (UTC) and the time observed
                in Washington, DC, and, if applicable, information on daylight
                saving time (DST). Where appropriate, a special note has been added
                to highlight those countries that have multiple time
                zones.

                name: Buenos Aires
                geographic coordinates: 34 36 S, 58 22
                W
                time difference: UTC-3 (2 hours ahead of
                Washington, DC, during Standard Time)
                etymology: the
                name translates as "fair winds" in Spanish and derives from the
                original designation of the settlement that would become the
                present-day city, "Santa Maria del Buen Aire" (Saint Mary of the
                Fair Winds)

                Administrative divisions:
                This entry generally gives the
                numbers, designatory terms, and first-order administrative
                divisions as approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (BGN).
                Changes that have been reported but not yet acted on by the BGN are
                noted. Geographic names conform to spellings approved by the BGN
                with the exception of the omission of diacritical marks and special
                characters.

                23 provinces (provincias,
                singular - provincia) and 1 autonomous city*; Buenos Aires,
                Catamarca, Chaco, Chubut, Ciudad Autonoma de Buenos Aires*,
                Cordoba, Corrientes, Entre Rios, Formosa, Jujuy, La Pampa, La
                Rioja, Mendoza, Misiones, Neuquen, Rio Negro, Salta, San Juan, San
                Luis, Santa Cruz, Santa Fe, Santiago del Estero, Tierra del Fuego -
                Antartida e Islas del Atlantico Sur (Tierra del Fuego - Antarctica
                and the South Atlantic Islands), Tucuman

                note: the US does not recognize any claims to
                Antarctica


                Independence: For most countries, this entry gives the date
                that sovereignty was achieved and from which nation, empire, or
                trusteeship. For the other countries, the date given may not
                represent "independence" in the strict sense, but rather some
                significant nationhood event such as the traditional founding date
                or the date of unification, federation, confederation,
                establishment, fundamental change in the form of government, or
                state succession. For a number of countries, the establishment of
                statehood . . . more

                9 July 1816 (from
                Spain)

                National holiday:
                This entry gives the primary national
                day of celebration - usually independence day.


                Revolution Day (May
                Revolution Day), 25 May (1810)

                Constitution: This entry provides information on a country’s
                constitution and includes two subfields. The history subfield
                includes the dates of previous constitutions and the main steps and
                dates in formulating and implementing the latest constitution. For
                countries with 1-3 previous constitutions, the years are listed;
                for those with 4-9 previous, the entry is listed as “several
                previous,” and for those with 10 or more, the entry is “many
                previous.” The amendments subfield summarizes the process of am . .
                . more


                history: several previous; latest effective
                11 May 1853
                amendments: a declaration of proposed
                amendments requires two-thirds majority vote by both houses of the
                National Congress followed by approval by an ad hoc, multi-member
                constitutional convention; amended many times, last significant
                amendment in 1994 (2018)

                Legal system: This entry provides the description of a
                country's legal system. A statement on judicial review of
                legislative acts is also included for a number of countries. The
                legal systems of nearly all countries are generally modeled upon
                elements of five main types: civil law (including French law, the
                Napoleonic Code, Roman law, Roman-Dutch law, and Spanish law);
                common law (including United State law); customary law; mixed or
                pluralistic law; and religious law (including Islamic law). An
                addition . . . more

                civil law system based on
                West European legal systems; note - in mid-2015, Argentina adopted
                a new civil code, replacing the old one in force since 1871


                International law organization
                participation: This entry
                includes information on a country's acceptance of jurisdiction of
                the International Court of Justice (ICJ) and of the International
                Criminal Court (ICCt); 59 countries have accepted ICJ jurisdiction
                with reservations and 11 have accepted ICJ jurisdiction without
                reservations; 122 countries have accepted ICCt jurisdiction.
                Appendix B: International Organizations and Groups explains the
                differing mandates of the ICJ and ICCt.

                has not submitted an ICJ
                jurisdiction declaration; accepts ICCt jurisdiction

                Citizenship: This entry provides information related to the
                acquisition and exercise of citizenship; it includes four
                subfields: citizenship by birth describes the acquisition of
                citizenship based on place of birth, known as Jus soli, regardless
                of the citizenship of parents. citizenship by descent only
                describes the acquisition of citizenship based on the principle of
                Jus sanguinis, or by descent, where at least one parent is a
                citizen of the state and being born within the territorial limits
                of the s . . . more

                citizenship by birth: yes
                citizenship by descent only: yes
                dual citizenship recognized: yes
                residency requirement for naturalization: 2
                years

                Suffrage: This entry gives the age at enfranchisement and
                whether the right to vote is universal or restricted.


                18-70 years of age;
                universal and compulsory; 16-17 years of age - optional for
                national elections

                Executive branch:
                This entry includes five subentries:
                chief of state; head of government; cabinet;
                elections/appointments; election results. Chief of state includes
                the name, title, and beginning date in office of the titular leader
                of the country who represents the state at official and ceremonial
                functions but may not be involved with the day-to-day activities of
                the government. Head of government includes the name, title of the
                top executive designated to manage the executive branch of the
                government, a . . . more

                chief of state: President Alberto Angel
                FERNANDEZ (since 10 December 2019); Vice President Cristina
                FERNANDEZ DE KIRCHNER (since 10 December 2019); note - the
                president is both chief of state and head of government
                head of government: President Alberto Angel
                FERNANDEZ (since 10 December 2019); Vice President Cristina
                FERNANDEZ DE KIRCHNER (since 10 December 2019)
                cabinet: Cabinet appointed by the
                president
                elections/appointments: president and vice
                president directly elected on the same ballot by qualified majority
                vote (to win, a candidate must receive at least 45% of votes or 40%
                of votes and a 10-point lead over the second place candidate; if
                neither occurs, a second round is held ); the president serves a
                4-year term (eligible for a second consecutive term); election last
                held on 27 October 2019 (next to be held in October 2023)
                election results: Alberto Angel FERNANDEZ
                elected president; percent of vote - Alberto Angel FERNANDEZ
                (TODOS) 48.1%, Mauricio MACRI (PRO) 40.4%, Roberto LAVAGNA
                (independent) 6.2%, other 5.3%

                Legislative branch:
                This entry has three subfields. The
                description subfield provides the legislative structure (unicameral
                – single house; bicameral – an upper and a lower house); formal
                name(s); number of member seats; types of constituencies or voting
                districts (single seat, multi-seat, nationwide); electoral voting
                system(s); and member term of office. The elections subfield
                includes the dates of the last election and next election. The
                election results subfield lists percent of vote by party/coalition
                an . . . more

                description: bicameral National Congress or
                Congreso Nacional consists of:
                Senate (72 seats; members directly elected in multi-seat
                constituencies by simple majority vote to serve 6-year terms with
                one-third of the membership elected every 2 years)
                Chamber of Deputies (257 seats; members directly elected in
                multi-seat constituencies by proportional representation vote;
                members serve 4-year terms with one-half of the membership renewed
                every 2 years)
                elections:
                Senate - last held on 27 October 2019 (next to be held in October
                2021)
                Chamber of Deputies - last held on 27 October 2019 (next to be held
                in October 2021)
                election results: Senate - percent of vote
                by bloc or party - NA; seats by bloc or party - TODOS 13, Cambiemos
                8, FCS 2, JSRN 1;
                Chamber of Deputies - percent of vote by bloc or party - NA; seats
                by bloc or party - TODOS 64, Cambiemos 56, CF 3, FCS 3, JSRN 1,
                other 3

                Judicial branch:
                This entry includes three subfields.
                The highest court(s) subfield includes the name(s) of a country's
                highest level court(s), the number and titles of the judges, and
                the types of cases heard by the court, which commonly are based on
                civil, criminal, administrative, and constitutional law. A number
                of countries have separate constitutional courts. The judge
                selection and term of office subfield includes the organizations
                and associated officials responsible for nominating and appointing
                j . . . more

                highest courts: Supreme Court or Corte
                Suprema (consists of the court president, vice president, and 5
                justices)
                judge selection and term of office: justices
                nominated by the president and approved by the Senate; justices can
                serve until mandatory retirement at age 75; extensions beyond 75
                require renomination by the president and approval by the
                Senate
                subordinate courts: federal level appellate,
                district, and territorial courts; provincial level supreme,
                appellate, and first instance courts


                Political parties and
                leaders: This entry includes a
                listing of significant political parties, coalitions, and electoral
                lists as of each country's last legislative election, unless
                otherwise noted.

                Argentina Federal
                [coalition led by Pablo KOSINER]
                Cambiemos [Mauricio MACRI] (coalition of CC-ARI, PRO, and
                UCR)
                Citizen's Unity or UC [Cristina FERNANDEZ DE KIRCHNER]
                Civic Coalition ARI or CC-ARI [Elisa CARRIO, Maximiliano
                FERRARO]
                Civic Front for Santiago or FCS [Gerardo ZAMORA]
                Everyone's Front (Frente de Todos) or TODOS [Alberto Angel
                FERNANDEZ]
                Federal Consensus or CF [Roberto LAVAGNA, Juan Manuel
                URTUBEY]
                Front for the Renewal of Concord or FRC
                Front for Victory or FpV [coalition led by Cristina FERNANDEZ DE
                KIRCHNER and Agustin ROSSI]
                Generation for a National Encounter or GEN [Monica PERALTA]
                Justicialist Party or PJ [Miguel Angel PICHETTO]
                Radical Civic Union or UCR [Alfredo CORNEJO]
                Renewal Front (Frente Renovador) or FR [Sergio MASSA]
                Republican Proposal or PRO [Mauricio MACRI, Humberto
                SCHIAVONI]
                Socialist Party or PS [Antonio BONFATTI]
                Socialist Workers’ Party or PTS [Jose MONTES]
                Together We Are Rio Negro or JSRN [Alberto Edgardo
                WERETILNECK]
                We Do For Cordoba (Hacemos Por Cordoba) or HC [Juan
                SCHIARETTI]
                Workers' Party or PO [Jorge ALTAMIRA]
                Worker’s Socialist Movement or MST [Alejandro BODDART; Vilma
                RIPOLL]
                numerous provincial parties


                International organization
                participation: This entry lists
                in alphabetical order by abbreviation those international
                organizations in which the subject country is a member or
                participates in some other way.

                AfDB (nonregional member),
                Australia Group, BCIE, BIS, CAN (associate), CD, CELAC, FAO, FATF,
                G-15, G-20, G-24, G-77, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC (national
                committees), ICCt, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO,
                IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC (NGOs), LAES,
                LAIA, Mercosur, MIGA, MINURSO, MINUSTAH, NAM (observer), NSG, OAS,
                OPANAL, OPCW, Paris Club (associate), PCA, SICA (observer), UN,
                UNASUR, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNFICYP, UNHCR, UNIDO, Union Latina
                (observer), UNTSO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU (NGOs), WHO, WIPO, WMO,
                WTO, ZC


                Diplomatic representation in
                the US: This entry includes the
                chief of mission, chancery address, telephone, FAX, consulate
                general locations, and consulate locations. The use of the
                annotated title Appointed Ambassador refers to a new ambassador who
                has presented his/her credentials to the secretary of state but not
                the US president. Such ambassadors fulfill all diplomatic functions
                except meeting with or appearing at functions attended by the
                president until such time as they formally present their
                credentials at a White Hou . . . more

                Ambassador Fernando ORIS
                DE ROA (since 24 January 2018)
                chancery: 1600 New Hampshire Avenue NW,
                Washington, DC 20009
                telephone: [1] (202) 238-6400
                FAX: [1] (202) 332-3171
                consulate(s) general: Atlanta, Chicago,
                Houston, Los Angeles, Miami, New York, Washington, DC


                Diplomatic representation from
                the US: This entry includes the
                chief of mission, embassy address, mailing address, telephone
                number, FAX number, branch office locations, consulate general
                locations, and consulate locations.

                chief of mission: Ambassador Edward Charles
                PRADO (since 16 May 2018)
                telephone: [54] (11) 5777-4533
                embassy: Avenida Colombia 4300, C1425GMN
                Buenos Aires
                mailing address: international mail: use
                embassy street address; APO address: US Embassy Buenos Aires, Unit
                4334, APO AA 34034
                FAX: [54] (11) 5777-4240

                Flag description:
                This entry provides a written flag
                description produced from actual flags or the best information
                available at the time the entry was written. The flags of
                independent states are used by their dependencies unless there is
                an officially recognized local flag. Some disputed and other areas
                do not have flags.

                three equal horizontal
                bands of sky blue (top), white, and sky blue; centered in the white
                band is a radiant yellow sun with a human face (delineated in
                brown) known as the Sun of May; the colors represent the clear
                skies and snow of the Andes; the sun symbol commemorates the
                appearance of the sun through cloudy skies on 25 May 1810 during
                the first mass demonstration in favor of independence; the sun
                features are those of Inti, the Inca god of the sun

                National symbol(s):
                A national symbol is a faunal,
                floral, or other abstract representation - or some distinctive
                object - that over time has come to be closely identified with a
                country or entity. Not all countries have national symbols; a few
                countries have more than one.

                Sun of May (a
                sun-with-face symbol); national colors: sky blue, white

                National anthem:
                A generally patriotic musical
                composition - usually in the form of a song or hymn of praise -
                that evokes and eulogizes the history, traditions, or struggles of
                a nation or its people. National anthems can be officially
                recognized as a national song by a country's constitution or by an
                enacted law, or simply by tradition. Although most anthems contain
                lyrics, some do not.

                name: "Himno Nacional Argentino" (Argentine
                National Anthem)
                lyrics/music: Vicente LOPEZ y PLANES/Jose
                Blas PARERA

                note: adopted 1813; Vicente LOPEZ was inspired
                to write the anthem after watching a play about the 1810 May
                Revolution against Spain


            </government>
            <economy>

                Argentina benefits from rich natural resources, a highly
                literate population, an export-oriented agricultural sector, and a
                diversified industrial base. Although one of the world's wealthiest
                countries 100 years ago, Argentina suffered during most of the 20th
                century from recurring economic crises, persistent fiscal and
                current account deficits, high inflation, mounting external debt,
                and capital flight.
                Cristina FERNANDEZ DE KIRCHNER succeeded her husband as
                president in late 2007, and in 2008 the rapid economic growth of
                previous years slowed sharply as government policies held back
                exports and the world economy fell into recession. In 2010 the
                economy rebounded strongly, but slowed in late 2011 even as the
                government continued to rely on expansionary fiscal and monetary
                policies, which kept inflation in the double digits.
                In order to deal with these problems, the government expanded
                state intervention in the economy: it nationalized the oil company
                YPF from Spain's Repsol, expanded measures to restrict imports, and
                further tightened currency controls in an effort to bolster foreign
                reserves and stem capital flight. Between 2011 and 2013, Central
                Bank foreign reserves dropped $21.3 billion from a high of $52.7
                billion. In July 2014, Argentina and China agreed on an $11 billion
                currency swap; the Argentine Central Bank has received the
                equivalent of $3.2 billion in Chinese yuan, which it counts as
                international reserves.
                With the election of President Mauricio MACRI in November 2015,
                Argentina began a historic political and economic transformation,
                as his administration took steps to liberalize the Argentine
                economy, lifting capital controls, floating the peso, removing
                export controls on some commodities, cutting some energy subsidies,
                and reforming the country’s official statistics. Argentina
                negotiated debt payments with holdout bond creditors, continued
                working with the IMF to shore up its finances, and returned to
                international capital markets in April 2016.
                In 2017, Argentina’s economy emerged from recession with GDP
                growth of nearly 3.0%. The government passed important pension,
                tax, and fiscal reforms. And after years of international
                isolation, Argentina took on several international leadership
                roles, including hosting the World Economic Forum on Latin America
                and the World Trade Organization Ministerial Conference, and is set
                to assume the presidency of the G-20 in 2018.

                <gdp>
                    $922.1 billion (2017 est.)
                    $896.5 billion (2016 est.)
                    $913.2 billion (2015 est.)

                    note: data are in 2017 dollars

                    country comparison to the world:
                    28
                </gdp>
                <agriculture>
                    agriculture: 10.8% (2017 est.)
                    industry: 28.1% (2017 est.)
                    services: 61.1% (2017 est.)
                </agriculture>
                <industries>
                    food processing, motor
                    vehicles, consumer durables, textiles, chemicals and
                    petrochemicals, printing, metallurgy, steel
                </industries>
                <uneployment>
                    8.4% (2017 est.)
                    8.5% (2016 est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    120
                </uneployment>
                <balance>
                    -$31.32 billion (2017
                    est.)
                    -$14.69 billion (2016
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    200
                </balance>
                <budget>
                    revenues: 120.6 billion (2017 est.)
                    expenditures: 158.6 billion (2017 est.)
                </budget>
            </economy>
            <communications>
                general assessment: one of the highest
                broadband penetrations in Latin America, supported by operator
                investment and govt programs aimed at expansion; govt
                provides 20 million euros for two 5G trials, Huawei conducts
                5G trials; major networks are entirely digital and the
                availability of telephone service continues to improve to rural
                areas; Argentinians own multiple SIM cards for work and personal
                use; even with numerous providers there is a lack of
                competition for broadband and mobile services; still Argentina
                is the 3rd largest in the region after Brazil and Mexico
                (2020)
                domestic: 22 per 100 fixed-line, 131 per 100
                mobile-cellular; microwave radio relay, fiber-optic cable, and a
                domestic satellite system with 40 earth stations serve the trunk
                network (2018)
                international: country code - 54; landing
                points for the UNISUR, Bicentenario, Atlantis-2, SAm-1,
                and SAC, Tannat, Malbec and ARBR submarine cable systems
                that provide links to Europe, Africa, South and Central America,
                and US; satellite earth stations - 112 (2019)
                note: the COVID-19
                outbreak is negatively impacting telecommunications production and
                supply chains globally; consumer spending on telecom devices and
                services has also slowed due to the pandemic's effect on economies
                worldwide; overall progress towards improvements in all facets of
                the telecom industry - mobile, fixed-line, broadband, submarine
                cable and satellite - has moderated
                <static-telephones>
                    total subscriptions: 9,764,014
                    subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
                    22 (2018 est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    18
                </static-telephones>
                <mobile-phones>
                    total subscriptions: 58,598,041
                    subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
                    131 (2018
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    27
                </mobile-phones>
                <broadcast-media>
                    government owns a TV
                    station and radio network; more than 2 dozen TV stations and
                    hundreds of privately owned radio stations; high rate of cable TV
                    subscription usage
                </broadcast-media>
                <internet>
                    total: 30,786,889
                    percent of population: 70.2% (July 2016
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    24
                </internet>
            </communications>
            <military>
                The Argentine military is
                a well-organized force constrained by the country's prolonged
                economic hardship; the military is implementing a modernization
                plan aimed at making the ground forces lighter and more
                responsive.

                President Mauricio Macri in July of 2019 said he would remove a
                2006 decree that limited the armed forces to defending against
                external attacks and banned military involvement in internal
                security issues.  Macri said he wanted the military to be able
                to collaborate in internal security, primarily by providing
                logistic support in the border areas. (2018)
                <forces>

                    Armed Forces of the Argentine Republic (Fuerzas Armadas de la
                    República Argentina): Argentine Army (Ejercito Argentino), Navy of
                    the Argentine Republic (Armada Republica; includes naval aviation
                    and naval infantry), Argentine Air Force (Fuerza Aerea Argentina,
                    FAA); Ministry of Security: Gendarmerie, Prefectura Naval (coast
                    guard)
                    (2019)
                </forces>
                <obligation>
                    18-24 years of age for
                    voluntary military service (18-21 requires parental consent); no
                    conscription; if the number of volunteers fails to meet the quota
                    of recruits for a particular year, Congress can authorize the
                    conscription of citizens turning 18 that year for a period not
                    exceeding one year (2012)
                </obligation>
                <expenditures>
                    0.7% of GDP (2019)
                    0.7% of GDP (2018)
                    0.9% of GDP (2017)
                    0.8% of GDP (2016)
                    0.9% of GDP (2015)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    130
                </expenditures>
            </military>
            <transportation>

                National air transport
                system: This entry includes four
                subfields describing the air transport system of a given country in
                terms of both structure and performance. The first subfield, number
                of registered air carriers, indicates the total number of air
                carriers registered with the country’s national aviation authority
                and issued an air operator certificate as required by the
                Convention on International Civil Aviation. The second subfield,
                inventory of registered aircraft operated by air carriers, lists
                the total number . . . more

                number of registered air carriers:
                6 (2015)
                inventory of registered aircraft operated by air
                carriers: 107
                (2015)
                annual passenger traffic on registered air
                carriers: 14,245,183
                (2015)
                annual freight traffic on registered air
                carriers: 243,772,567
                mt-km (2015)


                Civil aircraft registration
                country code prefix: This entry
                provides the one- or two-character alphanumeric code indicating the
                nationality of civil aircraft. Article 20 of the Convention on
                International Civil Aviation (Chicago Convention), signed in 1944,
                requires that all aircraft engaged in international air navigation
                bear appropriate nationality marks. The aircraft registration
                number consists of two parts: a prefix consisting of a one- or
                two-character alphanumeric code indicating nationality and a
                registration suffix of one to fi . . . more

                LV (2016)

                Airports: This entry gives the total number of airports or
                airfields recognizable from the air. The runway(s) may be paved
                (concrete or asphalt surfaces) or unpaved (grass, earth, sand, or
                gravel surfaces) and may include closed or abandoned installations.
                Airports or airfields that are no longer recognizable (overgrown,
                no facilities, etc.) are not included. Note that not all airports
                have accommodations for refueling, maintenance, or air traffic
                control.

                1,138 (2013)
                country comparison to the world:
                6


                Airports - with paved
                runways: This entry gives the
                total number of airports with paved runways (concrete or asphalt
                surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one runway, only
                the longest runway is included according to the following five
                groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2) 2,438 to 3,047 m
                (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000 to 8,000 ft), (4)
                914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under 914 m (under
                3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are included in this
                listing. Not all . . . more

                total: 161 (2017)
                over 3,047 m: 4 (2017)
                2,438 to 3,047 m: 29 (2017)
                1,524 to 2,437 m: 65 (2017)
                914 to 1,523 m: 53 (2017)
                under 914 m: 10 (2017)


                Airports - with unpaved
                runways: This entry gives the
                total number of airports with unpaved runways (grass, dirt, sand,
                or gravel surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one
                runway, only the longest runway is included according to the
                following five groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2)
                2,438 to 3,047 m (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000
                to 8,000 ft), (4) 914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under
                914 m (under 3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are
                included in this listin . . . more

                total: 977 (2013)
                over 3,047 m: 1 (2013)
                2,438 to 3,047 m: 1 (2013)
                1,524 to 2,437 m: 43 (2013)
                914 to 1,523 m: 484 (2013)
                under 914 m: 448 (2013)

                Heliports: This entry gives the total number of heliports
                with hard-surface runways, helipads, or landing areas that support
                routine sustained helicopter operations exclusively and have
                support facilities including one or more of the following
                facilities: lighting, fuel, passenger handling, or maintenance. It
                includes former airports used exclusively for helicopter operations
                but excludes heliports limited to day operations and natural
                clearings that could support helicopter landings and
                takeoffs.

                2 (2013)

                Pipelines: This entry gives the lengths and types of
                pipelines for transporting products like natural gas, crude oil, or
                petroleum products.

                29930 km gas, 41 km liquid
                petroleum gas, 6248 km oil, 3631 km refined products (2013)

                Railways: This entry states the total route length of the
                railway network and of its component parts by gauge, which is the
                measure of the distance between the inner sides of the load-bearing
                rails. The four typical types of gauges are: broad, standard,
                narrow, and dual. Other gauges are listed under note. Some 60% of
                the world's railways use the standard gauge of 1.4 m (4.7 ft).
                Gauges vary by country and sometimes within countries. The choice
                of gauge during initial construction was mainly in resp . . .
                more


                total: 36,917
                km (2014)
                standard gauge: 2,745.1 km 1.435-m gauge (41.1 km electrified)
                (2014)
                narrow gauge: 7,523.3 km 1.000-m gauge (2014)
                broad gauge: 26,391 km 1.676-m gauge (149 km electrified)
                (2014)
                258 km 0.750-m gauge
                country comparison to the world:
                6

                Roadways: This entry gives the total length of the road
                network and includes the length of the paved and unpaved
                portions.

                total: 281,290
                km (2017)
                paved: 117,616
                km (2017)
                unpaved: 163,674 km (2017)
                country comparison to the world:
                21

                Waterways: This entry gives the total length of navigable
                rivers, canals, and other inland bodies of water.


                11,000 km (2012)
                country comparison to the world:
                11

                Merchant marine:
                This entry provides the total and the
                number of each type of privately or publicly owned commercial ship
                for each country; military ships are not included; the five ships
                by type include: bulk carrier - for cargo such as coal, grain,
                cement, ores, and gravel; container ship - for loads in truck-size
                containers, a transportation system called containerization;
                general cargo - also referred to as break-bulk containers - for a
                wide variety of packaged merchandise, such as textiles, furniture .
                . . more


                total: 192
                by type: bulk carrier 1, general cargo 8,
                oil tanker 30, other 153 (2019)
                country comparison to the world:
                68

                Ports and terminals:
                This entry lists major ports and
                terminals primarily on the basis of the amount of cargo tonnage
                shipped through the facilities on an annual basis. In some
                instances, the number of containers handled or ship visits were
                also considered. Most ports service multiple classes of vessels
                including bulk carriers (dry and liquid), break bulk cargoes (goods
                loaded individually in bags, boxes, crates, or drums; sometimes
                palletized), containers, roll-on/roll-off, and passenger ships. The
                listing le . . . more

                major seaport(s): Bahia Blanca, Buenos
                Aires, La Plata, Punta Colorada, Ushuaia
                container port(s) (TEUs): Buenos Aires
                (1,851,701)
                LNG terminal(s) (import): Bahia Blanca
                river port(s): Arroyo Seco, Rosario, San
                Lorenzo-San Martin (Parana)

            </transportation>
        </country>
    </argentina>
    <cyprus>
        <country>
            <name>Cyprus</name>
            <introduction>
                A former British colony,
                Cyprus became independent in 1960 following years of resistance to
                British rule. Tensions between the Greek Cypriot majority and
                Turkish Cypriot minority communities came to a head in December
                1963, when violence broke out in the capital of Nicosia. Despite
                the deployment of UN peacekeepers in 1964, sporadic intercommunal
                violence continued, forcing most Turkish Cypriots into enclaves
                throughout the island. In 1974, a Greek Government-sponsored
                attempt to overthrow the elected president of Cyprus was met by
                military intervention from Turkey, which soon controlled more than
                a third of the island. In 1983, the Turkish Cypriot administered
                area declared itself the "Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus"
                ("TRNC"), but it is recognized only by Turkey. An UN-mediated
                agreement, the Annan Plan, failed to win approval by both
                communities in 2004. In February 2014, after a hiatus of nearly two
                years, the leaders of the two communities resumed formal
                discussions under UN auspices aimed at reuniting the divided
                island. The most recent round of negotiations to reunify the island
                were suspended in July 2017 after failure to achieve a
                breakthrough. The entire island entered the EU on 1 May 2004,
                although the EU acquis - the body of common rights and obligations
                - applies only to the areas under the internationally recognized
                government, and is suspended in the "TRNC." However, individual
                Turkish Cypriots able to document their eligibility for Republic of
                Cyprus citizenship legally enjoy the same rights accorded to other
                citizens of EU states.
            </introduction>
            <geography>Geography - note:
                This entry includes miscellaneous
                geographic information of significance not included
                elsewhere.
                <location>
                    Middle East, island in the
                    Mediterranean Sea, south of Turkey; note - Cyprus views itself as
                    part of Europe; geopolitically, it can be classified as falling
                    within Europe, the Middle East, or both
                </location>
                <coordinates>
                    35 00 N, 33 00 E
                </coordinates>
                <map-references>
                    Middle East
                </map-references>
                <area>
                    <total>9,251
                        sq km
                    </total>
                    <land>9,241 sq
                        km
                    </land>
                    <water>10 sq
                        km
                    </water>
                </area>
                <climate>
                    temperate; Mediterranean
                    with hot, dry summers and cool winters
                </climate>
                <natural-hazards>
                    moderate earthquake
                    activity; droughts
                </natural-hazards>
                <population-distribution>
                    population concentrated in
                    central Nicosia and in the major cities of the south: Paphos,
                    Limassol, and Larnaca
                </population-distribution>
            </geography>
            <people>
                <population>
                    1,266,676 (July 2020
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    157
                </population>
                <age-structure>
                    <category>0-14 years: 15.69% (male
                        102,095/female 96,676)
                    </category>
                    <category>15-24 years: 12.29% (male
                        84,832/female 70,879)
                    </category>
                    <category>25-54 years: 47.12% (male
                        316,710/female 280,167)
                    </category>
                    <category>55-64 years: 11.92% (male
                        72,476/female 78,511)
                    </category>
                    <category>65 years and over: 12.97% (male
                        71,053/female 93,277) (2020 est.)
                    </category>
                </age-structure>
                <urbanization>
                    urban population: 66.8% of total population (2020)
                    rate of urbanization: 0.75% annual rate of change (2015-20 est.)
                </urbanization>
                <distribution>
                    population concentrated in
                    central Nicosia and in the major cities of the south: Paphos,
                    Limassol, and Larnaca
                </distribution>
            </people>
            <government>
                Country name: This entry includes all forms of the country's
                name approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (Italy is used as
                an example): conventional long form (Italian Republic),
                conventional short form (Italy), local long form (Repubblica
                Italiana), local short form (Italia), former (Kingdom of Italy), as
                well as the abbreviation. Also see the Terminology
                note.

                conventional long form: Republic of
                Cyprus
                conventional short form: Cyprus
                local long form: Kypriaki Dimokratia/Kibris
                Cumhuriyeti
                local short form: Kypros/Kibris
                etymology: the derivation of the name
                "Cyprus" is unknown, but the extensive mining of copper metal on
                the island in antiquity gave rise to the Latin word "cuprum" for
                copper

                note: the Turkish Cypriot community, which
                administers the northern part of the island, refers to itself as
                the "Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus" or "TRNC" ("Kuzey Kibris
                Turk Cumhuriyeti" or "KKTC")


                Government type:
                This entry gives the basic form of
                government. Definitions of the major governmental terms are as
                follows. (Note that for some countries more than one definition
                applies.): Absolute monarchy - a form of government where the
                monarch rules unhindered, i.e., without any laws, constitution, or
                legally organized opposition. Anarchy - a condition of lawlessness
                or political disorder brought about by the absence of governmental
                authority. Authoritarian - a form of government in whic . . .
                more


                Republic of Cyprus -
                presidential republic; "Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus"
                (self-declared) - parliamentary republic with enhanced
                presidency

                note: a separation of the two main ethnic
                communities inhabiting the island began following the outbreak of
                communal strife in 1963; this separation was further solidified
                when a Greek military-junta-supported coup attempt prompted the
                Turkish military intervention in July 1974 that gave the Turkish
                Cypriots de facto control in the north; Greek Cypriots control the
                only internationally recognized government on the island; on 15
                November 1983, then Turkish Cypriot "President" Rauf DENKTAS
                declared independence and the formation of the "TRNC,” which is
                recognized only by Turkey


                Capital: This entry gives the name of the seat of
                government, its geographic coordinates, the time difference
                relative to Coordinated Universal Time (UTC) and the time observed
                in Washington, DC, and, if applicable, information on daylight
                saving time (DST). Where appropriate, a special note has been added
                to highlight those countries that have multiple time
                zones.

                name: Nicosia (Lefkosia/Lefkosa)
                geographic coordinates: 35 10 N, 33 22
                E
                time difference: UTC+2 (7 hours ahead of
                Washington, DC, during Standard Time)
                daylight saving time: +1hr, begins last
                Sunday in March; ends last Sunday in October
                etymology: a
                mispronunciation of the city's Greek name Lefkosia and its Turkish
                name Lefkosa, both of which mean "White City"; the Greek name may
                derive from the Greek phrase "leuke ousia" ("white estate")

                Administrative divisions:
                This entry generally gives the
                numbers, designatory terms, and first-order administrative
                divisions as approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (BGN).
                Changes that have been reported but not yet acted on by the BGN are
                noted. Geographic names conform to spellings approved by the BGN
                with the exception of the omission of diacritical marks and special
                characters.

                6 districts; Ammochostos
                (Famagusta); (all but a small part located in the Turkish Cypriot
                community), Keryneia (Kyrenia; the only district located entirely
                in the Turkish Cypriot community), Larnaka (Larnaca; with a small
                part located in the Turkish Cypriot community), Lefkosia (Nicosia;
                a small part administered by Turkish Cypriots), Lemesos (Limassol),
                Pafos (Paphos); note - the 5 "districts" of the "TRNC" are
                Gazimagusa (Famagusta), Girne (Kyrenia), Guzelyurt (Morphou),
                Iskele (Trikomo), Lefkosa (Nicosia)

                Independence: For most countries, this entry gives the date
                that sovereignty was achieved and from which nation, empire, or
                trusteeship. For the other countries, the date given may not
                represent "independence" in the strict sense, but rather some
                significant nationhood event such as the traditional founding date
                or the date of unification, federation, confederation,
                establishment, fundamental change in the form of government, or
                state succession. For a number of countries, the establishment of
                statehood . . . more

                16 August 1960 (from the
                UK); note - Turkish Cypriots proclaimed self-rule on 13 February
                1975 and independence in 1983, but these proclamations are
                recognized only by Turkey

                National holiday:
                This entry gives the primary national
                day of celebration - usually independence day.


                Independence Day, 1
                October (1960); note - Turkish Cypriots celebrate 15 November
                (1983) as "Republic Day"

                Constitution: This entry provides information on a country’s
                constitution and includes two subfields. The history subfield
                includes the dates of previous constitutions and the main steps and
                dates in formulating and implementing the latest constitution. For
                countries with 1-3 previous constitutions, the years are listed;
                for those with 4-9 previous, the entry is listed as “several
                previous,” and for those with 10 or more, the entry is “many
                previous.” The amendments subfield summarizes the process of am . .
                . more


                history: ratified 16 August 1960; note - in
                1963, the constitution was partly suspended as Turkish Cypriots
                withdrew from the government; Turkish-held territory in 1983 was
                declared the "Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus" ("TRNC"); in
                1985, the "TRNC" approved its own constitution
                amendments: constitution of the Republic of
                Cyprus - proposed by the House of Representatives; passage requires
                at least two-thirds majority vote of the total membership of the
                "Greek Community" and the "Turkish Community"; however, all seats
                of Turkish Cypriot members have remained vacant since 1964; amended
                10 times, last in 2016
                constitution of the “Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus” -
                proposed by at least 10 members of the "Assembly of the Republic";
                passage requires at least two-thirds majority vote of the total
                Assembly membership and approval by referendum; amended 2014
                (2019)

                Legal system: This entry provides the description of a
                country's legal system. A statement on judicial review of
                legislative acts is also included for a number of countries. The
                legal systems of nearly all countries are generally modeled upon
                elements of five main types: civil law (including French law, the
                Napoleonic Code, Roman law, Roman-Dutch law, and Spanish law);
                common law (including United State law); customary law; mixed or
                pluralistic law; and religious law (including Islamic law). An
                addition . . . more

                mixed legal system of
                English common law and civil law with European law supremacy


                International law organization
                participation: This entry
                includes information on a country's acceptance of jurisdiction of
                the International Court of Justice (ICJ) and of the International
                Criminal Court (ICCt); 59 countries have accepted ICJ jurisdiction
                with reservations and 11 have accepted ICJ jurisdiction without
                reservations; 122 countries have accepted ICCt jurisdiction.
                Appendix B: International Organizations and Groups explains the
                differing mandates of the ICJ and ICCt.

                accepts compulsory ICJ
                jurisdiction with reservations; accepts ICC jurisdiction

                Citizenship: This entry provides information related to the
                acquisition and exercise of citizenship; it includes four
                subfields: citizenship by birth describes the acquisition of
                citizenship based on place of birth, known as Jus soli, regardless
                of the citizenship of parents. citizenship by descent only
                describes the acquisition of citizenship based on the principle of
                Jus sanguinis, or by descent, where at least one parent is a
                citizen of the state and being born within the territorial limits
                of the s . . . more

                citizenship by birth: no
                citizenship by descent only: at least one
                parent must be a citizen of Cyprus
                dual citizenship recognized: yes
                residency requirement for naturalization: 7
                years

                Suffrage: This entry gives the age at enfranchisement and
                whether the right to vote is universal or restricted.


                18 years of age;
                universal

                Executive branch:
                This entry includes five subentries:
                chief of state; head of government; cabinet;
                elections/appointments; election results. Chief of state includes
                the name, title, and beginning date in office of the titular leader
                of the country who represents the state at official and ceremonial
                functions but may not be involved with the day-to-day activities of
                the government. Head of government includes the name, title of the
                top executive designated to manage the executive branch of the
                government, a . . . more

                chief of state: President  Nikos
                ANASTASIADIS (since 28 February 2013); the president is both chief
                of state and head of government; note - vice presidency reserved
                for a Turkish Cypriot, but vacant since 1974 because Turkish
                Cypriots do not participate in the Republic of Cyprus
                Government
                head of government: President Nikos
                ANASTASIADIS (since 28 February 2013)
                cabinet: Council of Ministers appointed by
                the president; note - under the 1960 constitution, 3 of the
                ministerial posts reserved for Turkish Cypriots, appointed by the
                vice president; positions currently filled by Greek Cypriots
                elections/appointments: president directly
                elected by absolute majority popular vote in 2 rounds if needed for
                a 5-year term; election last held on 28 January 2018 with a runoff
                on 4 February 2018 (next to be held in February 2023)
                election results: Nikos ANASTASIADIS
                reelected president in second round; percent of vote in first round
                - Nikos ANASTASIADIS (DISY) 35.5%, Stavros MALAS (AKEL) 30.2%,
                Nicolas PAPADOPOULOS (DIKO) 25.7%, other 8.6%; percent of vote in
                second round - Nikos ANASTASIADIS 56%, Savros MALAS 44%

                note: Mustafa AKINCI assumed office as
                "president" of the "TRNC" on 30 April 2015; percent of vote in
                first round (19 April 2015) - Dervis EROGLU 28.2%, Mustafa AKINCI
                26.9%, other 44.9%; percent of vote in runoff (26 April 2015) -
                AKINCI 60.5%, EROGLU 39.5%


                Legislative branch:
                This entry has three subfields. The
                description subfield provides the legislative structure (unicameral
                – single house; bicameral – an upper and a lower house); formal
                name(s); number of member seats; types of constituencies or voting
                districts (single seat, multi-seat, nationwide); electoral voting
                system(s); and member term of office. The elections subfield
                includes the dates of the last election and next election. The
                election results subfield lists percent of vote by party/coalition
                an . . . more

                description: area under government control:
                unicameral House of Representatives or Vouli Antiprosopon (80
                seats; 56 assigned to Greek Cypriots, 24 to Turkish Cypriots, but
                only those assigned to Greek Cypriots are filled; members directly
                elected by both proportional representation and preferential vote;
                members serve 5-year terms); area administered by Turkish Cypriots:
                unicameral "Assembly of the Republic" or Cumhuriyet Meclisi (50
                seats; members directly elected to 5-year terms by proportional
                representation system using a hybrid d'Hondt method with
                voter preferences for individual candidates
                elections: area under government control:
                last held on 22 May 2016 (next to be held in May 2021); area
                administered by Turkish Cypriots: last held on 7 January 2018 (next
                to be held in 2023, unless early election called)
                election results: area under government
                control: House of Representatives - percent of vote by party - DISY
                30.7%, AKEL 25.7%, DIKO 14.5%, KS-EDEK 6.2%, SP 6% Solidarity
                Movement 5.2%, other 11.7%; seats by party - DISY 18, AKEL 16, DIKO
                9, KS-EDEK 3, Citizen's Alliance 3 (2 left the party in 2017 and
                2018 due to disagreements over the party's policy regarding the
                presidential election campaign; one joined DIKO and the other
                became an independent MP), Solidarity Movement 3, other 4; area
                administered by Turkish Cypriots: "Assembly of the Republic" -
                percent of vote by party - UBP 35.6%, CTP 20.9%, HP 17.1%, TDP
                8.6%, DP 7.8%, YDP 7%, 3%; seats by party - UBP 21, CTP 12, HP 9,
                DP 3, TDP 3, YDP 2

                Judicial branch:
                This entry includes three subfields.
                The highest court(s) subfield includes the name(s) of a country's
                highest level court(s), the number and titles of the judges, and
                the types of cases heard by the court, which commonly are based on
                civil, criminal, administrative, and constitutional law. A number
                of countries have separate constitutional courts. The judge
                selection and term of office subfield includes the organizations
                and associated officials responsible for nominating and appointing
                j . . . more

                highest courts: Supreme Court of Cyprus
                (consists of 13 judges, including the court president); note - the
                highest court in the "TRNC" is the "Supreme Court" (consists of 8
                "judges," including the "court president")
                judge selection and term of office: Republic
                of Cyprus Supreme Court judges appointed by the president of the
                republic upon the recommendation of the Supreme Court judges;
                judges can serve until age 68; "TRNC Supreme Court" judges
                appointed by the "Supreme Council of Judicature," a 12-member body
                of judges, the attorney general, appointees by the president of the
                "TRNC," and by the "Legislative Assembly," and members elected by
                the bar association; judge tenure NA
                subordinate courts: Republic of Cyprus
                district courts; Assize Courts; Administrative Court; specialized
                courts for issues relating to family, industrial disputes, the
                military, and rent control; "TRNC Assize Courts"; "district and
                family courts"


                Political parties and
                leaders: This entry includes a
                listing of significant political parties, coalitions, and electoral
                lists as of each country's last legislative election, unless
                otherwise noted.

                area under
                government control:
                Citizens' Alliance or SP [Giorgos LILLIKAS]
                Democratic Party or DIKO [Nicolas PAPADOPOULOS]
                Democratic Rally or DISY [Averof NEOPHYTOU]
                Movement of Ecologists and Environmentalists or KOP (Green party)
                [Giorgos PERDIKIS]
                I, the Citizen or EOP [Georgios KOUNTOURIS]
                Movement of Social Democrats EDEK [Marinos SIZOPOULOS]
                National Popular Front or ELAM [Christos CHRISTOU]
                Progressive Party of the Working People or AKEL (Communist party)
                [Andros KYPRIANOU]
                Solidarity Movement [Eleni THEOCHAROUS]
                United Democrats or EDI [Praxoula ANTONIADOU]
                Democratic Front or DIPA [Marios GAROYIAN]
                Animal Party Cyprus or APC [Kyriacos KYRIACOU]
                area administered by Turkish Cypriots:
                Communal Democracy Party or TDP [Cemal OZYIGIT]
                Communal Liberation Party-New Forces or TKP-YG [Mehmet
                CAKICI]
                Cyprus Socialist Party or KSP [Mehmet BIRINCI]
                Democratic Party or DP [Serdar DENKTAS]
                National Democratic Party or NDP [Buray BUSKUVUTCU]
                National Unity Party or UBP [Ersin TATAR]
                New Cyprus Party or YKP [Murat KANATLI]
                People's Party or HP [Kudret OZERSAY]
                Rebirth Party or YDP [Erhan ARIKLI]
                Republican Turkish Party or CTP [Tufan ERHURMAN]
                United Cyprus Party or BKP [Izzet IZCAN]


                International organization
                participation: This entry lists
                in alphabetical order by abbreviation those international
                organizations in which the subject country is a member or
                participates in some other way.

                Australia Group, C, CD,
                CE, EBRD, ECB, EIB, EMU, EU, FAO, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC (national
                committees), ICCt, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO,
                IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC (NGOs), MIGA,
                NAM, NSG, OAS (observer), OIF, OPCW, OSCE, PCA, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO,
                UNHCR, UNIDO, UNIFIL, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU (NGOs), WHO, WIPO, WMO,
                WTO


                Diplomatic representation in
                the US: This entry includes the
                chief of mission, chancery address, telephone, FAX, consulate
                general locations, and consulate locations. The use of the
                annotated title Appointed Ambassador refers to a new ambassador who
                has presented his/her credentials to the secretary of state but not
                the US president. Such ambassadors fulfill all diplomatic functions
                except meeting with or appearing at functions attended by the
                president until such time as they formally present their
                credentials at a White Hou . . . more

                Ambassador Marios LYSIOTIS
                (since 17 September 2018)
                chancery: 2211 R Street NW, Washington, DC
                20008
                telephone: [1] (202) 462-5772,
                462-0873
                FAX: [1] (202) 483-6710
                consulate(s) general: New York

                note: representative of the Turkish Cypriot
                community in the US is Mustafa LAKADAMYALI; office at 1667 K Street
                NW, Washington, DC; telephone [1] (202) 887-6198


                Diplomatic representation from
                the US: This entry includes the
                chief of mission, embassy address, mailing address, telephone
                number, FAX number, branch office locations, consulate general
                locations, and consulate locations.

                chief of mission: Ambassador Judith Gail
                GARBER (since 18 March 2019)
                telephone: [357] (22) 393939
                embassy: corner of Metochiou and Ploutarchou
                Streets, 2407 Engomi, Nicosia
                mailing address: P. O. Box 24536, 1385
                Nicosia
                FAX: [357] (22) 393344

                Flag description:
                This entry provides a written flag
                description produced from actual flags or the best information
                available at the time the entry was written. The flags of
                independent states are used by their dependencies unless there is
                an officially recognized local flag. Some disputed and other areas
                do not have flags.

                centered on a white field
                is a copper-colored silhouette of the island (the island has long
                been famous for its copper deposits) above two olive-green-colored,
                crossed olive branches; the branches symbolize the hope for peace
                and reconciliation between the Greek and Turkish communities

                note: one of only two national flags that uses
                a map as a design element; the flag of Kosovo is the other
                note: the "Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus"
                flag retains the white field of the Cyprus national flag but
                displays narrow horizontal red stripes positioned a small distance
                from the top and bottom edges between which are centered a red
                crescent and a red five-pointed star; the banner is modeled after
                the Turkish national flag but with the colors reversed


                National symbol(s):
                A national symbol is a faunal,
                floral, or other abstract representation - or some distinctive
                object - that over time has come to be closely identified with a
                country or entity. Not all countries have national symbols; a few
                countries have more than one.

                Cypriot mouflon (wild
                sheep), white dove; national colors: blue, white

                National anthem:
                A generally patriotic musical
                composition - usually in the form of a song or hymn of praise -
                that evokes and eulogizes the history, traditions, or struggles of
                a nation or its people. National anthems can be officially
                recognized as a national song by a country's constitution or by an
                enacted law, or simply by tradition. Although most anthems contain
                lyrics, some do not.

                name: "Ymnos eis tin Eleftherian" (Hymn to
                Liberty)
                lyrics/music: Dionysios SOLOMOS/Nikolaos
                MANTZAROS

                note: adopted 1960; Cyprus adopted the Greek
                national anthem as its own; the Turkish Cypriot community in Cyprus
                uses the anthem of Turkey


            </government>
            <economy>

                The area of the Republic of Cyprus under government control has
                a market economy dominated by a services sector that accounts for
                more than four-fifths of GDP. Tourism, finance, shipping, and real
                estate have traditionally been the most important services. Cyprus
                has been a member of the EU since May 2004 and adopted the euro as
                its national currency in January 2008.
                During the first five years of EU membership, the Cyprus economy
                grew at an average rate of about 4%, with unemployment between 2004
                and 2008 averaging about 4%. However, the economy tipped into
                recession in 2009 as the ongoing global financial crisis and
                resulting low demand hit the tourism and construction sectors. An
                overextended banking sector with excessive exposure to Greek debt
                added to the contraction. Cyprus’ biggest two banks were among the
                largest holders of Greek bonds in Europe and had a substantial
                presence in Greece through bank branches and subsidiaries.
                Following numerous downgrades of its credit rating, Cyprus lost
                access to international capital markets in May 2011. In July 2012,
                Cyprus became the fifth euro-zone government to request an economic
                bailout program from the European Commission, European Central Bank
                and the International Monetary Fund - known collectively as the
                "Troika."
                Shortly after the election of President Nikos ANASTASIADES in
                February 2013, Cyprus reached an agreement with the Troika on a $13
                billion bailout that triggered a two-week bank closure and the
                imposition of capital controls that remained partially in place
                until April 2015. Cyprus' two largest banks merged and the combined
                entity was recapitalized through conversion of some large bank
                deposits to shares and imposition of losses on bank bondholders. As
                with other EU countries, the Troika conditioned the bailout on
                passing financial and structural reforms and privatizing
                state-owned enterprises. Despite downsizing and restructuring, the
                Cypriot financial sector remains burdened by the largest stock of
                non-performing loans in the euro zone, equal to nearly half of all
                loans. Since the bailout, Cyprus has received positive appraisals
                by the Troika and outperformed fiscal targets but has struggled to
                overcome political opposition to bailout-mandated legislation,
                particularly regarding privatizations. The rate of non-performing
                loans (NPLs) is still very high at around 49%, and growth would
                accelerate if Cypriot banks could increase the pace of resolution
                of the NPLs.
                In October 2013, a US-Israeli consortium completed preliminary
                appraisals of hydrocarbon deposits in Cyprus’ exclusive economic
                zone (EEZ), which estimated gross mean reserves of about 130
                billion cubic meters. Though exploration continues in Cyprus’ EEZ,
                no additional commercially exploitable reserves have been
                identified. Developing offshore hydrocarbon resources remains a
                critical component of the government’s economic recovery efforts,
                but development has been delayed as a result of regional
                developments and disagreements about exploitation methods.

                <gdp>
                    $31.78 billion (2017 est.)
                    $30.59 billion (2016 est.)
                    $29.58 billion (2015 est.)

                    note: data are in 2017 dollars

                    country comparison to the world:
                    129
                </gdp>
                <agriculture>
                    agriculture: 2% (2017 est.)
                    industry: 12.5% (2017 est.)
                    services: 85.5% (2017 est.)
                </agriculture>
                <industries>
                    tourism, food and beverage
                    processing, cement and gypsum, ship repair and refurbishment,
                    textiles, light chemicals, metal products, wood, paper, stone and
                    clay products
                </industries>
                <uneployment>
                    11.1% (2017 est.)
                    13% (2016 est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    150
                </uneployment>
                <balance>
                    -$1.458 billion (2017
                    est.)
                    -$984 million (2016 est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    154
                </balance>
                <budget>
                    revenues: 8.663 billion (2017 est.)
                    expenditures: 8.275 billion (2017 est.)
                </budget>
            </economy>
            <communications>
                general assessment: broadband market
                steadily developing with one of the highest penetrations rates in
                the region; despite the growth of Cyprus's telecom
                sector, the market overall continues to be dominated by the
                incumbent, Cyprus Telecommunications Authority (CyTA), which is
                still fully-owned by the state, but it is losing ground to its
                competition annually; improved regulatory
                circumstances, especially in relation to network
                interconnection and access, has given competing operators
                the certainty to invest in network infrastructure, and to
                launch competing services; fiber infrastructure in the early days
                and DSL remains the dominate access platform (2020)
                domestic: fixed-line is 25 per 100, and
                 97 per 100 for mobile-cellular; open-wire, fiber-optic cable,
                and microwave radio relay (2018)
                international: country code - 357 (area
                administered by Turkish Cypriots uses the country code of Turkey -
                90); a number of submarine cables, including the SEA-ME-WE-3,
                CADMOS, MedNautilus Submarine System, POSEIDON, TE
                North/TGN-Eurasia/SEACOM/Alexandros/Medes, UGARIT, Aphrodite2,
                Hawk, Lev Submarine System, and Tamares combine to provide
                connectivity to Europe, the Middle East, Africa, Asia,
                Australia, and Southeast Asia; Turcyos-1 and Turcyos-2 submarine
                cable in Turkish North Cyprus link to Turkey; tropospheric scatter;
                satellite earth stations - 8 (3 Intelsat - 1 Atlantic Ocean and 2
                Indian Ocean, 2 Eutelsat, 2 Intersputnik, and 1 Arabsat)
                (2019)
                note: the COVID-19
                outbreak is negatively impacting telecommunications production and
                supply chains globally; consumer spending on telecom devices and
                services has also slowed due to the pandemic's effect on economies
                worldwide; overall progress towards improvements in all facets of
                the telecom industry - mobile, fixed-line, broadband, submarine
                cable and satellite - has moderated
                <static-telephones>
                    total subscriptions: 311,559
                    subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
                    25 (2018 est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    112
                </static-telephones>
                <mobile-phones>
                    total subscriptions: 1,200,378
                    subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
                    97 (2018 est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    158
                </mobile-phones>
                <broadcast-media>
                    mixture of state and
                    privately run TV and radio services; the public broadcaster
                    operates 2 TV channels and 4 radio stations; 6 private TV
                    broadcasters, satellite and cable TV services including telecasts
                    from Greece and Turkey, and a number of private radio stations are
                    available; in areas administered by Turkish Cypriots, there are 2
                    public TV stations, 4 public radio stations, and 7 privately owned
                    TV and 21 radio broadcast stations plus 6 radio and 4 TV channels
                    of local universities, plus 1 radio station of military, security
                    forces and 1 radio station of civil defense cooperation, as well as
                    relay stations from Turkey (2019)
                </broadcast-media>
                <internet>
                    total: 915,036
                    percent of population: 75.9% (July 2016
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    134
                </internet>
            </communications>
            <military>
                the United Nations
                Peacekeeping Force in Cyprus (UNICYP) was set up in 1964 to prevent
                further fighting between the Greek Cypriot and Turkish Cypriot
                communities on the island and bring about a return to normal
                conditions;  as of October 2019, the UNICYP mission consisted
                of about 1,000 personnel
                <forces>
                    Republic of Cyprus:
                    Cypriot National Guard (Ethniki Froura, EF, includes ground, naval,
                    and air elements) (2019)
                </forces>
                <obligation>
                    Cypriot National Guard
                    (CNG): 18-50 years of age for compulsory military service for all
                    Greek Cypriot males; 17 years of age for voluntary service;
                    14-month service obligation (2016)
                </obligation>
                <expenditures>
                    1.6% of GDP (2019)
                    1.8% of GDP (2018)
                    1.6% of GDP (2017)
                    1.4% of GDP (2016)
                    1.7% of GDP (2015)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    70
                </expenditures>
            </military>
            <transportation>

                National air transport
                system: This entry includes four
                subfields describing the air transport system of a given country in
                terms of both structure and performance. The first subfield, number
                of registered air carriers, indicates the total number of air
                carriers registered with the country’s national aviation authority
                and issued an air operator certificate as required by the
                Convention on International Civil Aviation. The second subfield,
                inventory of registered aircraft operated by air carriers, lists
                the total number . . . more

                number of registered air carriers:
                2 (2015)
                inventory of registered aircraft operated by air
                carriers: 6
                (2015)
                annual passenger traffic on registered air
                carriers: 23,404
                (2015)
                annual freight traffic on registered air
                carriers: 230,600
                mt-km (2015)


                Civil aircraft registration
                country code prefix: This entry
                provides the one- or two-character alphanumeric code indicating the
                nationality of civil aircraft. Article 20 of the Convention on
                International Civil Aviation (Chicago Convention), signed in 1944,
                requires that all aircraft engaged in international air navigation
                bear appropriate nationality marks. The aircraft registration
                number consists of two parts: a prefix consisting of a one- or
                two-character alphanumeric code indicating nationality and a
                registration suffix of one to fi . . . more

                5B (2016)

                Airports: This entry gives the total number of airports or
                airfields recognizable from the air. The runway(s) may be paved
                (concrete or asphalt surfaces) or unpaved (grass, earth, sand, or
                gravel surfaces) and may include closed or abandoned installations.
                Airports or airfields that are no longer recognizable (overgrown,
                no facilities, etc.) are not included. Note that not all airports
                have accommodations for refueling, maintenance, or air traffic
                control.

                15 (2013)
                country comparison to the world:
                145


                Airports - with paved
                runways: This entry gives the
                total number of airports with paved runways (concrete or asphalt
                surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one runway, only
                the longest runway is included according to the following five
                groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2) 2,438 to 3,047 m
                (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000 to 8,000 ft), (4)
                914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under 914 m (under
                3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are included in this
                listing. Not all . . . more

                total: 13 (2017)
                2,438 to 3,047 m: 7 (2017)
                1,524 to 2,437 m: 2 (2017)
                914 to 1,523 m: 3 (2017)
                under 914 m: 1 (2017)


                Airports - with unpaved
                runways: This entry gives the
                total number of airports with unpaved runways (grass, dirt, sand,
                or gravel surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one
                runway, only the longest runway is included according to the
                following five groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2)
                2,438 to 3,047 m (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000
                to 8,000 ft), (4) 914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under
                914 m (under 3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are
                included in this listin . . . more

                total: 2 (2013)
                under 914 m: 2 (2013)

                Heliports: This entry gives the total number of heliports
                with hard-surface runways, helipads, or landing areas that support
                routine sustained helicopter operations exclusively and have
                support facilities including one or more of the following
                facilities: lighting, fuel, passenger handling, or maintenance. It
                includes former airports used exclusively for helicopter operations
                but excludes heliports limited to day operations and natural
                clearings that could support helicopter landings and
                takeoffs.

                9 (2013)

                Pipelines: This entry gives the lengths and types of
                pipelines for transporting products like natural gas, crude oil, or
                petroleum products.

                0 km oil

                Roadways: This entry gives the total length of the road
                network and includes the length of the paved and unpaved
                portions.

                total: 19,901
                km (2016)
                government control: 12,901 km (includes 272 km of expressways)
                (2016)
                paved: 8,631
                km (2016)
                unpaved: 4,270
                km (2016)
                Turkish Cypriot control: 7,000 km (2011)
                country comparison to the world:
                112

                Merchant marine:
                This entry provides the total and the
                number of each type of privately or publicly owned commercial ship
                for each country; military ships are not included; the five ships
                by type include: bulk carrier - for cargo such as coal, grain,
                cement, ores, and gravel; container ship - for loads in truck-size
                containers, a transportation system called containerization;
                general cargo - also referred to as break-bulk containers - for a
                wide variety of packaged merchandise, such as textiles, furniture .
                . . more


                total: 1,039
                by type: bulk carrier 304, container ship
                190, general cargo 183, oil tanker 42, other 320 (2019)
                country comparison to the world:
                25

                Ports and terminals:
                This entry lists major ports and
                terminals primarily on the basis of the amount of cargo tonnage
                shipped through the facilities on an annual basis. In some
                instances, the number of containers handled or ship visits were
                also considered. Most ports service multiple classes of vessels
                including bulk carriers (dry and liquid), break bulk cargoes (goods
                loaded individually in bags, boxes, crates, or drums; sometimes
                palletized), containers, roll-on/roll-off, and passenger ships. The
                listing le . . . more

                major seaport(s): area under government
                control: Larnaca, Limassol, Vasilikos
                area administered by Turkish
                Cypriots: Famagusta, Kyrenia

            </transportation>
        </country>
    </cyprus>
    <yemen>
        <country>
            <name>Yemen</name>
            <introduction>

                The Kingdom of Yemen (colloquially known as North Yemen) became
                independent from the Ottoman Empire in 1918 and in 1962 became the
                Yemen Arab Republic. The British, who had set up a protectorate
                area around the southern port of Aden in the 19th century, withdrew
                in 1967 from what became the People's Republic of Southern Yemen
                (colloquially known as South Yemen). Three years later, the
                southern government adopted a Marxist orientation and changed the
                country's name to the People's Democratic Republic of Yemen. The
                massive exodus of hundreds of thousands of Yemenis from the south
                to the north contributed to two decades of hostility between the
                states. The two countries were formally unified as the Republic of
                Yemen in 1990. A southern secessionist movement and brief civil war
                in 1994 was quickly subdued. In 2000, Saudi Arabia and Yemen agreed
                to delineate their border.
                Fighting in the northwest between the government and the Huthis,
                a Zaydi Shia Muslim minority, continued intermittently from 2004 to
                2010, and then again from 2014-present. The southern secessionist
                movement was revitalized in 2007.
                Public rallies in Sana'a against then President Ali Abdallah
                SALIH - inspired by similar demonstrations in Tunisia and Egypt -
                slowly built momentum starting in late January 2011 fueled by
                complaints over high unemployment, poor economic conditions, and
                corruption. By the following month, some protests had resulted in
                violence, and the demonstrations had spread to other major cities.
                By March the opposition had hardened its demands and was unifying
                behind calls for SALIH's immediate ouster. In April 2011, the Gulf
                Cooperation Council (GCC), in an attempt to mediate the crisis in
                Yemen, proposed the GCC Initiative, an agreement in which the
                president would step down in exchange for immunity from
                prosecution. SALIH's refusal to sign an agreement led to further
                violence. The UN Security Council passed Resolution 2014 in October
                2011 calling for an end to the violence and completing a power
                transfer deal. In November 2011, SALIH signed the GCC Initiative to
                step down and to transfer some of his powers to Vice President Abd
                Rabuh Mansur HADI. Following HADI's uncontested election victory in
                February 2012, SALIH formally transferred all presidential powers.
                In accordance with the GCC Initiative, Yemen launched a National
                Dialogue Conference (NDC) in March 2013 to discuss key
                constitutional, political, and social issues. HADI concluded the
                NDC in January 2014 and planned to begin implementing subsequent
                steps in the transition process, including constitutional drafting,
                a constitutional referendum, and national elections.
                The Huthis, perceiving their grievances were not addressed in
                the NDC, joined forces with SALIH and expanded their influence in
                northwestern Yemen, which culminated in a major offensive against
                military units and rival tribes and enabled their forces to overrun
                the capital, Sanaa, in September 2014. In January 2015, the Huthis
                surrounded the presidential palace, HADI's residence, and key
                government facilities, prompting HADI and the cabinet to submit
                their resignations. HADI fled to Aden in February 2015 and
                rescinded his resignation. He subsequently escaped to Oman and then
                moved to Saudi Arabia and asked the GCC to intervene militarily in
                Yemen to protect the legitimate government from the Huthis. In
                March, Saudi Arabia assembled a coalition of Arab militaries and
                began airstrikes against the Huthis and Huthi-affiliated forces.
                Ground fighting between Huthi-aligned forces and anti-Huthi groups
                backed by the Saudi-led coalition continued through 2016. In 2016,
                the UN brokered a months-long cessation of hostilities that reduced
                airstrikes and fighting, and initiated peace talks in Kuwait.
                However, the talks ended without agreement. The Huthis and SALIH’s
                political party announced a Supreme Political Council in August
                2016 and a National Salvation Government, including a prime
                minister and several dozen cabinet members, in November 2016, to
                govern in Sanaa and further challenge the legitimacy of HADI’s
                government. However, amid rising tensions between the Huthis and
                SALIH, sporadic clashes erupted in mid-2017, and escalated into
                open fighting that ended when Huthi forces killed SALIH in early
                December 2017. In 2018, anti-Huthi forces made the most battlefield
                progress in Yemen since early 2016, most notably in Al Hudaydah
                Governorate. In December 2018, the Huthis and Yemeni Government
                participated in the first UN-brokered peace talks since 2016,
                agreeing to a limited ceasefire in Al Hudaydah Governorate and the
                establishment of a UN Mission to monitor the agreement. In April
                2019, Yemen’s parliament convened in Say'un for the first time
                since the conflict broke out in 2014. In August 2019, violence
                erupted between HADI's government and the pro-secessionist Southern
                Transition Council (STC) in southern Yemen. In November 2019,
                HADI's government and the STC signed a power-sharing agreement to
                end the fighting between them.

            </introduction>
            <geography>Geography - note:
                This entry includes miscellaneous
                geographic information of significance not included
                elsewhere.
                <location>
                    Middle East, bordering the
                    Arabian Sea, Gulf of Aden, and Red Sea, between Oman and Saudi
                    Arabia
                </location>
                <coordinates>
                    15 00 N, 48 00 E
                </coordinates>
                <map-references>
                    Middle East
                </map-references>
                <area>
                    <total>527,968
                        sq km
                    </total>
                    <land>527,968
                        sq km
                    </land>
                    <water>0 sq
                        km
                    </water>
                </area>
                <climate>
                    mostly desert; hot and
                    humid along west coast; temperate in western mountains affected by
                    seasonal monsoon; extraordinarily hot, dry, harsh desert in
                    east
                </climate>
                <natural-hazards>

                    sandstorms and dust storms in summer
                    volcanism: limited volcanic activity; Jebel at
                    Tair (Jabal al-Tair, Jebel Teir, Jabal al-Tayr, Jazirat at-Tair)
                    (244 m), which forms an island in the Red Sea, erupted in 2007
                    after awakening from dormancy; other historically active volcanoes
                    include Harra of Arhab, Harras of Dhamar, Harra es-Sawad, and Jebel
                    Zubair, although many of these have not erupted in over a
                    century

                </natural-hazards>
                <population-distribution>
                    the vast majority of the
                    population is found in the Asir Mountains (part of the larger
                    Sarawat Mountain system), located in the far western region of the
                    country
                </population-distribution>
            </geography>
            <people>
                <population>
                    29,884,405 (July 2020
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    48
                </population>
                <age-structure>
                    <category>0-14 years: 39.16% (male
                        5,711,709 /female 5,513,526)
                    </category>
                    <category>15-24 years: 21.26% (male
                        3,089,817 /female 3,005,693)
                    </category>
                    <category>25-54 years: 32.78% (male
                        4,805,059 /female 4,591,811)
                    </category>
                    <category>55-64 years: 4% (male
                        523,769 /female 623,100)
                    </category>
                    <category>65 years and over: 2.8% (male
                        366,891 /female 435,855) (2018 est.)
                    </category>
                </age-structure>
                <urbanization>
                    urban population: 37.9% of total population (2020)
                    rate of urbanization: 4.06% annual rate of change (2015-20 est.)
                </urbanization>
                <distribution>
                    the vast majority of the
                    population is found in the Asir Mountains (part of the larger
                    Sarawat Mountain system), located in the far western region of the
                    country
                </distribution>
            </people>
            <government>
                Country name: This entry includes all forms of the country's
                name approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (Italy is used as
                an example): conventional long form (Italian Republic),
                conventional short form (Italy), local long form (Repubblica
                Italiana), local short form (Italia), former (Kingdom of Italy), as
                well as the abbreviation. Also see the Terminology
                note.

                conventional long form: Republic of
                Yemen
                conventional short form: Yemen
                local long form: Al Jumhuriyah al
                Yamaniyah
                local short form: Al Yaman
                former: Yemen Arab Republic [Yemen (Sanaa)
                or North Yemen] and People's Democratic Republic of Yemen [Yemen
                (Aden) or South Yemen]
                etymology: name derivation remains unclear
                but may come from the Arab term "yumn" (happiness) and be related
                to the region's classical name "Arabia Felix" (Fertile or Happy
                Arabia); the Romans referred to the rest of the peninsula as
                "Arabia Deserta" (Deserted Arabia)

                Government type:
                This entry gives the basic form of
                government. Definitions of the major governmental terms are as
                follows. (Note that for some countries more than one definition
                applies.): Absolute monarchy - a form of government where the
                monarch rules unhindered, i.e., without any laws, constitution, or
                legally organized opposition. Anarchy - a condition of lawlessness
                or political disorder brought about by the absence of governmental
                authority. Authoritarian - a form of government in whic . . .
                more


                in transition

                Capital: This entry gives the name of the seat of
                government, its geographic coordinates, the time difference
                relative to Coordinated Universal Time (UTC) and the time observed
                in Washington, DC, and, if applicable, information on daylight
                saving time (DST). Where appropriate, a special note has been added
                to highlight those countries that have multiple time
                zones.

                name: Sanaa
                geographic coordinates: 15 21 N, 44 12
                E
                time difference: UTC+3 (8 hours ahead of
                Washington, DC, during Standard Time)
                etymology: the
                name is reputed to mean "well-fortified" in Sabaean, the South
                Arabian language that went extinct in Yemen in the 6th century
                A.D.

                Administrative divisions:
                This entry generally gives the
                numbers, designatory terms, and first-order administrative
                divisions as approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (BGN).
                Changes that have been reported but not yet acted on by the BGN are
                noted. Geographic names conform to spellings approved by the BGN
                with the exception of the omission of diacritical marks and special
                characters.

                22 governorates
                (muhafazat, singular - muhafazah); Abyan, 'Adan (Aden), Ad Dali',
                Al Bayda', Al Hudaydah, Al Jawf, Al Mahrah, Al Mahwit, Amanat al
                'Asimah (Sanaa City), 'Amran, Arkhabil Suqutra (Socotra
                Archipelago), Dhamar, Hadramawt, Hajjah, Ibb, Lahij, Ma'rib,
                Raymah, Sa'dah, San'a' (Sanaa), Shabwah, Ta'izz

                Independence: For most countries, this entry gives the date
                that sovereignty was achieved and from which nation, empire, or
                trusteeship. For the other countries, the date given may not
                represent "independence" in the strict sense, but rather some
                significant nationhood event such as the traditional founding date
                or the date of unification, federation, confederation,
                establishment, fundamental change in the form of government, or
                state succession. For a number of countries, the establishment of
                statehood . . . more

                22 May 1990 (Republic of
                Yemen was established with the merger of the Yemen Arab Republic
                [Yemen (Sanaa) or North Yemen] and the Marxist-dominated People's
                Democratic Republic of Yemen [Yemen (Aden) or South Yemen]);
                notable earlier dates: North Yemen became independent on 1 November
                1918 (from the Ottoman Empire) and became a republic with the
                overthrow of the theocratic Imamate on 27 September 1962; South
                Yemen became independent on 30 November 1967 (from the UK)

                National holiday:
                This entry gives the primary national
                day of celebration - usually independence day.


                Unification Day, 22 May
                (1990)

                Constitution: This entry provides information on a country’s
                constitution and includes two subfields. The history subfield
                includes the dates of previous constitutions and the main steps and
                dates in formulating and implementing the latest constitution. For
                countries with 1-3 previous constitutions, the years are listed;
                for those with 4-9 previous, the entry is listed as “several
                previous,” and for those with 10 or more, the entry is “many
                previous.” The amendments subfield summarizes the process of am . .
                . more


                history: adopted by referendum 16 May 1991
                (following unification); note - after the National  Dialogue
                ended in January 2015, a Constitutional Drafting Committee
                appointed by the president worked to prepare a new draft
                constitution that was expected to be put to a national referendum
                before being adopted; however, the start of the current conflict in
                early 2015 interrupted the process
                amendments: amended several times, last in
                2009

                Legal system: This entry provides the description of a
                country's legal system. A statement on judicial review of
                legislative acts is also included for a number of countries. The
                legal systems of nearly all countries are generally modeled upon
                elements of five main types: civil law (including French law, the
                Napoleonic Code, Roman law, Roman-Dutch law, and Spanish law);
                common law (including United State law); customary law; mixed or
                pluralistic law; and religious law (including Islamic law). An
                addition . . . more

                mixed legal system of
                Islamic (sharia) law, Napoleonic law, English common law, and
                customary law


                International law organization
                participation: This entry
                includes information on a country's acceptance of jurisdiction of
                the International Court of Justice (ICJ) and of the International
                Criminal Court (ICCt); 59 countries have accepted ICJ jurisdiction
                with reservations and 11 have accepted ICJ jurisdiction without
                reservations; 122 countries have accepted ICCt jurisdiction.
                Appendix B: International Organizations and Groups explains the
                differing mandates of the ICJ and ICCt.

                has not submitted an ICJ
                jurisdiction declaration; non-party state to the ICCt

                Citizenship: This entry provides information related to the
                acquisition and exercise of citizenship; it includes four
                subfields: citizenship by birth describes the acquisition of
                citizenship based on place of birth, known as Jus soli, regardless
                of the citizenship of parents. citizenship by descent only
                describes the acquisition of citizenship based on the principle of
                Jus sanguinis, or by descent, where at least one parent is a
                citizen of the state and being born within the territorial limits
                of the s . . . more

                citizenship by birth: no
                citizenship by descent only: the father must
                be a citizen of Yemen; if the father is unknown, the mother must be
                a citizen
                dual citizenship recognized: no
                residency requirement for naturalization: 10
                years

                Suffrage: This entry gives the age at enfranchisement and
                whether the right to vote is universal or restricted.


                18 years of age;
                universal

                Executive branch:
                This entry includes five subentries:
                chief of state; head of government; cabinet;
                elections/appointments; election results. Chief of state includes
                the name, title, and beginning date in office of the titular leader
                of the country who represents the state at official and ceremonial
                functions but may not be involved with the day-to-day activities of
                the government. Head of government includes the name, title of the
                top executive designated to manage the executive branch of the
                government, a . . . more

                chief of state: President Abd Rabuh Mansur
                HADI (since 21 February 2012); Vice President ALI MUHSIN al-Ahmar,
                Lt. Gen. (since 3 April 2016)
                head of government: Prime Minister Maeen Abd
                al-Malik SAEED (since 15 October 2018)
                cabinet: appointed by the president
                elections/appointments: president directly
                elected by absolute majority popular vote in 2 rounds if needed for
                a 7-year term (eligible for a second term); election last held on
                21 February 2012 (next election NA); note - a special election was
                held on 21 February 2012 to remove Ali Abdallah SALIH under the
                terms of a Gulf Cooperation Council-mediated deal during the
                political crisis of 2011; vice president appointed by the
                president; prime minister appointed by the president
                election results: Abd Rabuh Mansur HADI
                (GPC) elected as a consensus president with about 50% popular
                participation; no other candidates

                Legislative branch:
                This entry has three subfields. The
                description subfield provides the legislative structure (unicameral
                – single house; bicameral – an upper and a lower house); formal
                name(s); number of member seats; types of constituencies or voting
                districts (single seat, multi-seat, nationwide); electoral voting
                system(s); and member term of office. The elections subfield
                includes the dates of the last election and next election. The
                election results subfield lists percent of vote by party/coalition
                an . . . more

                description: bicameral Parliament or Majlis
                consists of:
                Shura Council or Majlis Alshoora (111 seats; members appointed by
                the president; member tenure NA)
                House of Representatives or Majlis al Nuwaab (301 seats; members
                directly elected in single-seat constituencies by simple majority
                vote to serve 6-year terms)
                elections:
                House of Representatives - last held on 27 April 2003 (next
                scheduled for April 2009 but postponed indefinitely)
                election results:
                percent of vote by party - GPC 58.0%, Islah 22.6%, YSP 3.8%,
                Unionist Party 1.9%, other 13.7%; seats by party - GPC 238, Islah
                46, YSP 8, Nasserist Unionist Party 3, National Arab Socialist
                Ba'ath Party 2, independent 4

                Judicial branch:
                This entry includes three subfields.
                The highest court(s) subfield includes the name(s) of a country's
                highest level court(s), the number and titles of the judges, and
                the types of cases heard by the court, which commonly are based on
                civil, criminal, administrative, and constitutional law. A number
                of countries have separate constitutional courts. The judge
                selection and term of office subfield includes the organizations
                and associated officials responsible for nominating and appointing
                j . . . more

                highest courts: Supreme Court (consists of
                the court president, 2 deputies, and nearly 50 judges; court
                organized into constitutional, civil, commercial, family,
                administrative, criminal, military, and appeals scrutiny
                divisions)
                judge selection and term of office: judges
                appointed by the Supreme Judicial Council, which is chaired by the
                president of the republic and includes 10 high-ranking judicial
                officers; judges serve for life with mandatory retirement at age
                65
                subordinate courts: appeal courts; district
                or first instance courts; commercial courts


                Political parties and
                leaders: This entry includes a
                listing of significant political parties, coalitions, and electoral
                lists as of each country's last legislative election, unless
                otherwise noted.

                General People’s Congress
                or GPC (3 factions: pro-Hadi [Abdrabbi Mansur HADI], pro-Houthi
                [Sadeq Ameen Abu RAS], pro-Saleh [Ahmed SALEH]
                National Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party [Qassem Salam SAID]
                Nasserist Unionist People's Organization [Abdulmalik
                al-MEKHLAFI]
                Southern Transitional Council or STC [Aidarus al-ZOUBAIDA]
                Yemeni Reform Grouping or Islah [Muhammed Abdallah al-YADUMI]
                Yemeni Socialist Party or YSP [Dr. Abd al-Rahman Umar
                al-SAQQAF]
                (


                International organization
                participation: This entry lists
                in alphabetical order by abbreviation those international
                organizations in which the subject country is a member or
                participates in some other way.

                AFESD, AMF, CAEU, CD, EITI
                (temporarily suspended), FAO, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICRM, IDA,
                IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM,
                IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC (NGOs), LAS, MIGA, MINURSO, MINUSMA,
                MONUSCO, NAM, OAS (observer), OIC, OPCW, UN, UNAMID, UNCTAD,
                UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNISFA, UNMIL, UNMIS, UNOCI, UNWTO, UPU, WCO,
                WFTU (NGOs), WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO


                Diplomatic representation in
                the US: This entry includes the
                chief of mission, chancery address, telephone, FAX, consulate
                general locations, and consulate locations. The use of the
                annotated title Appointed Ambassador refers to a new ambassador who
                has presented his/her credentials to the secretary of state but not
                the US president. Such ambassadors fulfill all diplomatic functions
                except meeting with or appearing at functions attended by the
                president until such time as they formally present their
                credentials at a White Hou . . . more

                Ambassador Ahmad Awadh BIN
                MUBARAK (since 3 August 2015)
                chancery: 2319 Wyoming Avenue NW,
                Washington, DC 20008
                telephone: [1] (202) 965-4760
                FAX: [1] (202) 337-2017


                Diplomatic representation from
                the US: This entry includes the
                chief of mission, embassy address, mailing address, telephone
                number, FAX number, branch office locations, consulate general
                locations, and consulate locations.

                chief of mission: Ambassador Christopher
                HENZEL (since 20 May 2019); note - the embassy closed in March
                2015; Yemen Affairs Unit currently operates out of US Embassy
                Riyadh
                telephone: US Embassy Riyadh [966]
                11-488-3800
                embassy: Sa'awan Street, Sanaa
                mailing address:
                US Embassy Riyadh

                FAX: US Embassy Riyadh [966]
                11-488-7360

                Flag description:
                This entry provides a written flag
                description produced from actual flags or the best information
                available at the time the entry was written. The flags of
                independent states are used by their dependencies unless there is
                an officially recognized local flag. Some disputed and other areas
                do not have flags.

                three equal horizontal
                bands of red (top), white, and black; the band colors derive from
                the Arab Liberation flag and represent oppression (black), overcome
                through bloody struggle (red), to be replaced by a bright future
                (white)

                note: similar to the flag of Syria, which has
                two green stars in the white band, and of Iraq, which has an Arabic
                inscription centered in the white band; also similar to the flag of
                Egypt, which has a heraldic eagle centered in the white band


                National symbol(s):
                A national symbol is a faunal,
                floral, or other abstract representation - or some distinctive
                object - that over time has come to be closely identified with a
                country or entity. Not all countries have national symbols; a few
                countries have more than one.

                golden eagle; national
                colors: red, white, black

                National anthem:
                A generally patriotic musical
                composition - usually in the form of a song or hymn of praise -
                that evokes and eulogizes the history, traditions, or struggles of
                a nation or its people. National anthems can be officially
                recognized as a national song by a country's constitution or by an
                enacted law, or simply by tradition. Although most anthems contain
                lyrics, some do not.

                name: "al-qumhuriyatu l-muttahida" (United
                Republic)
                lyrics/music: Abdullah Abdulwahab
                NOA'MAN/Ayyoab Tarish ABSI

                note: adopted 1990; the music first served as
                the anthem for South Yemen before unification with North Yemen in
                1990


            </government>
            <economy>

                Yemen is a low-income country that faces difficult long-term
                challenges to stabilizing and growing its economy, and the current
                conflict has only exacerbated those issues. The ongoing war has
                halted Yemen’s exports, pressured the currency’s exchange rate,
                accelerated inflation, severely limited food and fuel imports, and
                caused widespread damage to infrastructure. The conflict has also
                created a severe humanitarian crisis - the world’s largest cholera
                outbreak currently at nearly 1 million cases, more than 7 million
                people at risk of famine, and more than 80% of the population in
                need of humanitarian assistance.
                Prior to the start of the conflict in 2014, Yemen was highly
                dependent on declining oil and gas resources for revenue. Oil and
                gas earnings accounted for roughly 25% of GDP and 65% of government
                revenue. The Yemeni Government regularly faced annual budget
                shortfalls and tried to diversify the Yemeni economy through a
                reform program designed to bolster non-oil sectors of the economy
                and foreign investment. In July 2014, the government continued
                reform efforts by eliminating some fuel subsidies and in August
                2014, the IMF approved a three-year, $570 million Extended Credit
                Facility for Yemen.
                However, the conflict that began in 2014 stalled these reform
                efforts and ongoing fighting continues to accelerate the country’s
                economic decline. In September 2016, President HADI announced the
                move of the main branch of Central Bank of Yemen from Sanaa to Aden
                where his government could exert greater control over the central
                bank’s dwindling resources. Regardless of which group controls the
                main branch, the central bank system is struggling to function.
                Yemen’s Central Bank’s foreign reserves, which stood at roughly
                $5.2 billion prior to the conflict, have declined to negligible
                amounts. The Central Bank can no longer fully support imports of
                critical goods or the country’s exchange rate. The country also is
                facing a growing liquidity crisis and rising inflation. The private
                sector is hemorrhaging, with almost all businesses making
                substantial layoffs. Access to food and other critical commodities
                such as medical equipment is limited across the country due to
                security issues on the ground. The Social Welfare Fund, a cash
                transfer program for Yemen’s neediest, is no longer operational and
                has not made any disbursements since late 2014.
                Yemen will require significant international assistance during
                and after the protracted conflict to stabilize its economy.
                Long-term challenges include a high population growth rate, high
                unemployment, declining water resources, and severe food
                scarcity.

                <gdp>
                    $73.63 billion (2017 est.)
                    $78.28 billion (2016 est.)
                    $90.63 billion (2015 est.)

                    note: data are in 2017 dollars

                    country comparison to the world:
                    98
                </gdp>
                <agriculture>
                    agriculture: 20.3% (2017 est.)
                    industry: 11.8% (2017 est.)
                    services: 67.9% (2017 est.)
                </agriculture>
                <industries>
                    crude oil production and
                    petroleum refining; small-scale production of cotton textiles,
                    leather goods; food processing; handicrafts; aluminum products;
                    cement; commercial ship repair; natural gas production
                </industries>
                <uneployment>
                    27% (2014 est.)
                    35% (2003 est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    198
                </uneployment>
                <balance>
                    -$1.236 billion (2017
                    est.)
                    -$1.868 billion (2016
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    149
                </balance>
                <budget>
                    revenues: 2.821 billion (2017 est.)
                    expenditures: 4.458 billion (2017 est.)
                </budget>
            </economy>
            <communications>
                general assessment: due to 75% of
                population needing humanitarian assistance, and given the
                civil conflict, telecommunications services are vital but
                disrupted; mobile towers are often deliberately targeted;
                maintenance is dangerous to staff; aid organization rely on
                satellite and radio communications; scarcity of telecommunications
                equipment in rural areas (2018)
                domestic: the national network consists of
                microwave radio relay, cable, tropospheric scatter, GSM and CDMA
                mobile-cellular telephone systems; fixed-line teledensity remains
                low by regional standards at 4 per 100 but mobile cellular use
                expanding at 53 per 100 (2018)
                international: country code - 967; landing
                points for the FALCON, SeaMeWe-5, Aden-Djibouti, and the AAE-1
                international submarine cable connecting Europe, Africa, the Middle
                East, Asia and Southeast Asia; satellite earth stations - 3
                Intelsat (2 Indian Ocean and 1 Atlantic Ocean), 1 Intersputnik
                (Atlantic Ocean region), and 2 Arabsat; microwave radio relay to
                Saudi Arabia and Djibouti (2020)
                <static-telephones>
                    total subscriptions: 1,165,828
                    subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
                    4 (July 2016
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    73
                </static-telephones>
                <mobile-phones>
                    total subscriptions: 15,297,789
                    subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
                    53 (2018 est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    67
                </mobile-phones>
                <broadcast-media>
                    state-run TV with 2
                    stations; state-run radio with 2 national radio stations and 5
                    local stations; stations from Oman and Saudi Arabia can be
                    accessed
                </broadcast-media>
                <internet>
                    total: 6,732,928
                    percent of population: 24.6% (July 2016
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    64
                </internet>
            </communications>
            <military>
                <forces>
                    Land Forces (includes
                    seven Military Regional Commands, supported by Strategic Reserve
                    Units), Naval and Coastal Defense Forces (includes Navy Infantry or
                    Marine units and Coast Guard), Air and Air Defense Force (although
                    it still exists in name, in practice many of the officers and
                    soldiers in this branch have been distributed to other military
                    branches and jobs), Border Guards, Strategic Reserve Forces
                    (supports the Land Forces at the discretion of the Armed Forces
                    Commander-in-Chief and also includes a Missile Group, Presidential
                    Protection Brigades, and Special Operations Forces), Minister of
                    Defense Intelligence Authority (consists of the Department of
                    Military Intelligence [active], Department of Reconnaissance
                    [active], Department of Military Security [inactive], and the
                    Electronic Warfare Department [inactive]) (2018)
                </forces>
                <obligation>
                    18 is the legal minimum
                    age for voluntary military service; no conscription; 2-year service
                    obligation (2018)
                </obligation>
                <expenditures>
                    3.98% of GDP (2014)
                    4.08% of GDP (2013)
                    4.57% of GDP (2012)
                    4.19% of GDP (2011)

                    note - no reliable information exists following the start of
                    renewed conflict in 2015

                    country comparison to the world:
                    13
                </expenditures>
            </military>
            <transportation>

                National air transport
                system: This entry includes four
                subfields describing the air transport system of a given country in
                terms of both structure and performance. The first subfield, number
                of registered air carriers, indicates the total number of air
                carriers registered with the country’s national aviation authority
                and issued an air operator certificate as required by the
                Convention on International Civil Aviation. The second subfield,
                inventory of registered aircraft operated by air carriers, lists
                the total number . . . more

                number of registered air carriers:
                2 (2015)
                inventory of registered aircraft operated by air
                carriers: 10
                (2015)
                annual passenger traffic on registered air
                carriers: 1,387,999
                (2015)
                annual freight traffic on registered air
                carriers: 0
                mt-km (2015)


                Civil aircraft registration
                country code prefix: This entry
                provides the one- or two-character alphanumeric code indicating the
                nationality of civil aircraft. Article 20 of the Convention on
                International Civil Aviation (Chicago Convention), signed in 1944,
                requires that all aircraft engaged in international air navigation
                bear appropriate nationality marks. The aircraft registration
                number consists of two parts: a prefix consisting of a one- or
                two-character alphanumeric code indicating nationality and a
                registration suffix of one to fi . . . more

                7O (2016)

                Airports: This entry gives the total number of airports or
                airfields recognizable from the air. The runway(s) may be paved
                (concrete or asphalt surfaces) or unpaved (grass, earth, sand, or
                gravel surfaces) and may include closed or abandoned installations.
                Airports or airfields that are no longer recognizable (overgrown,
                no facilities, etc.) are not included. Note that not all airports
                have accommodations for refueling, maintenance, or air traffic
                control.

                57 (2013)
                country comparison to the world:
                83


                Airports - with paved
                runways: This entry gives the
                total number of airports with paved runways (concrete or asphalt
                surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one runway, only
                the longest runway is included according to the following five
                groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2) 2,438 to 3,047 m
                (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000 to 8,000 ft), (4)
                914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under 914 m (under
                3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are included in this
                listing. Not all . . . more

                total: 17 (2013)
                over 3,047 m: 4 (2013)
                2,438 to 3,047 m: 9 (2013)
                1,524 to 2,437 m: 3 (2013)
                914 to 1,523 m: 1 (2013)


                Airports - with unpaved
                runways: This entry gives the
                total number of airports with unpaved runways (grass, dirt, sand,
                or gravel surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one
                runway, only the longest runway is included according to the
                following five groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2)
                2,438 to 3,047 m (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000
                to 8,000 ft), (4) 914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under
                914 m (under 3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are
                included in this listin . . . more

                total: 40 (2013)
                over 3,047 m: 3 (2013)
                2,438 to 3,047 m: 5 (2013)
                1,524 to 2,437 m: 7 (2013)
                914 to 1,523 m: 16 (2013)
                under 914 m: 9 (2013)

                Pipelines: This entry gives the lengths and types of
                pipelines for transporting products like natural gas, crude oil, or
                petroleum products.

                641 km gas, 22 km liquid
                petroleum gas, 1370 km oil (2013)

                Roadways: This entry gives the total length of the road
                network and includes the length of the paved and unpaved
                portions.

                total: 71,300
                km (2005)
                paved: 6,200
                km (2005)
                unpaved: 65,100 km (2005)
                country comparison to the world:
                68

                Merchant marine:
                This entry provides the total and the
                number of each type of privately or publicly owned commercial ship
                for each country; military ships are not included; the five ships
                by type include: bulk carrier - for cargo such as coal, grain,
                cement, ores, and gravel; container ship - for loads in truck-size
                containers, a transportation system called containerization;
                general cargo - also referred to as break-bulk containers - for a
                wide variety of packaged merchandise, such as textiles, furniture .
                . . more


                total: 34
                by type: general cargo 3, oil tanker 4,
                other 27 (2019)
                country comparison to the world:
                128

                Ports and terminals:
                This entry lists major ports and
                terminals primarily on the basis of the amount of cargo tonnage
                shipped through the facilities on an annual basis. In some
                instances, the number of containers handled or ship visits were
                also considered. Most ports service multiple classes of vessels
                including bulk carriers (dry and liquid), break bulk cargoes (goods
                loaded individually in bags, boxes, crates, or drums; sometimes
                palletized), containers, roll-on/roll-off, and passenger ships. The
                listing le . . . more

                major seaport(s): Aden, Al Hudaydah, Al
                Mukalla

            </transportation>
        </country>
    </yemen>
    <nepal>
        <country>
            <name>Nepal</name>
            <introduction>

                During the late 18th-early 19th centuries, the principality of
                Gorkha united many of the other principalities and states of the
                sub-Himalayan region into a Nepali Kingdom. Nepal retained its
                independence following the Anglo-Nepalese War of 1814-16 and the
                subsequent peace treaty laid the foundations for two centuries of
                amicable relations between Britain and Nepal. (The Brigade of
                Gurkhas continues to serve in the British Army to the present day.)
                In 1951, the Nepali monarch ended the century-old system of rule by
                hereditary premiers and instituted a cabinet system that brought
                political parties into the government. That arrangement lasted
                until 1960, when political parties were again banned, but was
                reinstated in 1990 with the establishment of a multiparty democracy
                within the framework of a constitutional monarchy.
                An insurgency led by Maoists broke out in 1996. During the
                ensuing 10-year civil war between Maoist and government forces, the
                monarchy dissolved the cabinet and parliament and re-assumed
                absolute power in 2002, after the crown prince massacred the royal
                family in 2001. A peace accord in 2006 led to the promulgation of
                an interim constitution in 2007. Following a nationwide Constituent
                Assembly (CA) election in 2008, the newly formed CA declared Nepal
                a federal democratic republic, abolished the monarchy, and elected
                the country's first president. After the CA failed to draft a
                constitution by a 2012 deadline set by the Supreme Court,
                then-Prime Minister Baburam BHATTARAI dissolved the CA. Months of
                negotiations ensued until 2013 when the major political parties
                agreed to create an interim government headed by then-Chief Justice
                Khil Raj REGMI with a mandate to hold elections for a new CA.
                Elections were held in 2013, in which the Nepali Congress (NC) won
                the largest share of seats in the CA and in 2014 formed a coalition
                government with the second-place Communist Party of Nepal-Unified
                Marxist-Leninist (UML) with NC President Sushil KOIRALA serving as
                prime minister. Nepal's new constitution came into effect in 2015,
                at which point the CA became the Parliament. Khagda Prasad Sharma
                OLI served as the first post-constitution prime minister from 2015
                to 2016. OLI resigned ahead of a no-confidence motion against him,
                and Parliament elected Communist Party of Nepal-Maoist (CPN-M)
                leader Pushpa Kamal DAHAL (aka "Prachanda") prime minister. The
                constitution provided for a transitional period during which three
                sets of elections – local, provincial, and national – needed to
                take place. The first local elections in 20 years occurred in three
                phases between May and September 2017, and state and federal
                elections proceeded in two phases in November and December 2017.
                The parties headed by OLI and DAHAL ran in coalition and swept the
                parliamentary elections, and OLI, who led the larger of the two
                parties, was sworn in as prime minister in February 2018. In May
                2018, OLI and DAHAL announced the merger of their parties - the UML
                and CPN-M - to establish the Nepal Communist Party (NCP), which is
                now the ruling party in Parliament.
                 

            </introduction>
            <geography>Geography - note:
                This entry includes miscellaneous
                geographic information of significance not included
                elsewhere.
                <location>
                    Southern Asia, between
                    China and India
                </location>
                <coordinates>
                    28 00 N, 84 00 E
                </coordinates>
                <map-references>
                    Asia
                </map-references>
                <area>
                    <total>147,181
                        sq km
                    </total>
                    <land>143,351
                        sq km
                    </land>
                    <water>3,830
                        sq km
                    </water>
                </area>
                <climate>
                    varies from cool summers
                    and severe winters in north to subtropical summers and mild winters
                    in south
                </climate>
                <natural-hazards>
                    severe thunderstorms;
                    flooding; landslides; drought and famine depending on the timing,
                    intensity, and duration of the summer monsoons
                </natural-hazards>
                <population-distribution>
                    most of the population is
                    divided nearly equally between a concentration in the southern-most
                    plains of the Tarai region and the central hilly region; overall
                    density is quite low
                </population-distribution>
            </geography>
            <people>
                <population>
                    30,327,877 (July 2020
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    46
                </population>
                <age-structure>
                    <category>0-14 years: 28.36% (male
                        4,526,786/female 4,073,642)
                    </category>
                    <category>15-24 years: 20.93% (male
                        3,276,431/female 3,070,843)
                    </category>
                    <category>25-54 years: 38.38% (male
                        5,251,553/female 6,387,365)
                    </category>
                    <category>55-64 years: 6.64% (male
                        954,836/female 1,059,360)
                    </category>
                    <category>65 years and over: 5.69% (male
                        852,969/female 874,092) (2020 est.)
                    </category>
                </age-structure>
                <urbanization>
                    urban population: 20.6% of total population (2020)
                    rate of urbanization: 3.15% annual rate of change (2015-20 est.)
                </urbanization>
                <distribution>
                    most of the population is
                    divided nearly equally between a concentration in the southern-most
                    plains of the Tarai region and the central hilly region; overall
                    density is quite low
                </distribution>
            </people>
            <government>
                Country name: This entry includes all forms of the country's
                name approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (Italy is used as
                an example): conventional long form (Italian Republic),
                conventional short form (Italy), local long form (Repubblica
                Italiana), local short form (Italia), former (Kingdom of Italy), as
                well as the abbreviation. Also see the Terminology
                note.

                conventional long form: Federal Democratic
                Republic of Nepal
                conventional short form: Nepal
                local long form: Sanghiya Loktantrik
                Ganatantra Nepal
                local short form: Nepal
                etymology: the Newar people of the Kathmandu
                Valley and surrounding areas apparently gave their name to the
                country; the terms "Nepal," "Newar," "Nepar," and "Newal" are
                phonetically different forms of the same word

                Government type:
                This entry gives the basic form of
                government. Definitions of the major governmental terms are as
                follows. (Note that for some countries more than one definition
                applies.): Absolute monarchy - a form of government where the
                monarch rules unhindered, i.e., without any laws, constitution, or
                legally organized opposition. Anarchy - a condition of lawlessness
                or political disorder brought about by the absence of governmental
                authority. Authoritarian - a form of government in whic . . .
                more


                federal parliamentary
                republic

                Capital: This entry gives the name of the seat of
                government, its geographic coordinates, the time difference
                relative to Coordinated Universal Time (UTC) and the time observed
                in Washington, DC, and, if applicable, information on daylight
                saving time (DST). Where appropriate, a special note has been added
                to highlight those countries that have multiple time
                zones.

                name: Kathmandu
                geographic coordinates: 27 43 N, 85 19
                E
                time difference: UTC+5.75 (10.75 hours ahead
                of Washington, DC, during Standard Time)
                etymology: name
                derives from the Kasthamandap temple that stood in Durbar Square;
                in Sanskrit, "kastha" means "wood" and "mandapa" means "pavilion";
                the three-story structure was made entirely of wood, without iron
                nails or supports, and dated to the late 16th century; it collapsed
                during a 2015 earthquake

                Administrative divisions:
                This entry generally gives the
                numbers, designatory terms, and first-order administrative
                divisions as approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (BGN).
                Changes that have been reported but not yet acted on by the BGN are
                noted. Geographic names conform to spellings approved by the BGN
                with the exception of the omission of diacritical marks and special
                characters.

                7 provinces; Gandaki
                Pradesh, Karnali Pradesh, Province No. One, Province No. Two,
                Province No. Three, Province No. Five, Sudurpashchim Pradesh

                Independence: For most countries, this entry gives the date
                that sovereignty was achieved and from which nation, empire, or
                trusteeship. For the other countries, the date given may not
                represent "independence" in the strict sense, but rather some
                significant nationhood event such as the traditional founding date
                or the date of unification, federation, confederation,
                establishment, fundamental change in the form of government, or
                state succession. For a number of countries, the establishment of
                statehood . . . more

                1768 (unified by Prithvi
                Narayan SHAH)

                National holiday:
                This entry gives the primary national
                day of celebration - usually independence day.


                Constitution Day, 20
                September (2015); note - marks the promulgation of Nepal’s
                constitution in 2015 and replaces the previous 28 May Republic Day
                as the official national day in Nepal; the Gregorian day fluctuates
                based on Nepal’s Hindu calendar

                Constitution: This entry provides information on a country’s
                constitution and includes two subfields. The history subfield
                includes the dates of previous constitutions and the main steps and
                dates in formulating and implementing the latest constitution. For
                countries with 1-3 previous constitutions, the years are listed;
                for those with 4-9 previous, the entry is listed as “several
                previous,” and for those with 10 or more, the entry is “many
                previous.” The amendments subfield summarizes the process of am . .
                . more


                history: several previous; latest approved
                by the Second Constituent Assembly 16 September 2015, signed by the
                president and effective 20 September 2015
                amendments: proposed as a bill by either
                house of the Federal Parliament; bills affecting a state border or
                powers delegated to a state must be submitted to the affected state
                assembly; passage of such bills requires a majority vote of that
                state assembly membership; bills not requiring state assembly
                consent require at least two-thirds majority vote by the membership
                of both houses of the Federal Parliament; parts of the constitution
                on the sovereignty, territorial integrity, independence, and
                sovereignty vested in the people cannot be amended; last amended
                2016 (2019)

                Legal system: This entry provides the description of a
                country's legal system. A statement on judicial review of
                legislative acts is also included for a number of countries. The
                legal systems of nearly all countries are generally modeled upon
                elements of five main types: civil law (including French law, the
                Napoleonic Code, Roman law, Roman-Dutch law, and Spanish law);
                common law (including United State law); customary law; mixed or
                pluralistic law; and religious law (including Islamic law). An
                addition . . . more

                English common law and
                Hindu legal concepts; note - new criminal and civil codes came
                into effect on 17 August 2018


                International law organization
                participation: This entry
                includes information on a country's acceptance of jurisdiction of
                the International Court of Justice (ICJ) and of the International
                Criminal Court (ICCt); 59 countries have accepted ICJ jurisdiction
                with reservations and 11 have accepted ICJ jurisdiction without
                reservations; 122 countries have accepted ICCt jurisdiction.
                Appendix B: International Organizations and Groups explains the
                differing mandates of the ICJ and ICCt.

                has not submitted an ICJ
                jurisdiction declaration; non-party state to the ICCt

                Citizenship: This entry provides information related to the
                acquisition and exercise of citizenship; it includes four
                subfields: citizenship by birth describes the acquisition of
                citizenship based on place of birth, known as Jus soli, regardless
                of the citizenship of parents. citizenship by descent only
                describes the acquisition of citizenship based on the principle of
                Jus sanguinis, or by descent, where at least one parent is a
                citizen of the state and being born within the territorial limits
                of the s . . . more

                citizenship by birth: yes
                citizenship by descent only: yes
                dual citizenship recognized: no
                residency requirement for naturalization: 15
                years

                Suffrage: This entry gives the age at enfranchisement and
                whether the right to vote is universal or restricted.


                18 years of age;
                universal

                Executive branch:
                This entry includes five subentries:
                chief of state; head of government; cabinet;
                elections/appointments; election results. Chief of state includes
                the name, title, and beginning date in office of the titular leader
                of the country who represents the state at official and ceremonial
                functions but may not be involved with the day-to-day activities of
                the government. Head of government includes the name, title of the
                top executive designated to manage the executive branch of the
                government, a . . . more

                chief of state: President Bidhya Devi
                BHANDARI (since October 2015)
                head of government: Prime Minister Khadga
                Prasad (KP) Sharma OLI (since 15 February 2018); deputy prime
                ministers Ishwar POKHREL, Upendra YADAV (since 1 June 2018)
                (an)
                cabinet: Council of Ministers appointed by
                the prime minister; cabinet dominated by the Nepal Communist
                Party
                elections/appointments: president indirectly
                elected by an electoral college of the Federal Parliament and of
                the state assemblies for a 5-year term (eligible for a second
                term); election last held 13 March 2018 (next to be held in 2023);
                prime minister indirectly elected by the Federal Parliament
                election results: Bidhya Devi BHANDARI
                reelected president; electoral vote - Bidhya Devi BHANDARI
                (CPN-UML) 39,275, Kumari Laxmi RAI (NC) 11,730
                head of state: President Bidhya Devi
                BHANDARI (since 29 October 2015); Vice President Nanda Bahadar PUN
                (since 31 October 2015)

                Legislative branch:
                This entry has three subfields. The
                description subfield provides the legislative structure (unicameral
                – single house; bicameral – an upper and a lower house); formal
                name(s); number of member seats; types of constituencies or voting
                districts (single seat, multi-seat, nationwide); electoral voting
                system(s); and member term of office. The elections subfield
                includes the dates of the last election and next election. The
                election results subfield lists percent of vote by party/coalition
                an . . . more

                description: bicameral Federal Parliament
                consists of:
                National Assembly (59 seats; 56 members, including at least 3
                women, 1 Dalit, 1 member with disabilities, or 1 minority
                indirectly elected by an electoral college of state and municipal
                government leaders, and 3 members, including 1 woman, nominated by
                the president of Nepal on the recommendation of the government;
                members serve 6-year terms with renewal of one-third of the
                membership every 2 years)
                House of Representatives (275 seats; 165 members directly elected
                in single-seat constituencies by simple majority vote and 110
                members directly elected in a single nationwide constituency by
                party-list proportional representation vote; members serve 5-year
                terms)
                elections:
                first election for the National Assembly held on 7 February 2018
                (next to be held in 2024)
                first election for House of Representatives held on 26 November and
                7 December 2017 (next to be held in 2022)
                election results:
                National Assembly - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party -
                NCP 42, NC 13, FSFN 2, RJPN 2; composition - men 37, women 22,
                percent of women 37.3%
                House of Representatives - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by
                party - NCP 174, NC 63, RJPN 17, FSFN 16, other 4, independent 1;
                composition - men 185, women 90, percent of women 32.7%; note -
                total Federal Parliament percent of women 33.5%

                Judicial branch:
                This entry includes three subfields.
                The highest court(s) subfield includes the name(s) of a country's
                highest level court(s), the number and titles of the judges, and
                the types of cases heard by the court, which commonly are based on
                civil, criminal, administrative, and constitutional law. A number
                of countries have separate constitutional courts. The judge
                selection and term of office subfield includes the organizations
                and associated officials responsible for nominating and appointing
                j . . . more

                highest courts: Supreme Court (consists of
                the chief justice and up to 20 judges)
                judge selection and term of office: Supreme
                Court chief justice appointed by the president upon the
                recommendation of the Constitutional Council, a 5-member,
                high-level advisory body headed by the prime minister; other judges
                appointed by the president upon the recommendation of the Judicial
                Council, a 5-member advisory body headed by the chief justice; the
                chief justice serves a 6-year term; judges serve until age 65
                subordinate courts: High Court; district
                courts


                Political parties and
                leaders: This entry includes a
                listing of significant political parties, coalitions, and electoral
                lists as of each country's last legislative election, unless
                otherwise noted.


                the Election Commission of Nepal granted ballot access under the
                proportional system to 88 political parties for the
                November-December 2017 House of Representatives election to the
                Federal Parliament; of these, the following 8 parties won
                seats:
                Federal Socialist Forum, Nepal or FSFN [Upendra YADAV]
                Naya Shakti Party, Nepal [Baburam BHATTARAI]
                Nepal Communist Party or NCP [Khadga Prasad OLI, Pushpa
                Kamal DAHAL]
                Nepali Congress or NC [Sher Bahadur DEUBA]
                Nepal Mazdoor Kisan Party [Narayan Man BIJUKCHHE]
                Rastriya Janamorcha [Chitra Bahadur K.C.]
                Rastriya Janata Party or RJPN [Mahanta THAKUR]
                Rastriya Prajatantra party or RPP [Kamal THAPA]


                International organization
                participation: This entry lists
                in alphabetical order by abbreviation those international
                organizations in which the subject country is a member or
                participates in some other way.

                ADB, BIMSTEC, CD, CP, FAO,
                G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC (NGOs), ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS,
                ILO, IMF, IMO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC
                (NGOs), MIGA, MINURSO, MINUSMA, MINUSTAH, MONUSCO, NAM, OPCW,
                SAARC, SACEP, UN, UNAMID, UNCTAD, UNDOF, UNESCO, UNIDO, UNIFIL,
                UNMIL, UNMISS, UNOCI, UNTSO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU (NGOs), WHO,
                WIPO, WMO, WTO


                Diplomatic representation in
                the US: This entry includes the
                chief of mission, chancery address, telephone, FAX, consulate
                general locations, and consulate locations. The use of the
                annotated title Appointed Ambassador refers to a new ambassador who
                has presented his/her credentials to the secretary of state but not
                the US president. Such ambassadors fulfill all diplomatic functions
                except meeting with or appearing at functions attended by the
                president until such time as they formally present their
                credentials at a White Hou . . . more

                Ambassador Arjun Kumar
                KARKI (since 18 May 2015)
                chancery: 2730 34th Place NW, Washington, DC
                20007
                telephone: [1] (202) 667-4550
                FAX: [1] (202) 667-5534
                consulate(s) general: Chicago (IL), New
                York


                Diplomatic representation from
                the US: This entry includes the
                chief of mission, embassy address, mailing address, telephone
                number, FAX number, branch office locations, consulate general
                locations, and consulate locations.

                chief of mission: Ambassador Randy BERRY
                (since 25 October 2018)
                telephone: [977] (1) 423-4000
                embassy: Maharajgunj, Kathmandu, Nepal
                mailing address: US Embassy, Maharajgunj
                Chakrapath, Kathmandu, Nepal 44600
                FAX: [977] (1) 400-7272

                Flag description:
                This entry provides a written flag
                description produced from actual flags or the best information
                available at the time the entry was written. The flags of
                independent states are used by their dependencies unless there is
                an officially recognized local flag. Some disputed and other areas
                do not have flags.

                crimson red with a blue
                border around the unique shape of two overlapping right triangles;
                the smaller, upper triangle bears a white stylized moon and the
                larger, lower triangle displays a white 12-pointed sun; the color
                red represents the rhododendron (Nepal's national flower) and is a
                sign of victory and bravery, the blue border signifies peace and
                harmony; the two right triangles are a combination of two single
                pennons (pennants) that originally symbolized the Himalaya
                Mountains while their charges represented the families of the king
                (upper) and the prime minister, but today they are understood to
                denote Hinduism and Buddhism, the country's two main religions; the
                moon represents the serenity of the Nepalese people and the shade
                and cool weather in the Himalayas, while the sun depicts the heat
                and higher temperatures of the lower parts of Nepal; the moon and
                the sun are also said to express the hope that the nation will
                endure as long as these heavenly bodies

                note: Nepal is the only country in the world
                whose flag is not rectangular or square


                National symbol(s):
                A national symbol is a faunal,
                floral, or other abstract representation - or some distinctive
                object - that over time has come to be closely identified with a
                country or entity. Not all countries have national symbols; a few
                countries have more than one.

                rhododendron blossom;
                national color: red

                National anthem:
                A generally patriotic musical
                composition - usually in the form of a song or hymn of praise -
                that evokes and eulogizes the history, traditions, or struggles of
                a nation or its people. National anthems can be officially
                recognized as a national song by a country's constitution or by an
                enacted law, or simply by tradition. Although most anthems contain
                lyrics, some do not.

                name: "Sayaun Thunga Phool Ka" (Hundreds of
                Flowers)
                lyrics/music: Pradeep Kumar RAI/Ambar
                GURUNG

                note: adopted 2007; after the abolition of the
                monarchy in 2006, a new anthem was required because of the previous
                anthem's praise for the king


            </government>
            <economy>

                Nepal is among the least developed countries in the world, with
                about one-quarter of its population living below the poverty line.
                Nepal is heavily dependent on remittances, which amount to as much
                as 30% of GDP. Agriculture is the mainstay of the economy,
                providing a livelihood for almost two-thirds of the population but
                accounting for less than a third of GDP. Industrial activity mainly
                involves the processing of agricultural products, including pulses,
                jute, sugarcane, tobacco, and grain.
                Nepal has considerable scope for exploiting its potential in
                hydropower, with an estimated 42,000 MW of commercially feasible
                capacity. Nepal has signed trade and investment agreements with
                India, China, and other countries, but political uncertainty and a
                difficult business climate have hampered foreign investment. The
                United States and Nepal signed a $500 million Millennium Challenge
                Corporation Compact in September 2017 which will expand Nepal’s
                electricity infrastructure and help maintain transportation
                infrastructure.
                Massive earthquakes struck Nepal in early 2015, which damaged or
                destroyed infrastructure and homes and set back economic
                development. Although political gridlock and lack of capacity have
                hindered post-earthquake recovery, government-led reconstruction
                efforts have progressively picked up speed, although many hard hit
                areas still have seen little assistance. Additional challenges to
                Nepal's growth include its landlocked geographic location,
                inconsistent electricity supply, and underdeveloped transportation
                infrastructure.

                <gdp>
                    $79.19 billion (2017 est.)
                    $73.39 billion (2016 est.)
                    $72.96 billion (2015 est.)

                    note: data are in 2017 dollars

                    country comparison to the world:
                    95
                </gdp>
                <agriculture>
                    agriculture: 27% (2017 est.)
                    industry: 13.5% (2017 est.)
                    services: 59.5% (2017 est.)
                </agriculture>
                <industries>
                    tourism, carpets,
                    textiles; small rice, jute, sugar, and oilseed mills; cigarettes,
                    cement and brick production
                </industries>
                <uneployment>
                    3% (2017 est.)
                    3.2% (2016 est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    36
                </uneployment>
                <balance>
                    -$93 million (2017 est.)
                    $1.339 billion (2016 est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    84
                </balance>
                <budget>
                    revenues: 5.925 billion (2017 est.)
                    expenditures: 5.945 billion (2017 est.)
                </budget>
            </economy>
            <communications>
                general assessment: mountainous topography
                hinders development of telecom infrastructure; mobile service
                has been extended to all 75 districts covering 90% of Nepal’s land
                area; fixed broadband is low due to limited number of fixed lines
                and preeminence of the mobile platform, with overall penetration
                2.8%; 3G and 4G subscribers, early stages for mobile broadband
                market; first launch of a Nepalese satellite (2020)
                domestic: 3G coverage is available in 20
                major cities (2019); disparity between high coverage in cities and
                coverage available in underdeveloped rural regions; fixed-line 3
                per 100 persons and mobile-cellular 132 per 100 persons; fair
                radiotelephone communication service; 20% of the market share is
                fixed (wired) broadband, 2% is fixed (wireless) broadband, and 78%
                is mobile broadband (2019)
                international: country code - 977; Nepal,
                China and Tibet connected across borders with underground and
                all-dielectric self-supporting (ADSS) fiber-optic cables;
                radiotelephone communications; microwave and fiber landlines to
                India; satellite earth station - 1 Intelsat (Indian Ocean)
                (2019)
                the COVID-19 outbreak is negatively
                impacting telecommunications production and supply chains globally;
                consumer spending on telecom devices and services has also slowed
                due to the pandemic's effect on economies worldwide; overall
                progress towards improvements in all facets of the telecom industry
                - mobile, fixed-line, broadband, submarine cable and satellite -
                has moderated
                <static-telephones>
                    total subscriptions: 799,368
                    subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
                    3 (2018 est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    82
                </static-telephones>
                <mobile-phones>
                    total subscriptions: 39,178,451
                    subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
                    132 (2018
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    38
                </mobile-phones>
                <broadcast-media>
                    state operates 3 TV
                    stations, as well as national and regional radio stations; 117
                    television channels are licensed, among those 71 are cable
                    television channels, three are distributed
                    through Direct-To-Home (DTH) system, and four are digital
                    terrestrial; 736 FM radio stations are licensed and at least
                    314 of those radio stations are community radio stations
                    (2019)
                </broadcast-media>
                <internet>
                    total: 5,716,419
                    percent of population: 19.7% (July 2016
                    est.)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    69
                </internet>
            </communications>
            <military>
                <forces>
                    Nepal Army (includes Air
                    Wing); Nepal Armed Police Force (under the Ministry of Home
                    Affairs; paramilitary force responsible for border and internal
                    security, including counter-insurgency, and assisting the Army in
                    the event of an external invasion) (2019)
                </forces>
                <obligation>
                    18 years of age for
                    voluntary military service (including women); no conscription
                    (2019)
                </obligation>
                <expenditures>
                    1.6% of GDP (2019)
                    1.6% of GDP (2018)
                    1.7% of GDP (2017)
                    1.7% of GDP (2016)
                    1.6% of GDP (2015)
                    country comparison to the world:
                    75
                </expenditures>
            </military>
            <transportation>

                National air transport
                system: This entry includes four
                subfields describing the air transport system of a given country in
                terms of both structure and performance. The first subfield, number
                of registered air carriers, indicates the total number of air
                carriers registered with the country’s national aviation authority
                and issued an air operator certificate as required by the
                Convention on International Civil Aviation. The second subfield,
                inventory of registered aircraft operated by air carriers, lists
                the total number . . . more

                number of registered air carriers:
                4 (2015)
                inventory of registered aircraft operated by air
                carriers: 15
                (2015)
                annual passenger traffic on registered air
                carriers: 510,341
                (2015)
                annual freight traffic on registered air
                carriers: 4,536,371
                mt-km (2015)


                Civil aircraft registration
                country code prefix: This entry
                provides the one- or two-character alphanumeric code indicating the
                nationality of civil aircraft. Article 20 of the Convention on
                International Civil Aviation (Chicago Convention), signed in 1944,
                requires that all aircraft engaged in international air navigation
                bear appropriate nationality marks. The aircraft registration
                number consists of two parts: a prefix consisting of a one- or
                two-character alphanumeric code indicating nationality and a
                registration suffix of one to fi . . . more

                9N (2016)

                Airports: This entry gives the total number of airports or
                airfields recognizable from the air. The runway(s) may be paved
                (concrete or asphalt surfaces) or unpaved (grass, earth, sand, or
                gravel surfaces) and may include closed or abandoned installations.
                Airports or airfields that are no longer recognizable (overgrown,
                no facilities, etc.) are not included. Note that not all airports
                have accommodations for refueling, maintenance, or air traffic
                control.

                47 (2013)
                country comparison to the world:
                92


                Airports - with paved
                runways: This entry gives the
                total number of airports with paved runways (concrete or asphalt
                surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one runway, only
                the longest runway is included according to the following five
                groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2) 2,438 to 3,047 m
                (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000 to 8,000 ft), (4)
                914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under 914 m (under
                3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are included in this
                listing. Not all . . . more

                total: 11 (2017)
                over 3,047 m: 1 (2017)
                1,524 to 2,437 m: 3 (2017)
                914 to 1,523 m: 6 (2017)
                under 914 m: 1 (2017)


                Airports - with unpaved
                runways: This entry gives the
                total number of airports with unpaved runways (grass, dirt, sand,
                or gravel surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one
                runway, only the longest runway is included according to the
                following five groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2)
                2,438 to 3,047 m (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000
                to 8,000 ft), (4) 914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under
                914 m (under 3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are
                included in this listin . . . more

                total: 36 (2013)
                1,524 to 2,437 m: 1 (2013)
                914 to 1,523 m: 6 (2013)
                under 914 m: 29 (2013)

                Railways: This entry states the total route length of the
                railway network and of its component parts by gauge, which is the
                measure of the distance between the inner sides of the load-bearing
                rails. The four typical types of gauges are: broad, standard,
                narrow, and dual. Other gauges are listed under note. Some 60% of
                the world's railways use the standard gauge of 1.4 m (4.7 ft).
                Gauges vary by country and sometimes within countries. The choice
                of gauge during initial construction was mainly in resp . . .
                more


                total: 59
                km (2018)
                narrow gauge: 59 km 0.762-m
                gauge (2018)
                country comparison to the world:
                131

                Roadways: This entry gives the total length of the road
                network and includes the length of the paved and unpaved
                portions.

                total: 27,990
                km (2016)
                paved: 11,890
                km (2016)
                unpaved: 16,100 km (2016)
                country comparison to the world:
                98

            </transportation>
        </country>
    </nepal>
</countries>
