<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<country>
    <name>Argentina</name>
    <introduction>

        In 1816, the United Provinces of the Rio Plata declared their
        independence from Spain. After Bolivia, Paraguay, and Uruguay went
        their separate ways, the area that remained became Argentina. The
        country's population and culture were heavily shaped by immigrants
        from throughout Europe, with Italy and Spain providing the largest
        percentage of newcomers from 1860 to 1930. Up until about the
        mid-20th century, much of Argentina's history was dominated by
        periods of internal political unrest and conflict between civilian
        and military factions.
        After World War II, an era of Peronist populism and direct and
        indirect military interference in subsequent governments was
        followed by a military junta that took power in 1976. Democracy
        returned in 1983 after a failed bid to seize the Falkland Islands
        (Islas Malvinas) by force, and has persisted despite numerous
        challenges, the most formidable of which was a severe economic
        crisis in 2001-02 that led to violent public protests and the
        successive resignations of several presidents. The years 2003-15
        saw Peronist rule by Nestor and Cristina FERNANDEZ de KIRCHNER,
        whose policies isolated Argentina and caused economic stagnation.
        With the election of Mauricio MACRI in November 2015, Argentina
        began a period of reform and international reintegration.

    </introduction>
    <geography>
        second-largest country in
        South America (after Brazil); strategic location relative to sea
        lanes between the South Atlantic and the South Pacific Oceans
        (Strait of Magellan, Beagle Channel, Drake Passage); diverse
        geophysical landscapes range from tropical climates in the north to
        tundra in the far south; Cerro Aconcagua is the Western
        Hemisphere's tallest mountain, while Laguna del Carbon is the
        lowest point in the Western Hemisphere; shares Iguazu Falls, the
        world's largest waterfalls system, with Brazil
        <location>
            Southern South America,
            bordering the South Atlantic Ocean, between Chile and Uruguay
        </location>
        <coordinates>
            34 00 S, 64 00 W
        </coordinates>
        <map-references>
            South America
        </map-references>
        <area>
            <total>2,780,400 sq km</total>
            <land>2,736,690 sq km</land>
            <water>43,710
                sq km
            </water>
        </area>
        <climate>
            mostly temperate; arid in
            southeast; subantarctic in southwest
        </climate>
        <natural-hazards>

            San Miguel de Tucuman and Mendoza areas in the Andes subject to
            earthquakes; pamperos are violent windstorms that can strike the
            pampas and northeast; heavy flooding in some areas
            volcanism: volcanic activity in the Andes
            Mountains along the Chilean border; Copahue (2,997 m) last erupted
            in 2000; other historically active volcanoes include Llullaillaco,
            Maipo, Planchon-Peteroa, San Jose, Tromen, Tupungatito, and
            Viedma

        </natural-hazards>
        <population-distribution>
            one-third of the
            population lives in Buenos Aires; pockets of agglomeration occur
            throughout the northern and central parts of the country; Patagonia
            to the south remains sparsely populated
        </population-distribution>
    </geography>
    <people>

        Argentina's population continues to grow but at a slower rate
        because of its steadily declining birth rate. Argentina's fertility
        decline began earlier than in the rest of Latin America, occurring
        most rapidly between the early 20th century and the 1950s, and then
        becoming more gradual. Life expectancy has been improving, most
        notably among the young and the poor. While the population under
        age 15 is shrinking, the youth cohort - ages 15-24 - is the largest
        in Argentina's history and will continue to bolster the working-age
        population. If this large working-age population is well-educated
        and gainfully employed, Argentina is likely to experience an
        economic boost and possibly higher per capita savings and
        investment. Although literacy and primary school enrollment are
        nearly universal, grade repetition is problematic and secondary
        school completion is low. Both of these issues vary widely by
        region and socioeconomic group.
        Argentina has been primarily a country of immigration for most
        of its history, welcoming European immigrants (often providing
        needed low-skilled labor) after its independence in the 19th
        century and attracting especially large numbers from Spain and
        Italy. More than 7 million European immigrants are estimated to
        have arrived in Argentina between 1880 and 1930, when it adopted a
        more restrictive immigration policy. European immigration also
        began to wane in the 1930s because of the global depression. The
        inflow rebounded temporarily following WWII and resumed its decline
        in the 1950s when Argentina's military dictators tightened
        immigration rules and European economies rebounded. Regional
        migration increased, however, supplying low-skilled workers
        escaping economic and political instability in their home
        countries. As of 2015, immigrants made up almost 5% of Argentina's
        population, the largest share in South America. Migration from
        neighboring countries accounted for approximately 80% of
        Argentina's immigrant population in 2015.
        The first waves of highly skilled Argentine emigrant workers
        headed mainly to the United States and Spain in the 1960s and
        1970s, driven by economic decline and repressive military
        dictatorships. The 2008 European economic crisis drove the return
        migration of some Argentinean and other Latin American nationals,
        as well as the immigration of Europeans to South America, where
        Argentina was a key recipient. In 2015, Argentina received the
        highest number of legal migrants in Latin America and the
        Caribbean. The majority of its migrant inflow came from Paraguay
        and Bolivia.

        <population>
            45,479,118 (July 2020
            est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            32
        </population>
        <age-structure>
            <category>0-14 years: 24.02% (male
                5,629,188/female 5,294,723)
            </category>
            <category>15-24 years: 15.19% (male
                3,539,021/female 3,367,321)
            </category>
            <category>25-54 years: 39.6% (male
                9,005,758/female 9,002,931)
            </category>
            <category>55-64 years: 9.07% (male
                2,000,536/female 2,122,699)
            </category>
            <category>65 years and over: 12.13% (male
                2,331,679/female 3,185,262) (2020 est.)
            </category>
        </age-structure>
        <urbanization>
            urban population: 92.1% of total population (2020)
            rate of urbanization: 1.07% annual rate of change (2015-20 est.)
        </urbanization>
        <distribution>
            one-third of the
            population lives in Buenos Aires; pockets of agglomeration occur
            throughout the northern and central parts of the country; Patagonia
            to the south remains sparsely populated
        </distribution>
    </people>
    <government>
        Country name: This entry includes all forms of the country's
        name approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (Italy is used as
        an example): conventional long form (Italian Republic),
        conventional short form (Italy), local long form (Repubblica
        Italiana), local short form (Italia), former (Kingdom of Italy), as
        well as the abbreviation. Also see the Terminology
        note.

        conventional long form: Argentine
        Republic
        conventional short form: Argentina
        local long form: Republica Argentina
        local short form: Argentina
        etymology: originally the area was referred
        to as Tierra Argentina, i.e., "Land beside the Silvery River" or
        "silvery land," which referred to the massive estuary in the east
        of the country, the Rio de la Plata (River of Silver); over time
        the name shortened to simply Argentina or "silvery"

        Government type:
        This entry gives the basic form of
        government. Definitions of the major governmental terms are as
        follows. (Note that for some countries more than one definition
        applies.): Absolute monarchy - a form of government where the
        monarch rules unhindered, i.e., without any laws, constitution, or
        legally organized opposition. Anarchy - a condition of lawlessness
        or political disorder brought about by the absence of governmental
        authority. Authoritarian - a form of government in whic . . .
        more


        presidential
        republic

        Capital: This entry gives the name of the seat of
        government, its geographic coordinates, the time difference
        relative to Coordinated Universal Time (UTC) and the time observed
        in Washington, DC, and, if applicable, information on daylight
        saving time (DST). Where appropriate, a special note has been added
        to highlight those countries that have multiple time
        zones.

        name: Buenos Aires
        geographic coordinates: 34 36 S, 58 22
        W
        time difference: UTC-3 (2 hours ahead of
        Washington, DC, during Standard Time)
        etymology: the
        name translates as "fair winds" in Spanish and derives from the
        original designation of the settlement that would become the
        present-day city, "Santa Maria del Buen Aire" (Saint Mary of the
        Fair Winds)

        Administrative divisions:
        This entry generally gives the
        numbers, designatory terms, and first-order administrative
        divisions as approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (BGN).
        Changes that have been reported but not yet acted on by the BGN are
        noted. Geographic names conform to spellings approved by the BGN
        with the exception of the omission of diacritical marks and special
        characters.

        23 provinces (provincias,
        singular - provincia) and 1 autonomous city*; Buenos Aires,
        Catamarca, Chaco, Chubut, Ciudad Autonoma de Buenos Aires*,
        Cordoba, Corrientes, Entre Rios, Formosa, Jujuy, La Pampa, La
        Rioja, Mendoza, Misiones, Neuquen, Rio Negro, Salta, San Juan, San
        Luis, Santa Cruz, Santa Fe, Santiago del Estero, Tierra del Fuego -
        Antartida e Islas del Atlantico Sur (Tierra del Fuego - Antarctica
        and the South Atlantic Islands), Tucuman

        note: the US does not recognize any claims to
        Antarctica


        Independence: For most countries, this entry gives the date
        that sovereignty was achieved and from which nation, empire, or
        trusteeship. For the other countries, the date given may not
        represent "independence" in the strict sense, but rather some
        significant nationhood event such as the traditional founding date
        or the date of unification, federation, confederation,
        establishment, fundamental change in the form of government, or
        state succession. For a number of countries, the establishment of
        statehood . . . more

        9 July 1816 (from
        Spain)

        National holiday:
        This entry gives the primary national
        day of celebration - usually independence day.


        Revolution Day (May
        Revolution Day), 25 May (1810)

        Constitution: This entry provides information on a country’s
        constitution and includes two subfields. The history subfield
        includes the dates of previous constitutions and the main steps and
        dates in formulating and implementing the latest constitution. For
        countries with 1-3 previous constitutions, the years are listed;
        for those with 4-9 previous, the entry is listed as “several
        previous,” and for those with 10 or more, the entry is “many
        previous.” The amendments subfield summarizes the process of am . .
        . more


        history: several previous; latest effective
        11 May 1853
        amendments: a declaration of proposed
        amendments requires two-thirds majority vote by both houses of the
        National Congress followed by approval by an ad hoc, multi-member
        constitutional convention; amended many times, last significant
        amendment in 1994 (2018)

        Legal system: This entry provides the description of a
        country's legal system. A statement on judicial review of
        legislative acts is also included for a number of countries. The
        legal systems of nearly all countries are generally modeled upon
        elements of five main types: civil law (including French law, the
        Napoleonic Code, Roman law, Roman-Dutch law, and Spanish law);
        common law (including United State law); customary law; mixed or
        pluralistic law; and religious law (including Islamic law). An
        addition . . . more

        civil law system based on
        West European legal systems; note - in mid-2015, Argentina adopted
        a new civil code, replacing the old one in force since 1871


        International law organization
        participation: This entry
        includes information on a country's acceptance of jurisdiction of
        the International Court of Justice (ICJ) and of the International
        Criminal Court (ICCt); 59 countries have accepted ICJ jurisdiction
        with reservations and 11 have accepted ICJ jurisdiction without
        reservations; 122 countries have accepted ICCt jurisdiction.
        Appendix B: International Organizations and Groups explains the
        differing mandates of the ICJ and ICCt.

        has not submitted an ICJ
        jurisdiction declaration; accepts ICCt jurisdiction

        Citizenship: This entry provides information related to the
        acquisition and exercise of citizenship; it includes four
        subfields: citizenship by birth describes the acquisition of
        citizenship based on place of birth, known as Jus soli, regardless
        of the citizenship of parents. citizenship by descent only
        describes the acquisition of citizenship based on the principle of
        Jus sanguinis, or by descent, where at least one parent is a
        citizen of the state and being born within the territorial limits
        of the s . . . more

        citizenship by birth: yes
        citizenship by descent only: yes
        dual citizenship recognized: yes
        residency requirement for naturalization: 2
        years

        Suffrage: This entry gives the age at enfranchisement and
        whether the right to vote is universal or restricted.


        18-70 years of age;
        universal and compulsory; 16-17 years of age - optional for
        national elections

        Executive branch:
        This entry includes five subentries:
        chief of state; head of government; cabinet;
        elections/appointments; election results. Chief of state includes
        the name, title, and beginning date in office of the titular leader
        of the country who represents the state at official and ceremonial
        functions but may not be involved with the day-to-day activities of
        the government. Head of government includes the name, title of the
        top executive designated to manage the executive branch of the
        government, a . . . more

        chief of state: President Alberto Angel
        FERNANDEZ (since 10 December 2019); Vice President Cristina
        FERNANDEZ DE KIRCHNER (since 10 December 2019); note - the
        president is both chief of state and head of government
        head of government: President Alberto Angel
        FERNANDEZ (since 10 December 2019); Vice President Cristina
        FERNANDEZ DE KIRCHNER (since 10 December 2019)
        cabinet: Cabinet appointed by the
        president
        elections/appointments: president and vice
        president directly elected on the same ballot by qualified majority
        vote (to win, a candidate must receive at least 45% of votes or 40%
        of votes and a 10-point lead over the second place candidate; if
        neither occurs, a second round is held ); the president serves a
        4-year term (eligible for a second consecutive term); election last
        held on 27 October 2019 (next to be held in October 2023)
        election results: Alberto Angel FERNANDEZ
        elected president; percent of vote - Alberto Angel FERNANDEZ
        (TODOS) 48.1%, Mauricio MACRI (PRO) 40.4%, Roberto LAVAGNA
        (independent) 6.2%, other 5.3%

        Legislative branch:
        This entry has three subfields. The
        description subfield provides the legislative structure (unicameral
        – single house; bicameral – an upper and a lower house); formal
        name(s); number of member seats; types of constituencies or voting
        districts (single seat, multi-seat, nationwide); electoral voting
        system(s); and member term of office. The elections subfield
        includes the dates of the last election and next election. The
        election results subfield lists percent of vote by party/coalition
        an . . . more

        description: bicameral National Congress or
        Congreso Nacional consists of:
        Senate (72 seats; members directly elected in multi-seat
        constituencies by simple majority vote to serve 6-year terms with
        one-third of the membership elected every 2 years)
        Chamber of Deputies (257 seats; members directly elected in
        multi-seat constituencies by proportional representation vote;
        members serve 4-year terms with one-half of the membership renewed
        every 2 years)
        elections:
        Senate - last held on 27 October 2019 (next to be held in October
        2021)
        Chamber of Deputies - last held on 27 October 2019 (next to be held
        in October 2021)
        election results: Senate - percent of vote
        by bloc or party - NA; seats by bloc or party - TODOS 13, Cambiemos
        8, FCS 2, JSRN 1;
        Chamber of Deputies - percent of vote by bloc or party - NA; seats
        by bloc or party - TODOS 64, Cambiemos 56, CF 3, FCS 3, JSRN 1,
        other 3

        Judicial branch:
        This entry includes three subfields.
        The highest court(s) subfield includes the name(s) of a country's
        highest level court(s), the number and titles of the judges, and
        the types of cases heard by the court, which commonly are based on
        civil, criminal, administrative, and constitutional law. A number
        of countries have separate constitutional courts. The judge
        selection and term of office subfield includes the organizations
        and associated officials responsible for nominating and appointing
        j . . . more

        highest courts: Supreme Court or Corte
        Suprema (consists of the court president, vice president, and 5
        justices)
        judge selection and term of office: justices
        nominated by the president and approved by the Senate; justices can
        serve until mandatory retirement at age 75; extensions beyond 75
        require renomination by the president and approval by the
        Senate
        subordinate courts: federal level appellate,
        district, and territorial courts; provincial level supreme,
        appellate, and first instance courts


        Political parties and
        leaders: This entry includes a
        listing of significant political parties, coalitions, and electoral
        lists as of each country's last legislative election, unless
        otherwise noted.

        Argentina Federal
        [coalition led by Pablo KOSINER]
        Cambiemos [Mauricio MACRI] (coalition of CC-ARI, PRO, and
        UCR)
        Citizen's Unity or UC [Cristina FERNANDEZ DE KIRCHNER]
        Civic Coalition ARI or CC-ARI [Elisa CARRIO, Maximiliano
        FERRARO]
        Civic Front for Santiago or FCS [Gerardo ZAMORA]
        Everyone's Front (Frente de Todos) or TODOS [Alberto Angel
        FERNANDEZ]
        Federal Consensus or CF [Roberto LAVAGNA, Juan Manuel
        URTUBEY]
        Front for the Renewal of Concord or FRC
        Front for Victory or FpV [coalition led by Cristina FERNANDEZ DE
        KIRCHNER and Agustin ROSSI]
        Generation for a National Encounter or GEN [Monica PERALTA]
        Justicialist Party or PJ [Miguel Angel PICHETTO]
        Radical Civic Union or UCR [Alfredo CORNEJO]
        Renewal Front (Frente Renovador) or FR [Sergio MASSA]
        Republican Proposal or PRO [Mauricio MACRI, Humberto
        SCHIAVONI]
        Socialist Party or PS [Antonio BONFATTI]
        Socialist Workers’ Party or PTS [Jose MONTES]
        Together We Are Rio Negro or JSRN [Alberto Edgardo
        WERETILNECK]
        We Do For Cordoba (Hacemos Por Cordoba) or HC [Juan
        SCHIARETTI]
        Workers' Party or PO [Jorge ALTAMIRA]
        Worker’s Socialist Movement or MST [Alejandro BODDART; Vilma
        RIPOLL]
        numerous provincial parties


        International organization
        participation: This entry lists
        in alphabetical order by abbreviation those international
        organizations in which the subject country is a member or
        participates in some other way.

        AfDB (nonregional member),
        Australia Group, BCIE, BIS, CAN (associate), CD, CELAC, FAO, FATF,
        G-15, G-20, G-24, G-77, IADB, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC (national
        committees), ICCt, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO,
        IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC (NGOs), LAES,
        LAIA, Mercosur, MIGA, MINURSO, MINUSTAH, NAM (observer), NSG, OAS,
        OPANAL, OPCW, Paris Club (associate), PCA, SICA (observer), UN,
        UNASUR, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNFICYP, UNHCR, UNIDO, Union Latina
        (observer), UNTSO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU (NGOs), WHO, WIPO, WMO,
        WTO, ZC


        Diplomatic representation in
        the US: This entry includes the
        chief of mission, chancery address, telephone, FAX, consulate
        general locations, and consulate locations. The use of the
        annotated title Appointed Ambassador refers to a new ambassador who
        has presented his/her credentials to the secretary of state but not
        the US president. Such ambassadors fulfill all diplomatic functions
        except meeting with or appearing at functions attended by the
        president until such time as they formally present their
        credentials at a White Hou . . . more

        Ambassador Fernando ORIS
        DE ROA (since 24 January 2018)
        chancery: 1600 New Hampshire Avenue NW,
        Washington, DC 20009
        telephone: [1] (202) 238-6400
        FAX: [1] (202) 332-3171
        consulate(s) general: Atlanta, Chicago,
        Houston, Los Angeles, Miami, New York, Washington, DC


        Diplomatic representation from
        the US: This entry includes the
        chief of mission, embassy address, mailing address, telephone
        number, FAX number, branch office locations, consulate general
        locations, and consulate locations.

        chief of mission: Ambassador Edward Charles
        PRADO (since 16 May 2018)
        telephone: [54] (11) 5777-4533
        embassy: Avenida Colombia 4300, C1425GMN
        Buenos Aires
        mailing address: international mail: use
        embassy street address; APO address: US Embassy Buenos Aires, Unit
        4334, APO AA 34034
        FAX: [54] (11) 5777-4240

        Flag description:
        This entry provides a written flag
        description produced from actual flags or the best information
        available at the time the entry was written. The flags of
        independent states are used by their dependencies unless there is
        an officially recognized local flag. Some disputed and other areas
        do not have flags.

        three equal horizontal
        bands of sky blue (top), white, and sky blue; centered in the white
        band is a radiant yellow sun with a human face (delineated in
        brown) known as the Sun of May; the colors represent the clear
        skies and snow of the Andes; the sun symbol commemorates the
        appearance of the sun through cloudy skies on 25 May 1810 during
        the first mass demonstration in favor of independence; the sun
        features are those of Inti, the Inca god of the sun

        National symbol(s):
        A national symbol is a faunal,
        floral, or other abstract representation - or some distinctive
        object - that over time has come to be closely identified with a
        country or entity. Not all countries have national symbols; a few
        countries have more than one.

        Sun of May (a
        sun-with-face symbol); national colors: sky blue, white

        National anthem:
        A generally patriotic musical
        composition - usually in the form of a song or hymn of praise -
        that evokes and eulogizes the history, traditions, or struggles of
        a nation or its people. National anthems can be officially
        recognized as a national song by a country's constitution or by an
        enacted law, or simply by tradition. Although most anthems contain
        lyrics, some do not.

        name: "Himno Nacional Argentino" (Argentine
        National Anthem)
        lyrics/music: Vicente LOPEZ y PLANES/Jose
        Blas PARERA

        note: adopted 1813; Vicente LOPEZ was inspired
        to write the anthem after watching a play about the 1810 May
        Revolution against Spain


    </government>
    <economy>

        Argentina benefits from rich natural resources, a highly
        literate population, an export-oriented agricultural sector, and a
        diversified industrial base. Although one of the world's wealthiest
        countries 100 years ago, Argentina suffered during most of the 20th
        century from recurring economic crises, persistent fiscal and
        current account deficits, high inflation, mounting external debt,
        and capital flight.
        Cristina FERNANDEZ DE KIRCHNER succeeded her husband as
        president in late 2007, and in 2008 the rapid economic growth of
        previous years slowed sharply as government policies held back
        exports and the world economy fell into recession. In 2010 the
        economy rebounded strongly, but slowed in late 2011 even as the
        government continued to rely on expansionary fiscal and monetary
        policies, which kept inflation in the double digits.
        In order to deal with these problems, the government expanded
        state intervention in the economy: it nationalized the oil company
        YPF from Spain's Repsol, expanded measures to restrict imports, and
        further tightened currency controls in an effort to bolster foreign
        reserves and stem capital flight. Between 2011 and 2013, Central
        Bank foreign reserves dropped $21.3 billion from a high of $52.7
        billion. In July 2014, Argentina and China agreed on an $11 billion
        currency swap; the Argentine Central Bank has received the
        equivalent of $3.2 billion in Chinese yuan, which it counts as
        international reserves.
        With the election of President Mauricio MACRI in November 2015,
        Argentina began a historic political and economic transformation,
        as his administration took steps to liberalize the Argentine
        economy, lifting capital controls, floating the peso, removing
        export controls on some commodities, cutting some energy subsidies,
        and reforming the country’s official statistics. Argentina
        negotiated debt payments with holdout bond creditors, continued
        working with the IMF to shore up its finances, and returned to
        international capital markets in April 2016.
        In 2017, Argentina’s economy emerged from recession with GDP
        growth of nearly 3.0%. The government passed important pension,
        tax, and fiscal reforms. And after years of international
        isolation, Argentina took on several international leadership
        roles, including hosting the World Economic Forum on Latin America
        and the World Trade Organization Ministerial Conference, and is set
        to assume the presidency of the G-20 in 2018.

        <gdp>
            $922.1 billion (2017 est.)
            $896.5 billion (2016 est.)
            $913.2 billion (2015 est.)

            note: data are in 2017 dollars

            country comparison to the world:
            28
        </gdp>
        <agriculture>
            agriculture: 10.8% (2017 est.)
            industry: 28.1% (2017 est.)
            services: 61.1% (2017 est.)
        </agriculture>
        <industries>
            food processing, motor
            vehicles, consumer durables, textiles, chemicals and
            petrochemicals, printing, metallurgy, steel
        </industries>
        <uneployment>
            8.4% (2017 est.)
            8.5% (2016 est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            120
        </uneployment>
        <balance>
            -$31.32 billion (2017
            est.)
            -$14.69 billion (2016
            est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            200
        </balance>
        <budget>
            revenues: 120.6 billion (2017 est.)
            expenditures: 158.6 billion (2017 est.)
        </budget>
    </economy>
    <communications>
        general assessment: one of the highest
        broadband penetrations in Latin America, supported by operator
        investment and govt programs aimed at expansion; govt
        provides 20 million euros for two 5G trials, Huawei conducts
        5G trials; major networks are entirely digital and the
        availability of telephone service continues to improve to rural
        areas; Argentinians own multiple SIM cards for work and personal
        use; even with numerous providers there is a lack of
        competition for broadband and mobile services; still Argentina
        is the 3rd largest in the region after Brazil and Mexico
        (2020)
        domestic: 22 per 100 fixed-line, 131 per 100
        mobile-cellular; microwave radio relay, fiber-optic cable, and a
        domestic satellite system with 40 earth stations serve the trunk
        network (2018)
        international: country code - 54; landing
        points for the UNISUR, Bicentenario, Atlantis-2, SAm-1,
        and SAC, Tannat, Malbec and ARBR submarine cable systems
        that provide links to Europe, Africa, South and Central America,
        and US; satellite earth stations - 112 (2019)
        note: the COVID-19
        outbreak is negatively impacting telecommunications production and
        supply chains globally; consumer spending on telecom devices and
        services has also slowed due to the pandemic's effect on economies
        worldwide; overall progress towards improvements in all facets of
        the telecom industry - mobile, fixed-line, broadband, submarine
        cable and satellite - has moderated
        <static-telephones>
            total subscriptions: 9,764,014
            subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
            22 (2018 est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            18
        </static-telephones>
        <mobile-phones>
            total subscriptions: 58,598,041
            subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
            131 (2018
            est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            27
        </mobile-phones>
        <broadcast-media>
            government owns a TV
            station and radio network; more than 2 dozen TV stations and
            hundreds of privately owned radio stations; high rate of cable TV
            subscription usage
        </broadcast-media>
        <internet>
            total: 30,786,889
            percent of population: 70.2% (July 2016
            est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            24
        </internet>
    </communications>
    <military>
        The Argentine military is
        a well-organized force constrained by the country's prolonged
        economic hardship; the military is implementing a modernization
        plan aimed at making the ground forces lighter and more
        responsive.

        President Mauricio Macri in July of 2019 said he would remove a
        2006 decree that limited the armed forces to defending against
        external attacks and banned military involvement in internal
        security issues.  Macri said he wanted the military to be able
        to collaborate in internal security, primarily by providing
        logistic support in the border areas. (2018)
        <forces>

            Armed Forces of the Argentine Republic (Fuerzas Armadas de la
            República Argentina): Argentine Army (Ejercito Argentino), Navy of
            the Argentine Republic (Armada Republica; includes naval aviation
            and naval infantry), Argentine Air Force (Fuerza Aerea Argentina,
            FAA); Ministry of Security: Gendarmerie, Prefectura Naval (coast
            guard)
            (2019)
        </forces>
        <obligation>
            18-24 years of age for
            voluntary military service (18-21 requires parental consent); no
            conscription; if the number of volunteers fails to meet the quota
            of recruits for a particular year, Congress can authorize the
            conscription of citizens turning 18 that year for a period not
            exceeding one year (2012)
        </obligation>
        <expenditures>
            0.7% of GDP (2019)
            0.7% of GDP (2018)
            0.9% of GDP (2017)
            0.8% of GDP (2016)
            0.9% of GDP (2015)
            country comparison to the world:
            130
        </expenditures>
    </military>
    <transportation>

        National air transport
        system: This entry includes four
        subfields describing the air transport system of a given country in
        terms of both structure and performance. The first subfield, number
        of registered air carriers, indicates the total number of air
        carriers registered with the country’s national aviation authority
        and issued an air operator certificate as required by the
        Convention on International Civil Aviation. The second subfield,
        inventory of registered aircraft operated by air carriers, lists
        the total number . . . more

        number of registered air carriers:
        6 (2015)
        inventory of registered aircraft operated by air
        carriers: 107
        (2015)
        annual passenger traffic on registered air
        carriers: 14,245,183
        (2015)
        annual freight traffic on registered air
        carriers: 243,772,567
        mt-km (2015)


        Civil aircraft registration
        country code prefix: This entry
        provides the one- or two-character alphanumeric code indicating the
        nationality of civil aircraft. Article 20 of the Convention on
        International Civil Aviation (Chicago Convention), signed in 1944,
        requires that all aircraft engaged in international air navigation
        bear appropriate nationality marks. The aircraft registration
        number consists of two parts: a prefix consisting of a one- or
        two-character alphanumeric code indicating nationality and a
        registration suffix of one to fi . . . more

        LV (2016)

        Airports: This entry gives the total number of airports or
        airfields recognizable from the air. The runway(s) may be paved
        (concrete or asphalt surfaces) or unpaved (grass, earth, sand, or
        gravel surfaces) and may include closed or abandoned installations.
        Airports or airfields that are no longer recognizable (overgrown,
        no facilities, etc.) are not included. Note that not all airports
        have accommodations for refueling, maintenance, or air traffic
        control.

        1,138 (2013)
        country comparison to the world:
        6


        Airports - with paved
        runways: This entry gives the
        total number of airports with paved runways (concrete or asphalt
        surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one runway, only
        the longest runway is included according to the following five
        groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2) 2,438 to 3,047 m
        (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000 to 8,000 ft), (4)
        914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under 914 m (under
        3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are included in this
        listing. Not all . . . more

        total: 161 (2017)
        over 3,047 m: 4 (2017)
        2,438 to 3,047 m: 29 (2017)
        1,524 to 2,437 m: 65 (2017)
        914 to 1,523 m: 53 (2017)
        under 914 m: 10 (2017)


        Airports - with unpaved
        runways: This entry gives the
        total number of airports with unpaved runways (grass, dirt, sand,
        or gravel surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one
        runway, only the longest runway is included according to the
        following five groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2)
        2,438 to 3,047 m (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000
        to 8,000 ft), (4) 914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under
        914 m (under 3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are
        included in this listin . . . more

        total: 977 (2013)
        over 3,047 m: 1 (2013)
        2,438 to 3,047 m: 1 (2013)
        1,524 to 2,437 m: 43 (2013)
        914 to 1,523 m: 484 (2013)
        under 914 m: 448 (2013)

        Heliports: This entry gives the total number of heliports
        with hard-surface runways, helipads, or landing areas that support
        routine sustained helicopter operations exclusively and have
        support facilities including one or more of the following
        facilities: lighting, fuel, passenger handling, or maintenance. It
        includes former airports used exclusively for helicopter operations
        but excludes heliports limited to day operations and natural
        clearings that could support helicopter landings and
        takeoffs.

        2 (2013)

        Pipelines: This entry gives the lengths and types of
        pipelines for transporting products like natural gas, crude oil, or
        petroleum products.

        29930 km gas, 41 km liquid
        petroleum gas, 6248 km oil, 3631 km refined products (2013)

        Railways: This entry states the total route length of the
        railway network and of its component parts by gauge, which is the
        measure of the distance between the inner sides of the load-bearing
        rails. The four typical types of gauges are: broad, standard,
        narrow, and dual. Other gauges are listed under note. Some 60% of
        the world's railways use the standard gauge of 1.4 m (4.7 ft).
        Gauges vary by country and sometimes within countries. The choice
        of gauge during initial construction was mainly in resp . . .
        more


        total: 36,917
        km (2014)
        standard gauge: 2,745.1 km 1.435-m gauge (41.1 km electrified)
        (2014)
        narrow gauge: 7,523.3 km 1.000-m gauge (2014)
        broad gauge: 26,391 km 1.676-m gauge (149 km electrified)
        (2014)
        258 km 0.750-m gauge
        country comparison to the world:
        6

        Roadways: This entry gives the total length of the road
        network and includes the length of the paved and unpaved
        portions.

        total: 281,290
        km (2017)
        paved: 117,616
        km (2017)
        unpaved: 163,674 km (2017)
        country comparison to the world:
        21

        Waterways: This entry gives the total length of navigable
        rivers, canals, and other inland bodies of water.


        11,000 km (2012)
        country comparison to the world:
        11

        Merchant marine:
        This entry provides the total and the
        number of each type of privately or publicly owned commercial ship
        for each country; military ships are not included; the five ships
        by type include: bulk carrier - for cargo such as coal, grain,
        cement, ores, and gravel; container ship - for loads in truck-size
        containers, a transportation system called containerization;
        general cargo - also referred to as break-bulk containers - for a
        wide variety of packaged merchandise, such as textiles, furniture .
        . . more


        total: 192
        by type: bulk carrier 1, general cargo 8,
        oil tanker 30, other 153 (2019)
        country comparison to the world:
        68

        Ports and terminals:
        This entry lists major ports and
        terminals primarily on the basis of the amount of cargo tonnage
        shipped through the facilities on an annual basis. In some
        instances, the number of containers handled or ship visits were
        also considered. Most ports service multiple classes of vessels
        including bulk carriers (dry and liquid), break bulk cargoes (goods
        loaded individually in bags, boxes, crates, or drums; sometimes
        palletized), containers, roll-on/roll-off, and passenger ships. The
        listing le . . . more

        major seaport(s): Bahia Blanca, Buenos
        Aires, La Plata, Punta Colorada, Ushuaia
        container port(s) (TEUs): Buenos Aires
        (1,851,701)
        LNG terminal(s) (import): Bahia Blanca
        river port(s): Arroyo Seco, Rosario, San
        Lorenzo-San Martin (Parana)

    </transportation>
</country>
