<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<country>
    <name>Cyprus</name>
    <introduction>
        A former British colony,
        Cyprus became independent in 1960 following years of resistance to
        British rule. Tensions between the Greek Cypriot majority and
        Turkish Cypriot minority communities came to a head in December
        1963, when violence broke out in the capital of Nicosia. Despite
        the deployment of UN peacekeepers in 1964, sporadic intercommunal
        violence continued, forcing most Turkish Cypriots into enclaves
        throughout the island. In 1974, a Greek Government-sponsored
        attempt to overthrow the elected president of Cyprus was met by
        military intervention from Turkey, which soon controlled more than
        a third of the island. In 1983, the Turkish Cypriot administered
        area declared itself the "Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus"
        ("TRNC"), but it is recognized only by Turkey. An UN-mediated
        agreement, the Annan Plan, failed to win approval by both
        communities in 2004. In February 2014, after a hiatus of nearly two
        years, the leaders of the two communities resumed formal
        discussions under UN auspices aimed at reuniting the divided
        island. The most recent round of negotiations to reunify the island
        were suspended in July 2017 after failure to achieve a
        breakthrough. The entire island entered the EU on 1 May 2004,
        although the EU acquis - the body of common rights and obligations
        - applies only to the areas under the internationally recognized
        government, and is suspended in the "TRNC." However, individual
        Turkish Cypriots able to document their eligibility for Republic of
        Cyprus citizenship legally enjoy the same rights accorded to other
        citizens of EU states.
    </introduction>
    <geography>Geography - note:
        This entry includes miscellaneous
        geographic information of significance not included
        elsewhere.
        <location>
            Middle East, island in the
            Mediterranean Sea, south of Turkey; note - Cyprus views itself as
            part of Europe; geopolitically, it can be classified as falling
            within Europe, the Middle East, or both
        </location>
        <coordinates>
            35 00 N, 33 00 E
        </coordinates>
        <map-references>
            Middle East
        </map-references>
        <area>
            <total>9,251
                sq km
            </total>
            <land>9,241 sq
                km
            </land>
            <water>10 sq
                km
            </water>
        </area>
        <climate>
            temperate; Mediterranean
            with hot, dry summers and cool winters
        </climate>
        <natural-hazards>
            moderate earthquake
            activity; droughts
        </natural-hazards>
        <population-distribution>
            population concentrated in
            central Nicosia and in the major cities of the south: Paphos,
            Limassol, and Larnaca
        </population-distribution>
    </geography>
    <people>
        <population>
            1,266,676 (July 2020
            est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            157
        </population>
        <age-structure>
            <category>0-14 years: 15.69% (male
                102,095/female 96,676)
            </category>
            <category>15-24 years: 12.29% (male
                84,832/female 70,879)
            </category>
            <category>25-54 years: 47.12% (male
                316,710/female 280,167)
            </category>
            <category>55-64 years: 11.92% (male
                72,476/female 78,511)
            </category>
            <category>65 years and over: 12.97% (male
                71,053/female 93,277) (2020 est.)
            </category>
        </age-structure>
        <urbanization>
            urban population: 66.8% of total population (2020)
            rate of urbanization: 0.75% annual rate of change (2015-20 est.)
        </urbanization>
        <distribution>
            population concentrated in
            central Nicosia and in the major cities of the south: Paphos,
            Limassol, and Larnaca
        </distribution>
    </people>
    <government>
        Country name: This entry includes all forms of the country's
        name approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (Italy is used as
        an example): conventional long form (Italian Republic),
        conventional short form (Italy), local long form (Repubblica
        Italiana), local short form (Italia), former (Kingdom of Italy), as
        well as the abbreviation. Also see the Terminology
        note.

        conventional long form: Republic of
        Cyprus
        conventional short form: Cyprus
        local long form: Kypriaki Dimokratia/Kibris
        Cumhuriyeti
        local short form: Kypros/Kibris
        etymology: the derivation of the name
        "Cyprus" is unknown, but the extensive mining of copper metal on
        the island in antiquity gave rise to the Latin word "cuprum" for
        copper

        note: the Turkish Cypriot community, which
        administers the northern part of the island, refers to itself as
        the "Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus" or "TRNC" ("Kuzey Kibris
        Turk Cumhuriyeti" or "KKTC")


        Government type:
        This entry gives the basic form of
        government. Definitions of the major governmental terms are as
        follows. (Note that for some countries more than one definition
        applies.): Absolute monarchy - a form of government where the
        monarch rules unhindered, i.e., without any laws, constitution, or
        legally organized opposition. Anarchy - a condition of lawlessness
        or political disorder brought about by the absence of governmental
        authority. Authoritarian - a form of government in whic . . .
        more


        Republic of Cyprus -
        presidential republic; "Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus"
        (self-declared) - parliamentary republic with enhanced
        presidency

        note: a separation of the two main ethnic
        communities inhabiting the island began following the outbreak of
        communal strife in 1963; this separation was further solidified
        when a Greek military-junta-supported coup attempt prompted the
        Turkish military intervention in July 1974 that gave the Turkish
        Cypriots de facto control in the north; Greek Cypriots control the
        only internationally recognized government on the island; on 15
        November 1983, then Turkish Cypriot "President" Rauf DENKTAS
        declared independence and the formation of the "TRNC,” which is
        recognized only by Turkey


        Capital: This entry gives the name of the seat of
        government, its geographic coordinates, the time difference
        relative to Coordinated Universal Time (UTC) and the time observed
        in Washington, DC, and, if applicable, information on daylight
        saving time (DST). Where appropriate, a special note has been added
        to highlight those countries that have multiple time
        zones.

        name: Nicosia (Lefkosia/Lefkosa)
        geographic coordinates: 35 10 N, 33 22
        E
        time difference: UTC+2 (7 hours ahead of
        Washington, DC, during Standard Time)
        daylight saving time: +1hr, begins last
        Sunday in March; ends last Sunday in October
        etymology: a
        mispronunciation of the city's Greek name Lefkosia and its Turkish
        name Lefkosa, both of which mean "White City"; the Greek name may
        derive from the Greek phrase "leuke ousia" ("white estate")

        Administrative divisions:
        This entry generally gives the
        numbers, designatory terms, and first-order administrative
        divisions as approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (BGN).
        Changes that have been reported but not yet acted on by the BGN are
        noted. Geographic names conform to spellings approved by the BGN
        with the exception of the omission of diacritical marks and special
        characters.

        6 districts; Ammochostos
        (Famagusta); (all but a small part located in the Turkish Cypriot
        community), Keryneia (Kyrenia; the only district located entirely
        in the Turkish Cypriot community), Larnaka (Larnaca; with a small
        part located in the Turkish Cypriot community), Lefkosia (Nicosia;
        a small part administered by Turkish Cypriots), Lemesos (Limassol),
        Pafos (Paphos); note - the 5 "districts" of the "TRNC" are
        Gazimagusa (Famagusta), Girne (Kyrenia), Guzelyurt (Morphou),
        Iskele (Trikomo), Lefkosa (Nicosia)

        Independence: For most countries, this entry gives the date
        that sovereignty was achieved and from which nation, empire, or
        trusteeship. For the other countries, the date given may not
        represent "independence" in the strict sense, but rather some
        significant nationhood event such as the traditional founding date
        or the date of unification, federation, confederation,
        establishment, fundamental change in the form of government, or
        state succession. For a number of countries, the establishment of
        statehood . . . more

        16 August 1960 (from the
        UK); note - Turkish Cypriots proclaimed self-rule on 13 February
        1975 and independence in 1983, but these proclamations are
        recognized only by Turkey

        National holiday:
        This entry gives the primary national
        day of celebration - usually independence day.


        Independence Day, 1
        October (1960); note - Turkish Cypriots celebrate 15 November
        (1983) as "Republic Day"

        Constitution: This entry provides information on a country’s
        constitution and includes two subfields. The history subfield
        includes the dates of previous constitutions and the main steps and
        dates in formulating and implementing the latest constitution. For
        countries with 1-3 previous constitutions, the years are listed;
        for those with 4-9 previous, the entry is listed as “several
        previous,” and for those with 10 or more, the entry is “many
        previous.” The amendments subfield summarizes the process of am . .
        . more


        history: ratified 16 August 1960; note - in
        1963, the constitution was partly suspended as Turkish Cypriots
        withdrew from the government; Turkish-held territory in 1983 was
        declared the "Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus" ("TRNC"); in
        1985, the "TRNC" approved its own constitution
        amendments: constitution of the Republic of
        Cyprus - proposed by the House of Representatives; passage requires
        at least two-thirds majority vote of the total membership of the
        "Greek Community" and the "Turkish Community"; however, all seats
        of Turkish Cypriot members have remained vacant since 1964; amended
        10 times, last in 2016
        constitution of the “Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus” -
        proposed by at least 10 members of the "Assembly of the Republic";
        passage requires at least two-thirds majority vote of the total
        Assembly membership and approval by referendum; amended 2014
        (2019)

        Legal system: This entry provides the description of a
        country's legal system. A statement on judicial review of
        legislative acts is also included for a number of countries. The
        legal systems of nearly all countries are generally modeled upon
        elements of five main types: civil law (including French law, the
        Napoleonic Code, Roman law, Roman-Dutch law, and Spanish law);
        common law (including United State law); customary law; mixed or
        pluralistic law; and religious law (including Islamic law). An
        addition . . . more

        mixed legal system of
        English common law and civil law with European law supremacy


        International law organization
        participation: This entry
        includes information on a country's acceptance of jurisdiction of
        the International Court of Justice (ICJ) and of the International
        Criminal Court (ICCt); 59 countries have accepted ICJ jurisdiction
        with reservations and 11 have accepted ICJ jurisdiction without
        reservations; 122 countries have accepted ICCt jurisdiction.
        Appendix B: International Organizations and Groups explains the
        differing mandates of the ICJ and ICCt.

        accepts compulsory ICJ
        jurisdiction with reservations; accepts ICC jurisdiction

        Citizenship: This entry provides information related to the
        acquisition and exercise of citizenship; it includes four
        subfields: citizenship by birth describes the acquisition of
        citizenship based on place of birth, known as Jus soli, regardless
        of the citizenship of parents. citizenship by descent only
        describes the acquisition of citizenship based on the principle of
        Jus sanguinis, or by descent, where at least one parent is a
        citizen of the state and being born within the territorial limits
        of the s . . . more

        citizenship by birth: no
        citizenship by descent only: at least one
        parent must be a citizen of Cyprus
        dual citizenship recognized: yes
        residency requirement for naturalization: 7
        years

        Suffrage: This entry gives the age at enfranchisement and
        whether the right to vote is universal or restricted.


        18 years of age;
        universal

        Executive branch:
        This entry includes five subentries:
        chief of state; head of government; cabinet;
        elections/appointments; election results. Chief of state includes
        the name, title, and beginning date in office of the titular leader
        of the country who represents the state at official and ceremonial
        functions but may not be involved with the day-to-day activities of
        the government. Head of government includes the name, title of the
        top executive designated to manage the executive branch of the
        government, a . . . more

        chief of state: President  Nikos
        ANASTASIADIS (since 28 February 2013); the president is both chief
        of state and head of government; note - vice presidency reserved
        for a Turkish Cypriot, but vacant since 1974 because Turkish
        Cypriots do not participate in the Republic of Cyprus
        Government
        head of government: President Nikos
        ANASTASIADIS (since 28 February 2013)
        cabinet: Council of Ministers appointed by
        the president; note - under the 1960 constitution, 3 of the
        ministerial posts reserved for Turkish Cypriots, appointed by the
        vice president; positions currently filled by Greek Cypriots
        elections/appointments: president directly
        elected by absolute majority popular vote in 2 rounds if needed for
        a 5-year term; election last held on 28 January 2018 with a runoff
        on 4 February 2018 (next to be held in February 2023)
        election results: Nikos ANASTASIADIS
        reelected president in second round; percent of vote in first round
        - Nikos ANASTASIADIS (DISY) 35.5%, Stavros MALAS (AKEL) 30.2%,
        Nicolas PAPADOPOULOS (DIKO) 25.7%, other 8.6%; percent of vote in
        second round - Nikos ANASTASIADIS 56%, Savros MALAS 44%

        note: Mustafa AKINCI assumed office as
        "president" of the "TRNC" on 30 April 2015; percent of vote in
        first round (19 April 2015) - Dervis EROGLU 28.2%, Mustafa AKINCI
        26.9%, other 44.9%; percent of vote in runoff (26 April 2015) -
        AKINCI 60.5%, EROGLU 39.5%


        Legislative branch:
        This entry has three subfields. The
        description subfield provides the legislative structure (unicameral
        – single house; bicameral – an upper and a lower house); formal
        name(s); number of member seats; types of constituencies or voting
        districts (single seat, multi-seat, nationwide); electoral voting
        system(s); and member term of office. The elections subfield
        includes the dates of the last election and next election. The
        election results subfield lists percent of vote by party/coalition
        an . . . more

        description: area under government control:
        unicameral House of Representatives or Vouli Antiprosopon (80
        seats; 56 assigned to Greek Cypriots, 24 to Turkish Cypriots, but
        only those assigned to Greek Cypriots are filled; members directly
        elected by both proportional representation and preferential vote;
        members serve 5-year terms); area administered by Turkish Cypriots:
        unicameral "Assembly of the Republic" or Cumhuriyet Meclisi (50
        seats; members directly elected to 5-year terms by proportional
        representation system using a hybrid d'Hondt method with
        voter preferences for individual candidates
        elections: area under government control:
        last held on 22 May 2016 (next to be held in May 2021); area
        administered by Turkish Cypriots: last held on 7 January 2018 (next
        to be held in 2023, unless early election called)
        election results: area under government
        control: House of Representatives - percent of vote by party - DISY
        30.7%, AKEL 25.7%, DIKO 14.5%, KS-EDEK 6.2%, SP 6% Solidarity
        Movement 5.2%, other 11.7%; seats by party - DISY 18, AKEL 16, DIKO
        9, KS-EDEK 3, Citizen's Alliance 3 (2 left the party in 2017 and
        2018 due to disagreements over the party's policy regarding the
        presidential election campaign; one joined DIKO and the other
        became an independent MP), Solidarity Movement 3, other 4; area
        administered by Turkish Cypriots: "Assembly of the Republic" -
        percent of vote by party - UBP 35.6%, CTP 20.9%, HP 17.1%, TDP
        8.6%, DP 7.8%, YDP 7%, 3%; seats by party - UBP 21, CTP 12, HP 9,
        DP 3, TDP 3, YDP 2

        Judicial branch:
        This entry includes three subfields.
        The highest court(s) subfield includes the name(s) of a country's
        highest level court(s), the number and titles of the judges, and
        the types of cases heard by the court, which commonly are based on
        civil, criminal, administrative, and constitutional law. A number
        of countries have separate constitutional courts. The judge
        selection and term of office subfield includes the organizations
        and associated officials responsible for nominating and appointing
        j . . . more

        highest courts: Supreme Court of Cyprus
        (consists of 13 judges, including the court president); note - the
        highest court in the "TRNC" is the "Supreme Court" (consists of 8
        "judges," including the "court president")
        judge selection and term of office: Republic
        of Cyprus Supreme Court judges appointed by the president of the
        republic upon the recommendation of the Supreme Court judges;
        judges can serve until age 68; "TRNC Supreme Court" judges
        appointed by the "Supreme Council of Judicature," a 12-member body
        of judges, the attorney general, appointees by the president of the
        "TRNC," and by the "Legislative Assembly," and members elected by
        the bar association; judge tenure NA
        subordinate courts: Republic of Cyprus
        district courts; Assize Courts; Administrative Court; specialized
        courts for issues relating to family, industrial disputes, the
        military, and rent control; "TRNC Assize Courts"; "district and
        family courts"


        Political parties and
        leaders: This entry includes a
        listing of significant political parties, coalitions, and electoral
        lists as of each country's last legislative election, unless
        otherwise noted.

        area under
        government control:
        Citizens' Alliance or SP [Giorgos LILLIKAS]
        Democratic Party or DIKO [Nicolas PAPADOPOULOS]
        Democratic Rally or DISY [Averof NEOPHYTOU]
        Movement of Ecologists and Environmentalists or KOP (Green party)
        [Giorgos PERDIKIS]
        I, the Citizen or EOP [Georgios KOUNTOURIS]
        Movement of Social Democrats EDEK [Marinos SIZOPOULOS]
        National Popular Front or ELAM [Christos CHRISTOU]
        Progressive Party of the Working People or AKEL (Communist party)
        [Andros KYPRIANOU]
        Solidarity Movement [Eleni THEOCHAROUS]
        United Democrats or EDI [Praxoula ANTONIADOU]
        Democratic Front or DIPA [Marios GAROYIAN]
        Animal Party Cyprus or APC [Kyriacos KYRIACOU]
        area administered by Turkish Cypriots:
        Communal Democracy Party or TDP [Cemal OZYIGIT]
        Communal Liberation Party-New Forces or TKP-YG [Mehmet
        CAKICI]
        Cyprus Socialist Party or KSP [Mehmet BIRINCI]
        Democratic Party or DP [Serdar DENKTAS]
        National Democratic Party or NDP [Buray BUSKUVUTCU]
        National Unity Party or UBP [Ersin TATAR]
        New Cyprus Party or YKP [Murat KANATLI]
        People's Party or HP [Kudret OZERSAY]
        Rebirth Party or YDP [Erhan ARIKLI]
        Republican Turkish Party or CTP [Tufan ERHURMAN]
        United Cyprus Party or BKP [Izzet IZCAN]


        International organization
        participation: This entry lists
        in alphabetical order by abbreviation those international
        organizations in which the subject country is a member or
        participates in some other way.

        Australia Group, C, CD,
        CE, EBRD, ECB, EIB, EMU, EU, FAO, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC (national
        committees), ICCt, ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, IHO, ILO, IMF, IMO,
        IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC (NGOs), MIGA,
        NAM, NSG, OAS (observer), OIF, OPCW, OSCE, PCA, UN, UNCTAD, UNESCO,
        UNHCR, UNIDO, UNIFIL, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU (NGOs), WHO, WIPO, WMO,
        WTO


        Diplomatic representation in
        the US: This entry includes the
        chief of mission, chancery address, telephone, FAX, consulate
        general locations, and consulate locations. The use of the
        annotated title Appointed Ambassador refers to a new ambassador who
        has presented his/her credentials to the secretary of state but not
        the US president. Such ambassadors fulfill all diplomatic functions
        except meeting with or appearing at functions attended by the
        president until such time as they formally present their
        credentials at a White Hou . . . more

        Ambassador Marios LYSIOTIS
        (since 17 September 2018)
        chancery: 2211 R Street NW, Washington, DC
        20008
        telephone: [1] (202) 462-5772,
        462-0873
        FAX: [1] (202) 483-6710
        consulate(s) general: New York

        note: representative of the Turkish Cypriot
        community in the US is Mustafa LAKADAMYALI; office at 1667 K Street
        NW, Washington, DC; telephone [1] (202) 887-6198


        Diplomatic representation from
        the US: This entry includes the
        chief of mission, embassy address, mailing address, telephone
        number, FAX number, branch office locations, consulate general
        locations, and consulate locations.

        chief of mission: Ambassador Judith Gail
        GARBER (since 18 March 2019)
        telephone: [357] (22) 393939
        embassy: corner of Metochiou and Ploutarchou
        Streets, 2407 Engomi, Nicosia
        mailing address: P. O. Box 24536, 1385
        Nicosia
        FAX: [357] (22) 393344

        Flag description:
        This entry provides a written flag
        description produced from actual flags or the best information
        available at the time the entry was written. The flags of
        independent states are used by their dependencies unless there is
        an officially recognized local flag. Some disputed and other areas
        do not have flags.

        centered on a white field
        is a copper-colored silhouette of the island (the island has long
        been famous for its copper deposits) above two olive-green-colored,
        crossed olive branches; the branches symbolize the hope for peace
        and reconciliation between the Greek and Turkish communities

        note: one of only two national flags that uses
        a map as a design element; the flag of Kosovo is the other
        note: the "Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus"
        flag retains the white field of the Cyprus national flag but
        displays narrow horizontal red stripes positioned a small distance
        from the top and bottom edges between which are centered a red
        crescent and a red five-pointed star; the banner is modeled after
        the Turkish national flag but with the colors reversed


        National symbol(s):
        A national symbol is a faunal,
        floral, or other abstract representation - or some distinctive
        object - that over time has come to be closely identified with a
        country or entity. Not all countries have national symbols; a few
        countries have more than one.

        Cypriot mouflon (wild
        sheep), white dove; national colors: blue, white

        National anthem:
        A generally patriotic musical
        composition - usually in the form of a song or hymn of praise -
        that evokes and eulogizes the history, traditions, or struggles of
        a nation or its people. National anthems can be officially
        recognized as a national song by a country's constitution or by an
        enacted law, or simply by tradition. Although most anthems contain
        lyrics, some do not.

        name: "Ymnos eis tin Eleftherian" (Hymn to
        Liberty)
        lyrics/music: Dionysios SOLOMOS/Nikolaos
        MANTZAROS

        note: adopted 1960; Cyprus adopted the Greek
        national anthem as its own; the Turkish Cypriot community in Cyprus
        uses the anthem of Turkey


    </government>
    <economy>

        The area of the Republic of Cyprus under government control has
        a market economy dominated by a services sector that accounts for
        more than four-fifths of GDP. Tourism, finance, shipping, and real
        estate have traditionally been the most important services. Cyprus
        has been a member of the EU since May 2004 and adopted the euro as
        its national currency in January 2008.
        During the first five years of EU membership, the Cyprus economy
        grew at an average rate of about 4%, with unemployment between 2004
        and 2008 averaging about 4%. However, the economy tipped into
        recession in 2009 as the ongoing global financial crisis and
        resulting low demand hit the tourism and construction sectors. An
        overextended banking sector with excessive exposure to Greek debt
        added to the contraction. Cyprus’ biggest two banks were among the
        largest holders of Greek bonds in Europe and had a substantial
        presence in Greece through bank branches and subsidiaries.
        Following numerous downgrades of its credit rating, Cyprus lost
        access to international capital markets in May 2011. In July 2012,
        Cyprus became the fifth euro-zone government to request an economic
        bailout program from the European Commission, European Central Bank
        and the International Monetary Fund - known collectively as the
        "Troika."
        Shortly after the election of President Nikos ANASTASIADES in
        February 2013, Cyprus reached an agreement with the Troika on a $13
        billion bailout that triggered a two-week bank closure and the
        imposition of capital controls that remained partially in place
        until April 2015. Cyprus' two largest banks merged and the combined
        entity was recapitalized through conversion of some large bank
        deposits to shares and imposition of losses on bank bondholders. As
        with other EU countries, the Troika conditioned the bailout on
        passing financial and structural reforms and privatizing
        state-owned enterprises. Despite downsizing and restructuring, the
        Cypriot financial sector remains burdened by the largest stock of
        non-performing loans in the euro zone, equal to nearly half of all
        loans. Since the bailout, Cyprus has received positive appraisals
        by the Troika and outperformed fiscal targets but has struggled to
        overcome political opposition to bailout-mandated legislation,
        particularly regarding privatizations. The rate of non-performing
        loans (NPLs) is still very high at around 49%, and growth would
        accelerate if Cypriot banks could increase the pace of resolution
        of the NPLs.
        In October 2013, a US-Israeli consortium completed preliminary
        appraisals of hydrocarbon deposits in Cyprus’ exclusive economic
        zone (EEZ), which estimated gross mean reserves of about 130
        billion cubic meters. Though exploration continues in Cyprus’ EEZ,
        no additional commercially exploitable reserves have been
        identified. Developing offshore hydrocarbon resources remains a
        critical component of the government’s economic recovery efforts,
        but development has been delayed as a result of regional
        developments and disagreements about exploitation methods.

        <gdp>
            $31.78 billion (2017 est.)
            $30.59 billion (2016 est.)
            $29.58 billion (2015 est.)

            note: data are in 2017 dollars

            country comparison to the world:
            129
        </gdp>
        <agriculture>
            agriculture: 2% (2017 est.)
            industry: 12.5% (2017 est.)
            services: 85.5% (2017 est.)
        </agriculture>
        <industries>
            tourism, food and beverage
            processing, cement and gypsum, ship repair and refurbishment,
            textiles, light chemicals, metal products, wood, paper, stone and
            clay products
        </industries>
        <uneployment>
            11.1% (2017 est.)
            13% (2016 est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            150
        </uneployment>
        <balance>
            -$1.458 billion (2017
            est.)
            -$984 million (2016 est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            154
        </balance>
        <budget>
            revenues: 8.663 billion (2017 est.)
            expenditures: 8.275 billion (2017 est.)
        </budget>
    </economy>
    <communications>
        general assessment: broadband market
        steadily developing with one of the highest penetrations rates in
        the region; despite the growth of Cyprus's telecom
        sector, the market overall continues to be dominated by the
        incumbent, Cyprus Telecommunications Authority (CyTA), which is
        still fully-owned by the state, but it is losing ground to its
        competition annually; improved regulatory
        circumstances, especially in relation to network
        interconnection and access, has given competing operators
        the certainty to invest in network infrastructure, and to
        launch competing services; fiber infrastructure in the early days
        and DSL remains the dominate access platform (2020)
        domestic: fixed-line is 25 per 100, and
         97 per 100 for mobile-cellular; open-wire, fiber-optic cable,
        and microwave radio relay (2018)
        international: country code - 357 (area
        administered by Turkish Cypriots uses the country code of Turkey -
        90); a number of submarine cables, including the SEA-ME-WE-3,
        CADMOS, MedNautilus Submarine System, POSEIDON, TE
        North/TGN-Eurasia/SEACOM/Alexandros/Medes, UGARIT, Aphrodite2,
        Hawk, Lev Submarine System, and Tamares combine to provide
        connectivity to Europe, the Middle East, Africa, Asia,
        Australia, and Southeast Asia; Turcyos-1 and Turcyos-2 submarine
        cable in Turkish North Cyprus link to Turkey; tropospheric scatter;
        satellite earth stations - 8 (3 Intelsat - 1 Atlantic Ocean and 2
        Indian Ocean, 2 Eutelsat, 2 Intersputnik, and 1 Arabsat)
        (2019)
        note: the COVID-19
        outbreak is negatively impacting telecommunications production and
        supply chains globally; consumer spending on telecom devices and
        services has also slowed due to the pandemic's effect on economies
        worldwide; overall progress towards improvements in all facets of
        the telecom industry - mobile, fixed-line, broadband, submarine
        cable and satellite - has moderated
        <static-telephones>
            total subscriptions: 311,559
            subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
            25 (2018 est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            112
        </static-telephones>
        <mobile-phones>
            total subscriptions: 1,200,378
            subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
            97 (2018 est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            158
        </mobile-phones>
        <broadcast-media>
            mixture of state and
            privately run TV and radio services; the public broadcaster
            operates 2 TV channels and 4 radio stations; 6 private TV
            broadcasters, satellite and cable TV services including telecasts
            from Greece and Turkey, and a number of private radio stations are
            available; in areas administered by Turkish Cypriots, there are 2
            public TV stations, 4 public radio stations, and 7 privately owned
            TV and 21 radio broadcast stations plus 6 radio and 4 TV channels
            of local universities, plus 1 radio station of military, security
            forces and 1 radio station of civil defense cooperation, as well as
            relay stations from Turkey (2019)
        </broadcast-media>
        <internet>
            total: 915,036
            percent of population: 75.9% (July 2016
            est.)
            country comparison to the world:
            134
        </internet>
    </communications>
    <military>
        the United Nations
        Peacekeeping Force in Cyprus (UNICYP) was set up in 1964 to prevent
        further fighting between the Greek Cypriot and Turkish Cypriot
        communities on the island and bring about a return to normal
        conditions;  as of October 2019, the UNICYP mission consisted
        of about 1,000 personnel
        <forces>
            Republic of Cyprus:
            Cypriot National Guard (Ethniki Froura, EF, includes ground, naval,
            and air elements) (2019)
        </forces>
        <obligation>
            Cypriot National Guard
            (CNG): 18-50 years of age for compulsory military service for all
            Greek Cypriot males; 17 years of age for voluntary service;
            14-month service obligation (2016)
        </obligation>
        <expenditures>
            1.6% of GDP (2019)
            1.8% of GDP (2018)
            1.6% of GDP (2017)
            1.4% of GDP (2016)
            1.7% of GDP (2015)
            country comparison to the world:
            70
        </expenditures>
    </military>
    <transportation>

        National air transport
        system: This entry includes four
        subfields describing the air transport system of a given country in
        terms of both structure and performance. The first subfield, number
        of registered air carriers, indicates the total number of air
        carriers registered with the country’s national aviation authority
        and issued an air operator certificate as required by the
        Convention on International Civil Aviation. The second subfield,
        inventory of registered aircraft operated by air carriers, lists
        the total number . . . more

        number of registered air carriers:
        2 (2015)
        inventory of registered aircraft operated by air
        carriers: 6
        (2015)
        annual passenger traffic on registered air
        carriers: 23,404
        (2015)
        annual freight traffic on registered air
        carriers: 230,600
        mt-km (2015)


        Civil aircraft registration
        country code prefix: This entry
        provides the one- or two-character alphanumeric code indicating the
        nationality of civil aircraft. Article 20 of the Convention on
        International Civil Aviation (Chicago Convention), signed in 1944,
        requires that all aircraft engaged in international air navigation
        bear appropriate nationality marks. The aircraft registration
        number consists of two parts: a prefix consisting of a one- or
        two-character alphanumeric code indicating nationality and a
        registration suffix of one to fi . . . more

        5B (2016)

        Airports: This entry gives the total number of airports or
        airfields recognizable from the air. The runway(s) may be paved
        (concrete or asphalt surfaces) or unpaved (grass, earth, sand, or
        gravel surfaces) and may include closed or abandoned installations.
        Airports or airfields that are no longer recognizable (overgrown,
        no facilities, etc.) are not included. Note that not all airports
        have accommodations for refueling, maintenance, or air traffic
        control.

        15 (2013)
        country comparison to the world:
        145


        Airports - with paved
        runways: This entry gives the
        total number of airports with paved runways (concrete or asphalt
        surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one runway, only
        the longest runway is included according to the following five
        groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2) 2,438 to 3,047 m
        (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000 to 8,000 ft), (4)
        914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under 914 m (under
        3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are included in this
        listing. Not all . . . more

        total: 13 (2017)
        2,438 to 3,047 m: 7 (2017)
        1,524 to 2,437 m: 2 (2017)
        914 to 1,523 m: 3 (2017)
        under 914 m: 1 (2017)


        Airports - with unpaved
        runways: This entry gives the
        total number of airports with unpaved runways (grass, dirt, sand,
        or gravel surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one
        runway, only the longest runway is included according to the
        following five groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2)
        2,438 to 3,047 m (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000
        to 8,000 ft), (4) 914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under
        914 m (under 3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are
        included in this listin . . . more

        total: 2 (2013)
        under 914 m: 2 (2013)

        Heliports: This entry gives the total number of heliports
        with hard-surface runways, helipads, or landing areas that support
        routine sustained helicopter operations exclusively and have
        support facilities including one or more of the following
        facilities: lighting, fuel, passenger handling, or maintenance. It
        includes former airports used exclusively for helicopter operations
        but excludes heliports limited to day operations and natural
        clearings that could support helicopter landings and
        takeoffs.

        9 (2013)

        Pipelines: This entry gives the lengths and types of
        pipelines for transporting products like natural gas, crude oil, or
        petroleum products.

        0 km oil

        Roadways: This entry gives the total length of the road
        network and includes the length of the paved and unpaved
        portions.

        total: 19,901
        km (2016)
        government control: 12,901 km (includes 272 km of expressways)
        (2016)
        paved: 8,631
        km (2016)
        unpaved: 4,270
        km (2016)
        Turkish Cypriot control: 7,000 km (2011)
        country comparison to the world:
        112

        Merchant marine:
        This entry provides the total and the
        number of each type of privately or publicly owned commercial ship
        for each country; military ships are not included; the five ships
        by type include: bulk carrier - for cargo such as coal, grain,
        cement, ores, and gravel; container ship - for loads in truck-size
        containers, a transportation system called containerization;
        general cargo - also referred to as break-bulk containers - for a
        wide variety of packaged merchandise, such as textiles, furniture .
        . . more


        total: 1,039
        by type: bulk carrier 304, container ship
        190, general cargo 183, oil tanker 42, other 320 (2019)
        country comparison to the world:
        25

        Ports and terminals:
        This entry lists major ports and
        terminals primarily on the basis of the amount of cargo tonnage
        shipped through the facilities on an annual basis. In some
        instances, the number of containers handled or ship visits were
        also considered. Most ports service multiple classes of vessels
        including bulk carriers (dry and liquid), break bulk cargoes (goods
        loaded individually in bags, boxes, crates, or drums; sometimes
        palletized), containers, roll-on/roll-off, and passenger ships. The
        listing le . . . more

        major seaport(s): area under government
        control: Larnaca, Limassol, Vasilikos
        area administered by Turkish
        Cypriots: Famagusta, Kyrenia

    </transportation>
</country>
