<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><country><name>Nepal</name><introduction>

During the late 18th-early 19th centuries, the principality of
Gorkha united many of the other principalities and states of the
sub-Himalayan region into a Nepali Kingdom. Nepal retained its
independence following the Anglo-Nepalese War of 1814-16 and the
subsequent peace treaty laid the foundations for two centuries of
amicable relations between Britain and Nepal. (The Brigade of
Gurkhas continues to serve in the British Army to the present day.)
In 1951, the Nepali monarch ended the century-old system of rule by
hereditary premiers and instituted a cabinet system that brought
political parties into the government. That arrangement lasted
until 1960, when political parties were again banned, but was
reinstated in 1990 with the establishment of a multiparty democracy
within the framework of a constitutional monarchy.
An insurgency led by Maoists broke out in 1996. During the
ensuing 10-year civil war between Maoist and government forces, the
monarchy dissolved the cabinet and parliament and re-assumed
absolute power in 2002, after the crown prince massacred the royal
family in 2001. A peace accord in 2006 led to the promulgation of
an interim constitution in 2007. Following a nationwide Constituent
Assembly (CA) election in 2008, the newly formed CA declared Nepal
a federal democratic republic, abolished the monarchy, and elected
the country's first president. After the CA failed to draft a
constitution by a 2012 deadline set by the Supreme Court,
then-Prime Minister Baburam BHATTARAI dissolved the CA. Months of
negotiations ensued until 2013 when the major political parties
agreed to create an interim government headed by then-Chief Justice
Khil Raj REGMI with a mandate to hold elections for a new CA.
Elections were held in 2013, in which the Nepali Congress (NC) won
the largest share of seats in the CA and in 2014 formed a coalition
government with the second-place Communist Party of Nepal-Unified
Marxist-Leninist (UML) with NC President Sushil KOIRALA serving as
prime minister. Nepal's new constitution came into effect in 2015,
at which point the CA became the Parliament. Khagda Prasad Sharma
OLI served as the first post-constitution prime minister from 2015
to 2016. OLI resigned ahead of a no-confidence motion against him,
and Parliament elected Communist Party of Nepal-Maoist (CPN-M)
leader Pushpa Kamal DAHAL (aka "Prachanda") prime minister. The
constitution provided for a transitional period during which three
sets of elections – local, provincial, and national – needed to
take place. The first local elections in 20 years occurred in three
phases between May and September 2017, and state and federal
elections proceeded in two phases in November and December 2017.
The parties headed by OLI and DAHAL ran in coalition and swept the
parliamentary elections, and OLI, who led the larger of the two
parties, was sworn in as prime minister in February 2018. In May
2018, OLI and DAHAL announced the merger of their parties - the UML
and CPN-M - to establish the Nepal Communist Party (NCP), which is
now the ruling party in Parliament.
 

</introduction><geography><location>
Southern Asia, between
China and India
</location><coordinates>
28 00 N, 84 00 E
</coordinates><map-references>
Asia
</map-references><area><total>147,181
sq km</total><land>143,351
sq km</land><water>3,830
sq km</water></area><climate>
varies from cool summers
and severe winters in north to subtropical summers and mild winters
in south
</climate></geography><people><population>
30,327,877 (July 2020
est.)
country comparison to the world:
46
</population><description/></people><government>
Country name: This entry includes all forms of the country's
name approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (Italy is used as
an example): conventional long form (Italian Republic),
conventional short form (Italy), local long form (Repubblica
Italiana), local short form (Italia), former (Kingdom of Italy), as
well as the abbreviation. Also see the Terminology
note. 

conventional long form: Federal Democratic
Republic of Nepal
conventional short form: Nepal
local long form: Sanghiya Loktantrik
Ganatantra Nepal
local short form: Nepal
etymology: the Newar people of the Kathmandu
Valley and surrounding areas apparently gave their name to the
country; the terms "Nepal," "Newar," "Nepar," and "Newal" are
phonetically different forms of the same word

Government type:
This entry gives the basic form of
government. Definitions of the major governmental terms are as
follows. (Note that for some countries more than one definition
applies.): Absolute monarchy - a form of government where the
monarch rules unhindered, i.e., without any laws, constitution, or
legally organized opposition. Anarchy - a condition of lawlessness
or political disorder brought about by the absence of governmental
authority. Authoritarian - a form of government in whic . . .
more


federal parliamentary
republic

Capital: This entry gives the name of the seat of
government, its geographic coordinates, the time difference
relative to Coordinated Universal Time (UTC) and the time observed
in Washington, DC, and, if applicable, information on daylight
saving time (DST). Where appropriate, a special note has been added
to highlight those countries that have multiple time
zones. 

name: Kathmandu
geographic coordinates: 27 43 N, 85 19
E
time difference: UTC+5.75 (10.75 hours ahead
of Washington, DC, during Standard Time)
etymology: name
derives from the Kasthamandap temple that stood in Durbar Square;
in Sanskrit, "kastha" means "wood" and "mandapa" means "pavilion";
the three-story structure was made entirely of wood, without iron
nails or supports, and dated to the late 16th century; it collapsed
during a 2015 earthquake

Administrative divisions:
This entry generally gives the
numbers, designatory terms, and first-order administrative
divisions as approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (BGN).
Changes that have been reported but not yet acted on by the BGN are
noted. Geographic names conform to spellings approved by the BGN
with the exception of the omission of diacritical marks and special
characters. 

7 provinces; Gandaki
Pradesh, Karnali Pradesh, Province No. One, Province No. Two,
Province No. Three, Province No. Five, Sudurpashchim Pradesh

Independence: For most countries, this entry gives the date
that sovereignty was achieved and from which nation, empire, or
trusteeship. For the other countries, the date given may not
represent "independence" in the strict sense, but rather some
significant nationhood event such as the traditional founding date
or the date of unification, federation, confederation,
establishment, fundamental change in the form of government, or
state succession. For a number of countries, the establishment of
statehood . . . more 

1768 (unified by Prithvi
Narayan SHAH)

National holiday:
This entry gives the primary national
day of celebration - usually independence day.


Constitution Day, 20
September (2015); note - marks the promulgation of Nepal’s
constitution in 2015 and replaces the previous 28 May Republic Day
as the official national day in Nepal; the Gregorian day fluctuates
based on Nepal’s Hindu calendar

Constitution: This entry provides information on a country’s
constitution and includes two subfields. The history subfield
includes the dates of previous constitutions and the main steps and
dates in formulating and implementing the latest constitution. For
countries with 1-3 previous constitutions, the years are listed;
for those with 4-9 previous, the entry is listed as “several
previous,” and for those with 10 or more, the entry is “many
previous.” The amendments subfield summarizes the process of am . .
. more


history: several previous; latest approved
by the Second Constituent Assembly 16 September 2015, signed by the
president and effective 20 September 2015
amendments: proposed as a bill by either
house of the Federal Parliament; bills affecting a state border or
powers delegated to a state must be submitted to the affected state
assembly; passage of such bills requires a majority vote of that
state assembly membership; bills not requiring state assembly
consent require at least two-thirds majority vote by the membership
of both houses of the Federal Parliament; parts of the constitution
on the sovereignty, territorial integrity, independence, and
sovereignty vested in the people cannot be amended; last amended
2016 (2019)

Legal system: This entry provides the description of a
country's legal system. A statement on judicial review of
legislative acts is also included for a number of countries. The
legal systems of nearly all countries are generally modeled upon
elements of five main types: civil law (including French law, the
Napoleonic Code, Roman law, Roman-Dutch law, and Spanish law);
common law (including United State law); customary law; mixed or
pluralistic law; and religious law (including Islamic law). An
addition . . . more 

English common law and
Hindu legal concepts; note - new criminal and civil codes came
into effect on 17 August 2018


International law organization
participation: This entry
includes information on a country's acceptance of jurisdiction of
the International Court of Justice (ICJ) and of the International
Criminal Court (ICCt); 59 countries have accepted ICJ jurisdiction
with reservations and 11 have accepted ICJ jurisdiction without
reservations; 122 countries have accepted ICCt jurisdiction.
Appendix B: International Organizations and Groups explains the
differing mandates of the ICJ and ICCt. 

has not submitted an ICJ
jurisdiction declaration; non-party state to the ICCt

Citizenship: This entry provides information related to the
acquisition and exercise of citizenship; it includes four
subfields: citizenship by birth describes the acquisition of
citizenship based on place of birth, known as Jus soli, regardless
of the citizenship of parents. citizenship by descent only
describes the acquisition of citizenship based on the principle of
Jus sanguinis, or by descent, where at least one parent is a
citizen of the state and being born within the territorial limits
of the s . . . more 

citizenship by birth: yes
citizenship by descent only: yes
dual citizenship recognized: no
residency requirement for naturalization: 15
years

Suffrage: This entry gives the age at enfranchisement and
whether the right to vote is universal or restricted.


18 years of age;
universal

Executive branch:
This entry includes five subentries:
chief of state; head of government; cabinet;
elections/appointments; election results. Chief of state includes
the name, title, and beginning date in office of the titular leader
of the country who represents the state at official and ceremonial
functions but may not be involved with the day-to-day activities of
the government. Head of government includes the name, title of the
top executive designated to manage the executive branch of the
government, a . . . more 

chief of state: President Bidhya Devi
BHANDARI (since October 2015)
head of government: Prime Minister Khadga
Prasad (KP) Sharma OLI (since 15 February 2018); deputy prime
ministers Ishwar POKHREL, Upendra YADAV (since 1 June 2018)
(an)
cabinet: Council of Ministers appointed by
the prime minister; cabinet dominated by the Nepal Communist
Party
elections/appointments: president indirectly
elected by an electoral college of the Federal Parliament and of
the state assemblies for a 5-year term (eligible for a second
term); election last held 13 March 2018 (next to be held in 2023);
prime minister indirectly elected by the Federal Parliament
election results: Bidhya Devi BHANDARI
reelected president; electoral vote - Bidhya Devi BHANDARI
(CPN-UML) 39,275, Kumari Laxmi RAI (NC) 11,730
head of state: President Bidhya Devi
BHANDARI (since 29 October 2015); Vice President Nanda Bahadar PUN
(since 31 October 2015)

Legislative branch:
This entry has three subfields. The
description subfield provides the legislative structure (unicameral
– single house; bicameral – an upper and a lower house); formal
name(s); number of member seats; types of constituencies or voting
districts (single seat, multi-seat, nationwide); electoral voting
system(s); and member term of office. The elections subfield
includes the dates of the last election and next election. The
election results subfield lists percent of vote by party/coalition
an . . . more 

description: bicameral Federal Parliament
consists of:
National Assembly (59 seats; 56 members, including at least 3
women, 1 Dalit, 1 member with disabilities, or 1 minority
indirectly elected by an electoral college of state and municipal
government leaders, and 3 members, including 1 woman, nominated by
the president of Nepal on the recommendation of the government;
members serve 6-year terms with renewal of one-third of the
membership every 2 years)
House of Representatives (275 seats; 165 members directly elected
in single-seat constituencies by simple majority vote and 110
members directly elected in a single nationwide constituency by
party-list proportional representation vote; members serve 5-year
terms)
elections:
first election for the National Assembly held on 7 February 2018
(next to be held in 2024)
first election for House of Representatives held on 26 November and
7 December 2017 (next to be held in 2022)
election results:
National Assembly - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party -
NCP 42, NC 13, FSFN 2, RJPN 2; composition - men 37, women 22,
percent of women 37.3%
House of Representatives - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by
party - NCP 174, NC 63, RJPN 17, FSFN 16, other 4, independent 1;
composition - men 185, women 90, percent of women 32.7%; note -
total Federal Parliament percent of women 33.5%

Judicial branch:
This entry includes three subfields.
The highest court(s) subfield includes the name(s) of a country's
highest level court(s), the number and titles of the judges, and
the types of cases heard by the court, which commonly are based on
civil, criminal, administrative, and constitutional law. A number
of countries have separate constitutional courts. The judge
selection and term of office subfield includes the organizations
and associated officials responsible for nominating and appointing
j . . . more 

highest courts: Supreme Court (consists of
the chief justice and up to 20 judges)
judge selection and term of office: Supreme
Court chief justice appointed by the president upon the
recommendation of the Constitutional Council, a 5-member,
high-level advisory body headed by the prime minister; other judges
appointed by the president upon the recommendation of the Judicial
Council, a 5-member advisory body headed by the chief justice; the
chief justice serves a 6-year term; judges serve until age 65
subordinate courts: High Court; district
courts


Political parties and
leaders: This entry includes a
listing of significant political parties, coalitions, and electoral
lists as of each country's last legislative election, unless
otherwise noted. 


the Election Commission of Nepal granted ballot access under the
proportional system to 88 political parties for the
November-December 2017 House of Representatives election to the
Federal Parliament; of these, the following 8 parties won
seats:
Federal Socialist Forum, Nepal or FSFN [Upendra YADAV]
Naya Shakti Party, Nepal [Baburam BHATTARAI]
Nepal Communist Party or NCP [Khadga Prasad OLI, Pushpa
Kamal DAHAL]
Nepali Congress or NC [Sher Bahadur DEUBA]
Nepal Mazdoor Kisan Party [Narayan Man BIJUKCHHE]
Rastriya Janamorcha [Chitra Bahadur K.C.]
Rastriya Janata Party or RJPN [Mahanta THAKUR]
Rastriya Prajatantra party or RPP [Kamal THAPA]



International organization
participation: This entry lists
in alphabetical order by abbreviation those international
organizations in which the subject country is a member or
participates in some other way. 

ADB, BIMSTEC, CD, CP, FAO,
G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC (NGOs), ICRM, IDA, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS,
ILO, IMF, IMO, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC
(NGOs), MIGA, MINURSO, MINUSMA, MINUSTAH, MONUSCO, NAM, OPCW,
SAARC, SACEP, UN, UNAMID, UNCTAD, UNDOF, UNESCO, UNIDO, UNIFIL,
UNMIL, UNMISS, UNOCI, UNTSO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU (NGOs), WHO,
WIPO, WMO, WTO


Diplomatic representation in
the US: This entry includes the
chief of mission, chancery address, telephone, FAX, consulate
general locations, and consulate locations. The use of the
annotated title Appointed Ambassador refers to a new ambassador who
has presented his/her credentials to the secretary of state but not
the US president. Such ambassadors fulfill all diplomatic functions
except meeting with or appearing at functions attended by the
president until such time as they formally present their
credentials at a White Hou . . . more 

Ambassador Arjun Kumar
KARKI (since 18 May 2015)
chancery: 2730 34th Place NW, Washington, DC
20007
telephone: [1] (202) 667-4550
FAX: [1] (202) 667-5534
consulate(s) general: Chicago (IL), New
York


Diplomatic representation from
the US: This entry includes the
chief of mission, embassy address, mailing address, telephone
number, FAX number, branch office locations, consulate general
locations, and consulate locations. 

chief of mission: Ambassador Randy BERRY
(since 25 October 2018)
telephone: [977] (1) 423-4000
embassy: Maharajgunj, Kathmandu, Nepal
mailing address: US Embassy, Maharajgunj
Chakrapath, Kathmandu, Nepal 44600
FAX: [977] (1) 400-7272

Flag description:
This entry provides a written flag
description produced from actual flags or the best information
available at the time the entry was written. The flags of
independent states are used by their dependencies unless there is
an officially recognized local flag. Some disputed and other areas
do not have flags. 

crimson red with a blue
border around the unique shape of two overlapping right triangles;
the smaller, upper triangle bears a white stylized moon and the
larger, lower triangle displays a white 12-pointed sun; the color
red represents the rhododendron (Nepal's national flower) and is a
sign of victory and bravery, the blue border signifies peace and
harmony; the two right triangles are a combination of two single
pennons (pennants) that originally symbolized the Himalaya
Mountains while their charges represented the families of the king
(upper) and the prime minister, but today they are understood to
denote Hinduism and Buddhism, the country's two main religions; the
moon represents the serenity of the Nepalese people and the shade
and cool weather in the Himalayas, while the sun depicts the heat
and higher temperatures of the lower parts of Nepal; the moon and
the sun are also said to express the hope that the nation will
endure as long as these heavenly bodies

note: Nepal is the only country in the world
whose flag is not rectangular or square


National symbol(s):
A national symbol is a faunal,
floral, or other abstract representation - or some distinctive
object - that over time has come to be closely identified with a
country or entity. Not all countries have national symbols; a few
countries have more than one. 

rhododendron blossom;
national color: red

National anthem:
A generally patriotic musical
composition - usually in the form of a song or hymn of praise -
that evokes and eulogizes the history, traditions, or struggles of
a nation or its people. National anthems can be officially
recognized as a national song by a country's constitution or by an
enacted law, or simply by tradition. Although most anthems contain
lyrics, some do not. 

name: "Sayaun Thunga Phool Ka" (Hundreds of
Flowers)
lyrics/music: Pradeep Kumar RAI/Ambar
GURUNG

note: adopted 2007; after the abolition of the
monarchy in 2006, a new anthem was required because of the previous
anthem's praise for the king



</government><economy>

Nepal is among the least developed countries in the world, with
about one-quarter of its population living below the poverty line.
Nepal is heavily dependent on remittances, which amount to as much
as 30% of GDP. Agriculture is the mainstay of the economy,
providing a livelihood for almost two-thirds of the population but
accounting for less than a third of GDP. Industrial activity mainly
involves the processing of agricultural products, including pulses,
jute, sugarcane, tobacco, and grain.
Nepal has considerable scope for exploiting its potential in
hydropower, with an estimated 42,000 MW of commercially feasible
capacity. Nepal has signed trade and investment agreements with
India, China, and other countries, but political uncertainty and a
difficult business climate have hampered foreign investment. The
United States and Nepal signed a $500 million Millennium Challenge
Corporation Compact in September 2017 which will expand Nepal’s
electricity infrastructure and help maintain transportation
infrastructure.
Massive earthquakes struck Nepal in early 2015, which damaged or
destroyed infrastructure and homes and set back economic
development. Although political gridlock and lack of capacity have
hindered post-earthquake recovery, government-led reconstruction
efforts have progressively picked up speed, although many hard hit
areas still have seen little assistance. Additional challenges to
Nepal's growth include its landlocked geographic location,
inconsistent electricity supply, and underdeveloped transportation
infrastructure.

</economy></country>