<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><country><name>Yemen</name><introduction>

The Kingdom of Yemen (colloquially known as North Yemen) became
independent from the Ottoman Empire in 1918 and in 1962 became the
Yemen Arab Republic. The British, who had set up a protectorate
area around the southern port of Aden in the 19th century, withdrew
in 1967 from what became the People's Republic of Southern Yemen
(colloquially known as South Yemen). Three years later, the
southern government adopted a Marxist orientation and changed the
country's name to the People's Democratic Republic of Yemen. The
massive exodus of hundreds of thousands of Yemenis from the south
to the north contributed to two decades of hostility between the
states. The two countries were formally unified as the Republic of
Yemen in 1990. A southern secessionist movement and brief civil war
in 1994 was quickly subdued. In 2000, Saudi Arabia and Yemen agreed
to delineate their border.
Fighting in the northwest between the government and the Huthis,
a Zaydi Shia Muslim minority, continued intermittently from 2004 to
2010, and then again from 2014-present. The southern secessionist
movement was revitalized in 2007.
Public rallies in Sana'a against then President Ali Abdallah
SALIH - inspired by similar demonstrations in Tunisia and Egypt -
slowly built momentum starting in late January 2011 fueled by
complaints over high unemployment, poor economic conditions, and
corruption. By the following month, some protests had resulted in
violence, and the demonstrations had spread to other major cities.
By March the opposition had hardened its demands and was unifying
behind calls for SALIH's immediate ouster. In April 2011, the Gulf
Cooperation Council (GCC), in an attempt to mediate the crisis in
Yemen, proposed the GCC Initiative, an agreement in which the
president would step down in exchange for immunity from
prosecution. SALIH's refusal to sign an agreement led to further
violence. The UN Security Council passed Resolution 2014 in October
2011 calling for an end to the violence and completing a power
transfer deal. In November 2011, SALIH signed the GCC Initiative to
step down and to transfer some of his powers to Vice President Abd
Rabuh Mansur HADI. Following HADI's uncontested election victory in
February 2012, SALIH formally transferred all presidential powers.
In accordance with the GCC Initiative, Yemen launched a National
Dialogue Conference (NDC) in March 2013 to discuss key
constitutional, political, and social issues. HADI concluded the
NDC in January 2014 and planned to begin implementing subsequent
steps in the transition process, including constitutional drafting,
a constitutional referendum, and national elections.
The Huthis, perceiving their grievances were not addressed in
the NDC, joined forces with SALIH and expanded their influence in
northwestern Yemen, which culminated in a major offensive against
military units and rival tribes and enabled their forces to overrun
the capital, Sanaa, in September 2014. In January 2015, the Huthis
surrounded the presidential palace, HADI's residence, and key
government facilities, prompting HADI and the cabinet to submit
their resignations. HADI fled to Aden in February 2015 and
rescinded his resignation. He subsequently escaped to Oman and then
moved to Saudi Arabia and asked the GCC to intervene militarily in
Yemen to protect the legitimate government from the Huthis. In
March, Saudi Arabia assembled a coalition of Arab militaries and
began airstrikes against the Huthis and Huthi-affiliated forces.
Ground fighting between Huthi-aligned forces and anti-Huthi groups
backed by the Saudi-led coalition continued through 2016. In 2016,
the UN brokered a months-long cessation of hostilities that reduced
airstrikes and fighting, and initiated peace talks in Kuwait.
However, the talks ended without agreement. The Huthis and SALIH’s
political party announced a Supreme Political Council in August
2016 and a National Salvation Government, including a prime
minister and several dozen cabinet members, in November 2016, to
govern in Sanaa and further challenge the legitimacy of HADI’s
government. However, amid rising tensions between the Huthis and
SALIH, sporadic clashes erupted in mid-2017, and escalated into
open fighting that ended when Huthi forces killed SALIH in early
December 2017. In 2018, anti-Huthi forces made the most battlefield
progress in Yemen since early 2016, most notably in Al Hudaydah
Governorate. In December 2018, the Huthis and Yemeni Government
participated in the first UN-brokered peace talks since 2016,
agreeing to a limited ceasefire in Al Hudaydah Governorate and the
establishment of a UN Mission to monitor the agreement. In April
2019, Yemen’s parliament convened in Say'un for the first time
since the conflict broke out in 2014. In August 2019, violence
erupted between HADI's government and the pro-secessionist Southern
Transition Council (STC) in southern Yemen. In November 2019,
HADI's government and the STC signed a power-sharing agreement to
end the fighting between them.

</introduction><geography>Geography - note:
This entry includes miscellaneous
geographic information of significance not included
elsewhere. <location>
Middle East, bordering the
Arabian Sea, Gulf of Aden, and Red Sea, between Oman and Saudi
Arabia
</location><coordinates>
15 00 N, 48 00 E
</coordinates><map-references>
Middle East
</map-references><area><total>527,968
sq km</total><land>527,968
sq km</land><water>0 sq
km</water></area><climate>
mostly desert; hot and
humid along west coast; temperate in western mountains affected by
seasonal monsoon; extraordinarily hot, dry, harsh desert in
east
</climate><natural-hazards>

sandstorms and dust storms in summer
volcanism: limited volcanic activity; Jebel at
Tair (Jabal al-Tair, Jebel Teir, Jabal al-Tayr, Jazirat at-Tair)
(244 m), which forms an island in the Red Sea, erupted in 2007
after awakening from dormancy; other historically active volcanoes
include Harra of Arhab, Harras of Dhamar, Harra es-Sawad, and Jebel
Zubair, although many of these have not erupted in over a
century

</natural-hazards><population-distribution>
the vast majority of the
population is found in the Asir Mountains (part of the larger
Sarawat Mountain system), located in the far western region of the
country
</population-distribution></geography><people><population>
29,884,405 (July 2020
est.)
country comparison to the world:
48
</population><age-structure>
</age-structure><urbanization>
urban population: 37.9% of total population (2020)
rate of urbanization: 4.06% annual rate of change (2015-20 est.)
</urbanization><distribution>
the vast majority of the
population is found in the Asir Mountains (part of the larger
Sarawat Mountain system), located in the far western region of the
country
</distribution></people><government>
Country name: This entry includes all forms of the country's
name approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (Italy is used as
an example): conventional long form (Italian Republic),
conventional short form (Italy), local long form (Repubblica
Italiana), local short form (Italia), former (Kingdom of Italy), as
well as the abbreviation. Also see the Terminology
note. 

conventional long form: Republic of
Yemen
conventional short form: Yemen
local long form: Al Jumhuriyah al
Yamaniyah
local short form: Al Yaman
former: Yemen Arab Republic [Yemen (Sanaa)
or North Yemen] and People's Democratic Republic of Yemen [Yemen
(Aden) or South Yemen]
etymology: name derivation remains unclear
but may come from the Arab term "yumn" (happiness) and be related
to the region's classical name "Arabia Felix" (Fertile or Happy
Arabia); the Romans referred to the rest of the peninsula as
"Arabia Deserta" (Deserted Arabia)

Government type:
This entry gives the basic form of
government. Definitions of the major governmental terms are as
follows. (Note that for some countries more than one definition
applies.): Absolute monarchy - a form of government where the
monarch rules unhindered, i.e., without any laws, constitution, or
legally organized opposition. Anarchy - a condition of lawlessness
or political disorder brought about by the absence of governmental
authority. Authoritarian - a form of government in whic . . .
more


in transition

Capital: This entry gives the name of the seat of
government, its geographic coordinates, the time difference
relative to Coordinated Universal Time (UTC) and the time observed
in Washington, DC, and, if applicable, information on daylight
saving time (DST). Where appropriate, a special note has been added
to highlight those countries that have multiple time
zones. 

name: Sanaa
geographic coordinates: 15 21 N, 44 12
E
time difference: UTC+3 (8 hours ahead of
Washington, DC, during Standard Time)
etymology: the
name is reputed to mean "well-fortified" in Sabaean, the South
Arabian language that went extinct in Yemen in the 6th century
A.D.

Administrative divisions:
This entry generally gives the
numbers, designatory terms, and first-order administrative
divisions as approved by the US Board on Geographic Names (BGN).
Changes that have been reported but not yet acted on by the BGN are
noted. Geographic names conform to spellings approved by the BGN
with the exception of the omission of diacritical marks and special
characters. 

22 governorates
(muhafazat, singular - muhafazah); Abyan, 'Adan (Aden), Ad Dali',
Al Bayda', Al Hudaydah, Al Jawf, Al Mahrah, Al Mahwit, Amanat al
'Asimah (Sanaa City), 'Amran, Arkhabil Suqutra (Socotra
Archipelago), Dhamar, Hadramawt, Hajjah, Ibb, Lahij, Ma'rib,
Raymah, Sa'dah, San'a' (Sanaa), Shabwah, Ta'izz

Independence: For most countries, this entry gives the date
that sovereignty was achieved and from which nation, empire, or
trusteeship. For the other countries, the date given may not
represent "independence" in the strict sense, but rather some
significant nationhood event such as the traditional founding date
or the date of unification, federation, confederation,
establishment, fundamental change in the form of government, or
state succession. For a number of countries, the establishment of
statehood . . . more 

22 May 1990 (Republic of
Yemen was established with the merger of the Yemen Arab Republic
[Yemen (Sanaa) or North Yemen] and the Marxist-dominated People's
Democratic Republic of Yemen [Yemen (Aden) or South Yemen]);
notable earlier dates: North Yemen became independent on 1 November
1918 (from the Ottoman Empire) and became a republic with the
overthrow of the theocratic Imamate on 27 September 1962; South
Yemen became independent on 30 November 1967 (from the UK)

National holiday:
This entry gives the primary national
day of celebration - usually independence day.


Unification Day, 22 May
(1990)

Constitution: This entry provides information on a country’s
constitution and includes two subfields. The history subfield
includes the dates of previous constitutions and the main steps and
dates in formulating and implementing the latest constitution. For
countries with 1-3 previous constitutions, the years are listed;
for those with 4-9 previous, the entry is listed as “several
previous,” and for those with 10 or more, the entry is “many
previous.” The amendments subfield summarizes the process of am . .
. more


history: adopted by referendum 16 May 1991
(following unification); note - after the National  Dialogue
ended in January 2015, a Constitutional Drafting Committee
appointed by the president worked to prepare a new draft
constitution that was expected to be put to a national referendum
before being adopted; however, the start of the current conflict in
early 2015 interrupted the process
amendments: amended several times, last in
2009

Legal system: This entry provides the description of a
country's legal system. A statement on judicial review of
legislative acts is also included for a number of countries. The
legal systems of nearly all countries are generally modeled upon
elements of five main types: civil law (including French law, the
Napoleonic Code, Roman law, Roman-Dutch law, and Spanish law);
common law (including United State law); customary law; mixed or
pluralistic law; and religious law (including Islamic law). An
addition . . . more 

mixed legal system of
Islamic (sharia) law, Napoleonic law, English common law, and
customary law


International law organization
participation: This entry
includes information on a country's acceptance of jurisdiction of
the International Court of Justice (ICJ) and of the International
Criminal Court (ICCt); 59 countries have accepted ICJ jurisdiction
with reservations and 11 have accepted ICJ jurisdiction without
reservations; 122 countries have accepted ICCt jurisdiction.
Appendix B: International Organizations and Groups explains the
differing mandates of the ICJ and ICCt. 

has not submitted an ICJ
jurisdiction declaration; non-party state to the ICCt

Citizenship: This entry provides information related to the
acquisition and exercise of citizenship; it includes four
subfields: citizenship by birth describes the acquisition of
citizenship based on place of birth, known as Jus soli, regardless
of the citizenship of parents. citizenship by descent only
describes the acquisition of citizenship based on the principle of
Jus sanguinis, or by descent, where at least one parent is a
citizen of the state and being born within the territorial limits
of the s . . . more 

citizenship by birth: no
citizenship by descent only: the father must
be a citizen of Yemen; if the father is unknown, the mother must be
a citizen
dual citizenship recognized: no
residency requirement for naturalization: 10
years

Suffrage: This entry gives the age at enfranchisement and
whether the right to vote is universal or restricted.


18 years of age;
universal

Executive branch:
This entry includes five subentries:
chief of state; head of government; cabinet;
elections/appointments; election results. Chief of state includes
the name, title, and beginning date in office of the titular leader
of the country who represents the state at official and ceremonial
functions but may not be involved with the day-to-day activities of
the government. Head of government includes the name, title of the
top executive designated to manage the executive branch of the
government, a . . . more 

chief of state: President Abd Rabuh Mansur
HADI (since 21 February 2012); Vice President ALI MUHSIN al-Ahmar,
Lt. Gen. (since 3 April 2016)
head of government: Prime Minister Maeen Abd
al-Malik SAEED (since 15 October 2018)
cabinet: appointed by the president
elections/appointments: president directly
elected by absolute majority popular vote in 2 rounds if needed for
a 7-year term (eligible for a second term); election last held on
21 February 2012 (next election NA); note - a special election was
held on 21 February 2012 to remove Ali Abdallah SALIH under the
terms of a Gulf Cooperation Council-mediated deal during the
political crisis of 2011; vice president appointed by the
president; prime minister appointed by the president
election results: Abd Rabuh Mansur HADI
(GPC) elected as a consensus president with about 50% popular
participation; no other candidates

Legislative branch:
This entry has three subfields. The
description subfield provides the legislative structure (unicameral
– single house; bicameral – an upper and a lower house); formal
name(s); number of member seats; types of constituencies or voting
districts (single seat, multi-seat, nationwide); electoral voting
system(s); and member term of office. The elections subfield
includes the dates of the last election and next election. The
election results subfield lists percent of vote by party/coalition
an . . . more 

description: bicameral Parliament or Majlis
consists of:
Shura Council or Majlis Alshoora (111 seats; members appointed by
the president; member tenure NA)
House of Representatives or Majlis al Nuwaab (301 seats; members
directly elected in single-seat constituencies by simple majority
vote to serve 6-year terms)
elections:
House of Representatives - last held on 27 April 2003 (next
scheduled for April 2009 but postponed indefinitely)
election results:
percent of vote by party - GPC 58.0%, Islah 22.6%, YSP 3.8%,
Unionist Party 1.9%, other 13.7%; seats by party - GPC 238, Islah
46, YSP 8, Nasserist Unionist Party 3, National Arab Socialist
Ba'ath Party 2, independent 4

Judicial branch:
This entry includes three subfields.
The highest court(s) subfield includes the name(s) of a country's
highest level court(s), the number and titles of the judges, and
the types of cases heard by the court, which commonly are based on
civil, criminal, administrative, and constitutional law. A number
of countries have separate constitutional courts. The judge
selection and term of office subfield includes the organizations
and associated officials responsible for nominating and appointing
j . . . more 

highest courts: Supreme Court (consists of
the court president, 2 deputies, and nearly 50 judges; court
organized into constitutional, civil, commercial, family,
administrative, criminal, military, and appeals scrutiny
divisions)
judge selection and term of office: judges
appointed by the Supreme Judicial Council, which is chaired by the
president of the republic and includes 10 high-ranking judicial
officers; judges serve for life with mandatory retirement at age
65
subordinate courts: appeal courts; district
or first instance courts; commercial courts


Political parties and
leaders: This entry includes a
listing of significant political parties, coalitions, and electoral
lists as of each country's last legislative election, unless
otherwise noted. 

General People’s Congress
or GPC (3 factions: pro-Hadi [Abdrabbi Mansur HADI], pro-Houthi
[Sadeq Ameen Abu RAS], pro-Saleh [Ahmed SALEH]
National Arab Socialist Ba'ath Party [Qassem Salam SAID]
Nasserist Unionist People's Organization [Abdulmalik
al-MEKHLAFI]
Southern Transitional Council or STC [Aidarus al-ZOUBAIDA]
Yemeni Reform Grouping or Islah [Muhammed Abdallah al-YADUMI]
Yemeni Socialist Party or YSP [Dr. Abd al-Rahman Umar
al-SAQQAF]
(


International organization
participation: This entry lists
in alphabetical order by abbreviation those international
organizations in which the subject country is a member or
participates in some other way. 

AFESD, AMF, CAEU, CD, EITI
(temporarily suspended), FAO, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICRM, IDA,
IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, IMO, IMSO, Interpol, IOC, IOM,
IPU, ISO, ITSO, ITU, ITUC (NGOs), LAS, MIGA, MINURSO, MINUSMA,
MONUSCO, NAM, OAS (observer), OIC, OPCW, UN, UNAMID, UNCTAD,
UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNISFA, UNMIL, UNMIS, UNOCI, UNWTO, UPU, WCO,
WFTU (NGOs), WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO


Diplomatic representation in
the US: This entry includes the
chief of mission, chancery address, telephone, FAX, consulate
general locations, and consulate locations. The use of the
annotated title Appointed Ambassador refers to a new ambassador who
has presented his/her credentials to the secretary of state but not
the US president. Such ambassadors fulfill all diplomatic functions
except meeting with or appearing at functions attended by the
president until such time as they formally present their
credentials at a White Hou . . . more 

Ambassador Ahmad Awadh BIN
MUBARAK (since 3 August 2015)
chancery: 2319 Wyoming Avenue NW,
Washington, DC 20008
telephone: [1] (202) 965-4760
FAX: [1] (202) 337-2017


Diplomatic representation from
the US: This entry includes the
chief of mission, embassy address, mailing address, telephone
number, FAX number, branch office locations, consulate general
locations, and consulate locations. 

chief of mission: Ambassador Christopher
HENZEL (since 20 May 2019); note - the embassy closed in March
2015; Yemen Affairs Unit currently operates out of US Embassy
Riyadh
telephone: US Embassy Riyadh [966]
11-488-3800
embassy: Sa'awan Street, Sanaa
mailing address:
US Embassy Riyadh

FAX: US Embassy Riyadh [966]
11-488-7360

Flag description:
This entry provides a written flag
description produced from actual flags or the best information
available at the time the entry was written. The flags of
independent states are used by their dependencies unless there is
an officially recognized local flag. Some disputed and other areas
do not have flags. 

three equal horizontal
bands of red (top), white, and black; the band colors derive from
the Arab Liberation flag and represent oppression (black), overcome
through bloody struggle (red), to be replaced by a bright future
(white)

note: similar to the flag of Syria, which has
two green stars in the white band, and of Iraq, which has an Arabic
inscription centered in the white band; also similar to the flag of
Egypt, which has a heraldic eagle centered in the white band


National symbol(s):
A national symbol is a faunal,
floral, or other abstract representation - or some distinctive
object - that over time has come to be closely identified with a
country or entity. Not all countries have national symbols; a few
countries have more than one. 

golden eagle; national
colors: red, white, black

National anthem:
A generally patriotic musical
composition - usually in the form of a song or hymn of praise -
that evokes and eulogizes the history, traditions, or struggles of
a nation or its people. National anthems can be officially
recognized as a national song by a country's constitution or by an
enacted law, or simply by tradition. Although most anthems contain
lyrics, some do not. 

name: "al-qumhuriyatu l-muttahida" (United
Republic)
lyrics/music: Abdullah Abdulwahab
NOA'MAN/Ayyoab Tarish ABSI

note: adopted 1990; the music first served as
the anthem for South Yemen before unification with North Yemen in
1990



</government><economy>

Yemen is a low-income country that faces difficult long-term
challenges to stabilizing and growing its economy, and the current
conflict has only exacerbated those issues. The ongoing war has
halted Yemen’s exports, pressured the currency’s exchange rate,
accelerated inflation, severely limited food and fuel imports, and
caused widespread damage to infrastructure. The conflict has also
created a severe humanitarian crisis - the world’s largest cholera
outbreak currently at nearly 1 million cases, more than 7 million
people at risk of famine, and more than 80% of the population in
need of humanitarian assistance.
Prior to the start of the conflict in 2014, Yemen was highly
dependent on declining oil and gas resources for revenue. Oil and
gas earnings accounted for roughly 25% of GDP and 65% of government
revenue. The Yemeni Government regularly faced annual budget
shortfalls and tried to diversify the Yemeni economy through a
reform program designed to bolster non-oil sectors of the economy
and foreign investment. In July 2014, the government continued
reform efforts by eliminating some fuel subsidies and in August
2014, the IMF approved a three-year, $570 million Extended Credit
Facility for Yemen.
However, the conflict that began in 2014 stalled these reform
efforts and ongoing fighting continues to accelerate the country’s
economic decline. In September 2016, President HADI announced the
move of the main branch of Central Bank of Yemen from Sanaa to Aden
where his government could exert greater control over the central
bank’s dwindling resources. Regardless of which group controls the
main branch, the central bank system is struggling to function.
Yemen’s Central Bank’s foreign reserves, which stood at roughly
$5.2 billion prior to the conflict, have declined to negligible
amounts. The Central Bank can no longer fully support imports of
critical goods or the country’s exchange rate. The country also is
facing a growing liquidity crisis and rising inflation. The private
sector is hemorrhaging, with almost all businesses making
substantial layoffs. Access to food and other critical commodities
such as medical equipment is limited across the country due to
security issues on the ground. The Social Welfare Fund, a cash
transfer program for Yemen’s neediest, is no longer operational and
has not made any disbursements since late 2014.
Yemen will require significant international assistance during
and after the protracted conflict to stabilize its economy.
Long-term challenges include a high population growth rate, high
unemployment, declining water resources, and severe food
scarcity.

<gdp>
$73.63 billion (2017 est.)
$78.28 billion (2016 est.)
$90.63 billion (2015 est.)

note: data are in 2017 dollars

country comparison to the world:
98
</gdp><agriculture>
agriculture: 20.3% (2017 est.)
industry: 11.8% (2017 est.)
services: 67.9% (2017 est.)
</agriculture><industries>
crude oil production and
petroleum refining; small-scale production of cotton textiles,
leather goods; food processing; handicrafts; aluminum products;
cement; commercial ship repair; natural gas production
</industries><uneployment>
27% (2014 est.)
35% (2003 est.)
country comparison to the world:
198
</uneployment><balance>
-$1.236 billion (2017
est.)
-$1.868 billion (2016
est.)
country comparison to the world:
149
</balance><budget>
revenues: 2.821 billion (2017 est.)
expenditures: 4.458 billion (2017 est.)
</budget></economy><communications>
general assessment: due to 75% of
population needing humanitarian assistance, and given the
civil conflict, telecommunications services are vital but
disrupted; mobile towers are often deliberately targeted;
maintenance is dangerous to staff; aid organization rely on
satellite and radio communications; scarcity of telecommunications
equipment in rural areas (2018)
domestic: the national network consists of
microwave radio relay, cable, tropospheric scatter, GSM and CDMA
mobile-cellular telephone systems; fixed-line teledensity remains
low by regional standards at 4 per 100 but mobile cellular use
expanding at 53 per 100 (2018)
international: country code - 967; landing
points for the FALCON, SeaMeWe-5, Aden-Djibouti, and the AAE-1
international submarine cable connecting Europe, Africa, the Middle
East, Asia and Southeast Asia; satellite earth stations - 3
Intelsat (2 Indian Ocean and 1 Atlantic Ocean), 1 Intersputnik
(Atlantic Ocean region), and 2 Arabsat; microwave radio relay to
Saudi Arabia and Djibouti (2020)
<static-telephones>
total subscriptions: 1,165,828
subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
4 (July 2016
est.)
country comparison to the world:
73
</static-telephones><mobile-phones>
total subscriptions: 15,297,789
subscriptions per 100 inhabitants:
53 (2018 est.)
country comparison to the world:
67
</mobile-phones><broadcast-media>
state-run TV with 2
stations; state-run radio with 2 national radio stations and 5
local stations; stations from Oman and Saudi Arabia can be
accessed
</broadcast-media><internet>
total: 6,732,928
percent of population: 24.6% (July 2016
est.)
country comparison to the world:
64
</internet></communications><military><forces>
Land Forces (includes
seven Military Regional Commands, supported by Strategic Reserve
Units), Naval and Coastal Defense Forces (includes Navy Infantry or
Marine units and Coast Guard), Air and Air Defense Force (although
it still exists in name, in practice many of the officers and
soldiers in this branch have been distributed to other military
branches and jobs), Border Guards, Strategic Reserve Forces
(supports the Land Forces at the discretion of the Armed Forces
Commander-in-Chief and also includes a Missile Group, Presidential
Protection Brigades, and Special Operations Forces), Minister of
Defense Intelligence Authority (consists of the Department of
Military Intelligence [active], Department of Reconnaissance
[active], Department of Military Security [inactive], and the
Electronic Warfare Department [inactive]) (2018)
</forces><obligation>
18 is the legal minimum
age for voluntary military service; no conscription; 2-year service
obligation (2018)
</obligation><expenditures>
3.98% of GDP (2014)
4.08% of GDP (2013)
4.57% of GDP (2012)
4.19% of GDP (2011)

note - no reliable information exists following the start of
renewed conflict in 2015

country comparison to the world:
13
</expenditures></military><transportation>

National air transport
system: This entry includes four
subfields describing the air transport system of a given country in
terms of both structure and performance. The first subfield, number
of registered air carriers, indicates the total number of air
carriers registered with the country’s national aviation authority
and issued an air operator certificate as required by the
Convention on International Civil Aviation. The second subfield,
inventory of registered aircraft operated by air carriers, lists
the total number . . . more 

number of registered air carriers:
2 (2015)
inventory of registered aircraft operated by air
carriers: 10
(2015)
annual passenger traffic on registered air
carriers: 1,387,999
(2015)
annual freight traffic on registered air
carriers: 0
mt-km (2015)


Civil aircraft registration
country code prefix: This entry
provides the one- or two-character alphanumeric code indicating the
nationality of civil aircraft. Article 20 of the Convention on
International Civil Aviation (Chicago Convention), signed in 1944,
requires that all aircraft engaged in international air navigation
bear appropriate nationality marks. The aircraft registration
number consists of two parts: a prefix consisting of a one- or
two-character alphanumeric code indicating nationality and a
registration suffix of one to fi . . . more 

7O (2016)

Airports: This entry gives the total number of airports or
airfields recognizable from the air. The runway(s) may be paved
(concrete or asphalt surfaces) or unpaved (grass, earth, sand, or
gravel surfaces) and may include closed or abandoned installations.
Airports or airfields that are no longer recognizable (overgrown,
no facilities, etc.) are not included. Note that not all airports
have accommodations for refueling, maintenance, or air traffic
control. 

57 (2013)
country comparison to the world:
83


Airports - with paved
runways: This entry gives the
total number of airports with paved runways (concrete or asphalt
surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one runway, only
the longest runway is included according to the following five
groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2) 2,438 to 3,047 m
(8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000 to 8,000 ft), (4)
914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under 914 m (under
3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are included in this
listing. Not all . . . more 

total: 17 (2013)
over 3,047 m: 4 (2013)
2,438 to 3,047 m: 9 (2013)
1,524 to 2,437 m: 3 (2013)
914 to 1,523 m: 1 (2013)


Airports - with unpaved
runways: This entry gives the
total number of airports with unpaved runways (grass, dirt, sand,
or gravel surfaces) by length. For airports with more than one
runway, only the longest runway is included according to the
following five groups - (1) over 3,047 m (over 10,000 ft), (2)
2,438 to 3,047 m (8,000 to 10,000 ft), (3) 1,524 to 2,437 m (5,000
to 8,000 ft), (4) 914 to 1,523 m (3,000 to 5,000 ft), and (5) under
914 m (under 3,000 ft). Only airports with usable runways are
included in this listin . . . more 

total: 40 (2013)
over 3,047 m: 3 (2013)
2,438 to 3,047 m: 5 (2013)
1,524 to 2,437 m: 7 (2013)
914 to 1,523 m: 16 (2013)
under 914 m: 9 (2013)

Pipelines: This entry gives the lengths and types of
pipelines for transporting products like natural gas, crude oil, or
petroleum products. 

641 km gas, 22 km liquid
petroleum gas, 1370 km oil (2013)

Roadways: This entry gives the total length of the road
network and includes the length of the paved and unpaved
portions. 

total: 71,300
km (2005)
paved: 6,200
km (2005)
unpaved: 65,100 km (2005)
country comparison to the world:
68

Merchant marine:
This entry provides the total and the
number of each type of privately or publicly owned commercial ship
for each country; military ships are not included; the five ships
by type include: bulk carrier - for cargo such as coal, grain,
cement, ores, and gravel; container ship - for loads in truck-size
containers, a transportation system called containerization;
general cargo - also referred to as break-bulk containers - for a
wide variety of packaged merchandise, such as textiles, furniture .
. . more


total: 34
by type: general cargo 3, oil tanker 4,
other 27 (2019)
country comparison to the world:
128

Ports and terminals:
This entry lists major ports and
terminals primarily on the basis of the amount of cargo tonnage
shipped through the facilities on an annual basis. In some
instances, the number of containers handled or ship visits were
also considered. Most ports service multiple classes of vessels
including bulk carriers (dry and liquid), break bulk cargoes (goods
loaded individually in bags, boxes, crates, or drums; sometimes
palletized), containers, roll-on/roll-off, and passenger ships. The
listing le . . . more 

major seaport(s): Aden, Al Hudaydah, Al
Mukalla

</transportation></country>